welcome to the fourth in our series of
ce teachers i'm john shattuck
the president and director of central
european university and it's my great
privilege
throughout this week to
host five lectures by george soros
held here in budapest at the hungarian
academy of sciences
under the auspices of european
university
in his lecture today mr soros will build
on the concept of open society that he
outlined yesterday
and he will explore the conflict between
capitalism and open society and between
market values
and
social values he will continue his
challenge to market fundamentalism while
presenting his ideas for protecting the
public good all the ceu lectures this
week are being video conference to
universities on several continents
creating an unprecedented
global
real-time audience of students
today's lecture will include students
from fudan university in shanghai whom
you will meet in a few moments
in addition to the invited guests and
ceu students who are here in budapest
our moderator today is mark danner an
award-winning
american journalist and commentator on
foreign affairs politics and human
rights
as he has in previous lectures mr soros
will speak for approximately 50 minutes
following which mr danner will offer his
own brief commentary mr soros will then
take questions starting with three
questions from shanghai from the
students at fudon university
and then further questions from all of
you here in budapest
now to deliver his fourth lecture i'm
delighted once again to introduce george
soros whose extraordinary performance
over the last three days provides the
best possible introduction to what he
will tell us this afternoon
thank you
today
i want to explore the conflict between
capitalism
and open society
market values
and social values
but i'm going to approach the subject
indirectly
and by first introducing
introducing a phenomenon
that has attracted my attention only
recently but has assumed such importance
in my thinking
that i am
almost inclined to call it the fourth
pillar of my conceptual framework
that phenomenon is the principal agent
problem
agents
are supposed to represent the interests
of their principles
but in fact
they tend to put their own interests
ahead of the interests of those whom
they are supposed to represent that's
the agency problem
it's been extensively analyzed by
economists
but they look at it exclusively in terms
of contracts and incentives
and they largely disregard questions of
ethics and values
yet
if you leave
the ethical consideration out
the problem becomes pretty well
intractable
values like honesty and integrity lose
their grip
on people's behavior and people become
increasingly motivated by economic
incentives
by claiming to be value free
market fundamentalism
has actually undermined moral values
markets
are supposed to be guided by an
invisible hand
that's what makes them so efficient
participants need to exercise no moral
judgments in reaching their buy and sell
decisions because their actions are not
supposed to have any visible effect on
the market prices
in truth
the rules
governing mark financial markets are
decided by the visible hand of
politicians
and in a representative democracy
politicians run into an agency problem
thus
the agency problem poses grave
difficulties both for representative
democracy and the market economy which
can't be resolved without an appeal to
moral principles
that's how the agency problem has gained
such prominence in my thinking
first i'll analyze the agency problem
and then i will deal with the conflict
between capitalism and open society
let me start at the beginning
i first encountered the agency problem
in connection with the so-called
resource curse
by resource curse i mean that countries
that are rich in natural resources are
often curves accursed by corrupt or
repressive governments insurrections
civil wars
so that the people are even poorer
and lead more miserable lives than in
countries that are less well endowed by
nature
think of the congo
sudan
sierra leone and liberia
one of the non-governmental
organizations i support global witness
proposed the campaign
based on the slogan publish what you pay
the idea was to get oil companies and
mining companies to disclose the
payments they make to various
governments
the amounts could then be added up
and the governments could be held
responsible by the people for for the
monies they received
the campaign was launched in 2002
and it has had an interesting history
the idea itself
turned out to be a
fertile fallacy because
while public opinion could could put
enough pressure on the big oil companies
fly-by-night operators
and companies domiciled in
non-democratic states were less
susceptible
so the amounts could not be added up
fortunately the british government took
up the course and formed the extractive
industries transparency initiative
which brought together governments
companies and civil society in an
in an effort to establish international
standards of transparency
which apply both to companies and to
governments
in those countries that subscribe to the
transparency initiative the governments
undertook to publish the amounts they
received
that is actually working
in countries like nigeria
and azerbaijan
in analyzing the resource curse
i came to attribute great importance to
what i called an asymmetric agency
problem
according to the modern concept of
sovereignty
the natural resources of a country
belong to the people of that country
but governments which are supposed to be
agents of the people
put their own interests ahead of the
interests of the people whom they are
supposed to represent
and engage in all sorts of corrupt
practices
on the opposite side
the managements of the international oil
and mining companies
represent the interests of of the
companies all too well
they used to go so far as to bribe
governments in order to obtain
concessions
willing takers and givers of tribes
are the root cause
root cause of the resource curse
once i became aware
of the agency problem
i discovered it everywhere
communism failed
because of the agency problem
karl marx's proposition
from everybody according to their
ability and to everybody according to
their needs
was a very attractive idea
but the communist rulers put their own
interests ahead of the interests of the
people
the agency problem is also the bane of
representative democracy
because the elected representatives
use their powers
for their own interests to the detriment
of the common
interest and
in the recent financial crisis
the agency problem proved to be the
undoing of the financial system
when financial engineers
turned mortgages into securities
by issuing collateralized debt
obligations or cdos
they thought
they were reducing risks
through geographical
diversification
in reality
they were introducing a new risk
by separating the interests of the
agents who who created and distributed
the synthetic instruments from the
interests of the owners of those
securities
and the agents were more interested in
earning fees
than in protecting the interests of the
principles
so the agency problem seemed ubiquitous
yet in spite of its pervasive influence
it escaped attention until recently
in my student days it was almost totally
unrecognized
in the last 20 years
it has received more attention
but mainly from economists who studied
it in terms of contracts and incentives
in reality
the agency problem is more of an ethical
problem
and analyzing it in terms of contracts
and incentives actually aggravated the
ethical problem
establishing the principle
that principle that people's behavior is
governed by contracts and incentives had
the effect of eliminating or at least
diminishing ethical considerations
that may sound perverse but only because
reflexivity is not well understood
values
are less
closely governed by an objective reality
than cognitive notions
therefore they are more easily
shaped by the theories that people adopt
and economic theory is a case in point
markets are supposed to act as an
invisible hand bringing the demand and
supply into balance
what makes the invisible hand so
efficient
is that there is no need to exercise
moral judgment all values can be
expressed in terms of money and money is
fungible pecunia knowledge
money doesn't smell
the romans used to say
but taking it for granted that all human
behavior is guided by self-interest
leaves no room for the exercise of moral
judgment
and society can't exist
without some ethical precepts
the behavior of market participants is
guided by market values
and market values are quite different in
character
from the moral values that are supposed
to guide the behavior of people as
members of society
this opens up a whole range of questions
which i have not been able to resolve
concerning the conflict between market
values and social values
the
agency problem has provided me with some
new insights
i was also inspired by a short monograph
by bruce r scott on the concept of
capitalism
as a result i may have something new to
say
indeed
i myself am shocked by some of the
conclusions i have reached
scott argues
that capitalism has been misinterpreted
by conflating it with the market
mechanism
this is a distortion that scott
attributes mainly to milton friedman
i'm less specific and attributed to
market fundamentalism
scott argues
further
that behind the invisible hand of the
market lurks the visible hand of human
agency namely the political process
which sets and administers the rules
this is where the agency problem comes
into play
so does the conflict between market
values
and social values
the united states is a democratic open
society based on the freedom of the
individual protected by the rule of law
as defined by the constitution
at the same time the american economy is
based on the market mechanism which
allows individuals to engage in free
exchange without undue
interference from arbitrary actions by
governmental
authority
the political
and economic arrangements seem to fit
together seamlessly
one could easily speak of an open
society and a market economy in the same
breath
and people including me often do
but appearances are deceptive
there is a deep-seated conflict between
capitalism and open society market
values and social values
the conf the conflict has been
successfully covered up by the market
fundamentalist ideology
which gained the upper hand in the 1980s
during ronald reagan's presidency
the distinguishing feature of the market
mechanism is that it is a moral
one person's dollar is worth exactly the
same as another person's irrespective of
how he how she came to possess it
that's what makes markets so efficient
participants needn't worry about moral
considerations
in an efficient market an individual
individual decisions affect market
prices only marginally if one person
abstained from participating as either
buyer or seller someone else would take
her place with only a marginal
difference in the price
therefore
individual market participants bear
little responsibility for the outcome
but
markets are suitable only for individual
choices
not for social decisions
they allow individual participants to
engage in free exchange but they are not
designed to exercise social choices such
as deciding the rules that should govern
society including how market how the
market mechanism should function
that's the preview of politics
extending the idea of a freestanding
market
self-governing and self-correcting to
the political sphere
is highly deceptive because it removes
ethical considerations from politics
which can't properly function without
them
in the united states
politics takes the form of
representative democracy
people elect representatives who operate
believers of power
they are agents who are supposed to
represent the interests of the people
in reality
they tend to put their own interests
ahead of the interests of the people
getting elected
is expensive
and representatives are beholden to
their supporters
those who don't play
who don't play the game
don't get elected
that's how money pollutes politics and
special interests
trump the public interest
the agency problem in the american
political system is not new it's
inherent in a representative democracy
the right to petition elected
representatives was written into the
constitution
yet
the agency problem seems to be much more
severe today
than it was even as recently as my
arrival in the united states in 1956
why
there are several
objective historical developments
which may be held partly responsibly
partly responsible
notably the development of sophisticated
methods of manipulating public opinion
and the growth of special interests
but the main culprit is a decline in
public morality
fostered by the rise of market
fundamentalism
i'd like to think that at the time of
the founding of the republic citizens
were genuinely guided by a sense of
civic virtue
fortunately the founding fathers didn't
put much faith in that and built the
constitution on the division of powers
they created checks and balances between
competing interests
that's why the constitution
holds up so well
in spite of the decline in morality
even when i first arrived in 1956
people professed to be guided by
intrinsic values like honesty and intel
integrity
it may have been
hypocritical with all kinds of vices
clandestinely practiced
but still it was very different from
today's public life
where the blatant pursuit of
self-interest is openly admitted and
people are admired for being successful
irrespective of how they achieved it
i don't want to be misunderstood
painting too rosy a picture of the past
is characteristic of people of a certain
age
and i i don't want to fall into such an
obvious trap
i don't claim
that politicians were more honest and
society more just in 1956
america has made great progress since
then in transparency accountability and
social equality but there has been
a remarkable transformation in what i
believe uh in in is the behavior of uh
of what is socially acceptable and even
admirable
due to the rise of market fundamentalism
i describe it
as a decline in public morality in a
very special sense by contrasting it
with the immorality
of market values
i define market fundamentalism as the
undue extension of market values to
other spheres of social life notably
politics
economic theory claims that in
conditions of general equilibrium the
invisible hand assures the optimum
allocation of resources
this means
that people pursuing their self-interest
are indirectly
also serving the public interest
it gives self-interest and the profit
motive
moral imprimatur which allows them to
replace virtues like honesty integrity
and concern for others
the argument is invalid on several
counts
first
financial markets don't tend towards
equilibrium
general equilibrium
theory reached this its conclusion by
taking the conditions of supply and
demand as independently given
the invisible hand of the market then
brings supply and demand into
equilibrium
this approach ignores
the reflexive feedback loops between
market prices
prices and the underlying conditions of
supply and demand
it also ignores the visible hand of the
political process
which lies hidden
behind the market mechanism
second
the general equilibrium theory takes the
initial allocation of resources as given
this rules out any consideration of
social justice
most importantly
the theory assumes that people know
what their self-interest is
and how best to pursue it
in reality
there is a significant gap between what
people think
and what the facts are
nevertheless
market fundamentalism has emerged
triumphant
how could that happen
one reason is
that the main
policy implication of market
fundamentalism
that government interference in the
economy should be kept to a minimum
is not as unsound
as the arguments employed to justify it
the market mechanism may be flawed
by but the political process is even
more so
participants in the political process
are even more fallible than market
participants
because
politics revolve around social values
whereas markets
take the the participants values as
given
as we have seen
social values are highly susceptible to
manipulation
moreover
politics are poisoned by the agency
problem
to guard against the agency problem
all kinds of safeguards have to be
introduced and this makes the behavior
of governmental agencies in the economic
sphere much more rigid and bureaucratic
than the behavior of private
participants
on all these grounds
it makes sense to argue
that governmental interference in the
economy should be kept to a minimum
so
market fundamentalism has merely
substituted an invalid argument for what
could have been a much stronger one
it could have argued
that all human constructs are imperfect
and social choices involve choosing the
lesser level and on those grounds
government intervention in the economy
should be kept to a minimum that would
have been a reasonable position
instead it claimed that the failures of
government intervention proved that the
free markets are perfect and that's
simply bad logic
i want to make myself quite clear
i condemn market fundamentalism as a
false and dangerous doctrine but i'm in
favor of keeping government intervention
and regulations to a minimum for other
and better reasons
by far the most powerful force
working in favor of market
fundamentalism
is that it serves the self-interest of
the owners and managers of capital
the distribution of wealth is taken as
given and the pursuit of self-interest
is found to serve the common interest
what more could those who are in control
of capital ask for
they constitute
a wealthy and powerful group
well positioned to promote market
fundamentalism not only by cognitive
argument
but by the active manipulation of public
opinion
market fundamentalism endows them at the
market mechanism which is immoral by
nature with a moral character and turns
the pursuit of self-interest into a
civic virtue similar to the pursuit of
truth
it has prevailed by the force of
manipulation
not by the force of reason it's
supported by a powerful and
well-financed propaganda machine which
distorts the public's understanding
of its own self-interest
for example
how could the how else
could the campaign to repeal the estate
tax which applies only to an elite one
percent of the population have been so
successful
there are of course
competing forces in the political arena
that use similar methods of manipulation
but they tend to be less well financed
because they can't draw on the
self-interest of the wealthiest and most
powerful segment of the population
that's how
market fundamentalism has emerged
triumphant in the last 25 years
and even the financial crisis was not
sufficient to impair its influence
this was demonstrated by president
obama's decision
to avoid recapitalizing the banks in a
way that would have given the government
majority control
market fundamentalism should not be
conflated with the efficient market
hypothesis you can be an economist
working on that hypothesis
or with that hypothesis without being a
market fundamentalist indeed many
economies are bleeding hard liberals
but the efficient market hypothesis has
a stranglehold on the teaching of
economics in american universities and
that phenomenon can be attributed to the
financial support given by capitalists
and foundations committed to market
fundamentalism
they are also responsible for the
encroachment of market values into other
disciplines like law
and political science
capitalism is not directly opposed to
open society
the way
soviet communism was nevertheless it
poses some serious threats
i've also i have already discussed one
of them the financial markets are not
equilibrium bound but bubble prone
the dismantling of the regular
regulatory mechanism has given rise to a
super bubble whose bursting will
negatively influence the american
economy for several years to come
this discussion has revealed another
threat you know to open society the
agency problem and the influence of
money in politics which contaminate the
political process
in an open society the political process
is supposed to serve the common interest
in contemporary america the political
process has been captured by special
interests
our elected representatives are beholden
to those who finance their election not
to the electorate at large
what's happening to president obama's
health care and energy bills provides a
vivid illustration
the electorate has been brainwashed to
such an extent that a responsible
discussion of the public good
has become well nigh impossible
a national health service and the carbon
tax are non-starters
our choices are confined to solutions
that can be gained
by a special interest such as cap and
trade
lobbying
is at the core of the agency problem
how can it be brought under control
this is an ethical issue
and not a matter of modifying economic
incentives
because
lobbying is lucrative and it's liable to
remain so even if the rules are
tightened
in the absence of moral values
regulations can always be circumvented
and what's worse the regulations
themselves will be designed to serve
special interests
not the common interest
this is the danger facing the united
states today
when a wounded financial sector
is his work is seeking to regain its
former preeminence
there is a way
to deal with the ethical issue
we need to draw a clear distinction
between the economic and political
spheres
market participation and rule making
are two different functions
markets allow participants to engage in
free exchange here it's quite legitimate
for the participants to be guided by the
profit motive
by contrast
the making and enforcement of rules
ought to be guided by consideration of
the public good
here the profit motive is misplaced
it's when people try to bend the rules
to their own advantage
that the political process becomes
corrupted
and representative democracy fails to
produce the results that would make open
society a desirable form of social
organization
it should be emphasized
that this argument directly contradicts
the currently fashionable market
fundamentalist attitude which speaks of
a political marketplace
how could
the political process be improved in an
open society
i propose a rather simple rule
people should separate their role as
market participants from their role as
political participants
as market participants they ought to
pursue their
their self-interest
as participants in the political process
they ought to be guided by the public
interest
the justification for this rule
is also rather simple
if in conditions close to perfect
competition
no single competitor can affect the
market prices
therefore
individual market decisions have no
effect on social conditions whether or
not
one cares about the common good
but political decisions
do affect social conditions therefore it
makes all the difference whether or not
they serve the public interest
the trouble is
that
the public good can't be determined by
reference to a generally accepted
objective standard it's contingent on
the views of the electorate
but
in the absence of an objective standard
these views are easily manipulated
and manipulation is self-reinforcing
the more outrageous the political claims
and counter-claims the harder it is to
tell what is right and what is wrong
that's what has made the political
process so ineffective in the united
states today
by contrast the market mechanism
functions much better
people may not know what's good for them
but profits do provide an objective
criterion by which market participants
performance can be measured
no wonder
that the profit motive has gained such
prominence among the values that guide
people's behavior
not only do prophets provide the means
for the pursuit of whatever ends people
may have but they also serve as an end
in itself
because as a reliable measure of success
they attract other people's admiration
and generate self-esteem
indeed
many successful business people feel
much more secure in making money
than in using their wealth
the spread
of market values has brought immense
economic benefits
in the course of history
looking back
christianity
used to treat the pursuit of profit as
sinful
this hampered economic development
the reformation then facilitated the
development of markets and opened the
way to material progress and the
accumulation of wealth
society underwent a great transformation
traditional relationships were replaced
by contractual ones
contractual relations
came to penetrate into more and more
spheres of social life
and eventually relationships started to
be replaced by transactions
the pace of change continued to
accelerate
it sped up spread up tremendously during
my lifetime
the difference
between my childhood in hungary
and my adult life in america is quite
dramatic
so were the changes that occurred in
america between my arrival in 1956 and
the present day
when i first came to america
i was struck by how much further market
values had penetrated into society
than in my native hungary or even
england where traditional values and
class distinctions still prevailed
since then
both england and america underwent a
further transformation
the professions like medicine and law
became businesses
in my view
this has had a destabilizing effect on
society
just as market fundamentalism has had a
destabilizing effect on financial
markets
now
exactly what level of stability is
socially desirable is of course a matter
of opinion
what is the proper role of the profit
motive in the professions such as law
and medicine
and the media
is similarly open to debate
but there can be no question
that the profit motive has had a
nefarious influence in the political
sphere because it has aggravated the
agency problem
how can the agency problem be minimized
it's too much to expect
uh those value those who have a vital
and special interest at stake not to
lobby congress
the tobacco industry is bound to oppose
legislation against cigarettes
and the insurance industry
will be against a single-payer
healthcare system
but those who don't have a vital
interest at stake ought to give pressure
precedence to the public interest over
their narrow self-interest
they needn't be bothered by the
so-called free rider problem namely that
others who act more selfishly would also
benefit from their unselfish behavior
because the objective of the exercise is
to benefit the public
to sum up
yesterday
i argued
that the cognitive
function ought to be given precedence
over the manipulative function today
i argue that while the prophet motive is
perfectly justified within the existing
rules when it comes to making the rules
the public interests ought to be given
precedence over personal interests
i firmly believe
that if
a minority of the electorate met those
two requirements
representative democracy would function
better now
i realize that this is
perhaps a politically
incorrect
elitist
point of view because i attribute
great importance to to
an elite
that is devoted to the pursuit of truth
and
uh devoted to the public in in interest
but uh
i i firmly believe
that that is what we need
uh for
an open society uh to
uh
to flourish
uh uh
and and and actually even to survive
now i'd like to end on a personal mode
uh i have practiced what i preach
as a fan as a hedge fund manager i have
played by the rules
and try to maximize my profits
as a citizen
i try to improve the rules even if the
reforms go against my personal interests
for instance i support the regulation of
hedge funds along with other financial
institutions
i firmly believe
that if more people followed this
precept
our political system would function much
better
i also believe
that foundations like mine can play an
important role
exactly
because so few people
follow that precept
in
the open society institute we have made
it our business
to protect the public interest against
the encroachments of private interests
we are also supporting civil society
in holding governments accountable
i would describe these endeavors as
political philanthropy
and i believe that it can make a greater
contribution to make the world a better
place than more conventional
philanthropy because fewer people are
engaged in it
i'm in a privileged position
i'm more independent than most people
because i don't depend on clients or
customers
and i feel under a moral obligation to
put my privileged position to good use
i'm of course
greatly outgunned
by
special interests but at least i have
the satisfaction that my money has
greater scarcity value
the trouble is
that special interests also seek to
disguise themselves as protectors of the
public interest
and it takes a discerning eye to
discriminate between the genuine and the
phony
especially as both sides are for forced
to resort to similar methods of
persuasion and manipulation
in the absence
of objective criteria
one can only reach a judgment by a
process of trial and error
people
of good intentions engaged on one side
of the debate often find it difficult to
believe that there are people on the
other side with equally good intentions
the best way to find out
is by taking their claims at face value
and engaging them on the substance of
their argument
this has the beneficial effect
of giving the cognitive function
precedence in the political debate
only if they fail to respond in kind
should they be dismissed and
subsequently ignored
there are people like that in every
country
unfortunately
in the united states they are not
ignored they have become very
influential
whether the electorate
also refuses to be influenced by
people who try to manipulate them
with total disregard for the truth is
the test that every open society has to
pass to remain open
given the success of ovalian propaganda
america is not doing very well in this
regard
the political process
which has served america well for two
centuries seems to have deteriorated
we used to have two parties competing
for the middle
but the middle ground
has shrunk
and politics
have become increasingly polarized
president obama has done his level best
to reverse the trend he has tried to be
the great uniter but to no avail
in the end
how a democracy functions
depends on the people who live in it
i believe that if more people separated
their role as political participants
from their role
as
market participants american democracy
would function
much better it's up to each individual
that's what i have done
and even a small minority could be
helpful in rebuilding the vanishing
middle ground
thank you
[Applause]
you