well
the short talk is this
I did a lot of math
I made a lot of money
and I gave almost all of it away
that's the story of my life now
it's a good story but it's short
but for reasons which I won't go into
I uh
I needed money
and I had borrowed money to invest in a
company with a friends of mine
and I need needed to pay it back
but there was a place in Princeton
called The Institute for defense
analyzes
which was a highly
classified place
under the Aegis of the government the
defense department
and what we're supposed to do
is uh break Russian codes
well that was an interesting challenge
uh
I like the work
they told us you could do your own
mathematics up to half your time which
the other half you had to do you know
this cold cracking business
at a certain point
I came to
Stony Brook University I was 30 years
old
to be the chair
of their math department
which was not a very strong Department
and I was pretty young to be the
chairman but I thought it would be fun
and I had a lot of money to work with
because
the governor at the time was a guy named
Rockefeller now I think everyone has
probably heard of the name Rockefeller
but if has anyone not heard of the name
Rockefeller
okay most of you have heard of
Rockefeller Rockefeller loved the State
University and was pouring money on it
so I had a lot of money to work with
and uh
hired some terrific people so
hire some terrific people
but at the same time in that time frame
I started again interested in another
area of math
and uh
I worked on that area
and came up with something really quite
beautiful
three dimensions it was a function I
can't really describe it but it
it lived in three dimensions closed
three-dimensional spaces
and I
was quite pleased
I showed it to churn
I I say I showed it I we I centered by
the mail because in those days there was
no email
and chern said well you've done this in
three dimensions
but it should work in all dimensions
I was very dubious but I said okay let's
work together and see
and he was right
it would work in all dimensions
and I was very pleased we published the
paper
and about five years later
a physicist
named Whitton
saw this paper and thought and he was
right it could apply to physics
and then some other physicists saw how
it could apply to physics
I didn't know any physics at all
churn might have known something but it
never occurred to him that would apply
to physics
and remarkably so you never know where
something will go
you think you're doing math and you're
actually doing physics maybe or whatever
so today
that is
called churn Simon's Theory
it's all over the place in physics on
average every day
four papers in physics
reference this churn Simon's Theory
so I can't take any credit for it at all
but uh but there it was and of course
I'm quite pleased about it but I can't
say that oh I I invented this for
physics
well
shortly after that
I started to get interested
in the world of Investments
I had come into to
a very small amount of money but it was
enough to start investing
and one thing led to another
I started hiring people
and we made what was called a hedge fund
and it was
remarkably successful
it's still going I'm not with it anymore
but I made
a tremendous amount of money
from this from this hedge fund
now my lovely wife Marilyn
said let's give some of it away
so I said okay fine so we gave some
charity
and then she said well why don't we
start a foundation
and uh
okay starting Foundation
she started a foundation
I put money into it
the good thing about putting money into
a foundation is you can give the money
away you've got the tax advantage but it
doesn't have to be spent immediately so
you can put money into the foundation
and say well we'll see what we want to
do with it tomorrow or next year or
whatever
but it grew and grew
and grew
so uh
it today
oh well
we decided to focus on science
with our uh Foundation
focus on science
uh
90 percent of it
should be science eight 60 of that
should be basic science
and 30 of that could be translational
science
and 10 could be education and Outreach
and things like that
so today uh
that Foundation is
extremely large
and so most of the money that I made was
put into the foundation
so I'm not so rich as I was before but
uh Rich enough it was extremely
interesting to model things and see them
uh programmed up God knows not by me but
someone else could program them up and
test out theories of models would it
work what it would not work and at the
same time mathematics was going
extremely well and I did do the work
there that subsequently got this
bubbling prize solved the you know kind
of a major problem in geometry and uh
was going swimmingly I was it was a it
was a great experience I was there
but then this was the time of the
Vietnam War
and uh the president of this
organization two two steps up from my
local boss
guy named Maxwell Taylor some of the
people with gray hair in the room might
remember General Maxwell Taylor anyway
he ran this outfit and he wrote a crazy
article which was well I thought it was
crazy in the New York Times magazine
section
uh saying how we were going to win the
Vietnam War and it was just you know
victory was days away or whatever it was
that he was touting and uh
I didn't
agree with that now the work we were
doing had nothing to do with the Vietnam
War but it annoyed me
that my head of my organization could
take such a silly point of view and I
wrote a nice letter to the New York
Times expressing that view
which they kindly published
in that same Sunday edition
several weeks later so now I was on the
watch list I didn't know it but I was on
the watch list for the for this place
and then a guy came along a few months
later three or four
and he was a he announced that he was a
reporter for news Week Magazine
and he was doing an article on people
who worked for the defense department
but were opposed to the war and he was
having a hard time finding anyone to
interview but he heard about me he read
my letter could he interview me and I
said sure what did I know of course
of course
you can see how sophisticated I was at
that time so he said well uh you know
what what do you do well I blathered on
about this and that but I said but my
algorithm has been
uh since they say you can do 50 of your
work on mathematics and the other 50 on
their work uh right now I'm doing only
mathematics and I'm keeping careful
records when the war is over then I'll
do an equal amount of their work
and uh that's my Approach
so
no I mean you know
it's not unreasonable
[Laughter]
so I went back to tell my local boss I
it was the first intelligent thing that
had occurred to me a little late perhaps
but that I decided I better tell my my
local boss that I gave this interview
and he said you did and what did you say
and I said well I said what I said he
said hmm he said I better call Taylor
okay pick up the phone call this General
Maxwell Taylor that was
a little
silence at the other end and so on and
and he couldn't hear what Taylor was
saying and then he hung up he looked at
me said you're fired
fired I mean I'm fine you're fired
and well it was the first time and
happily the last time I was ever fired
but I was fired summarily and I said
well
I'm a permanent member that was my title
permanent member
he said I'll tell you the difference and
when I started I was a temporary member
I was a temporary member and then I
became a permanent member
so he said I'll tell you the difference
between a temporary member and a
permanent member I said yes he said a
temporary member has a contract
well I guess it was true I had a letter
when I was a temporary member but when
it became a permanent member I didn't
have a contract and so there I was out
on my ear but not especially
worried and I did go against his advice
and I did take the job as chairman
at Stony Brook I figured
uh
it was better to be a fire Roar than a
fiery and
there was a fair amount of firing
regrettably that had to be done uh the
department was very weak but we hired a
lot of people we had a good time and we
did build a good department and I did do
some some mathematics there that ended
up with churn that ended up being a
pretty useful in physics
and uh and it was there that I did
learn about uh the bone marinop
experiment and the relation the apparent
relation between
what we mathematician called you know
bundles with connection and what the
physicists call Gage Theory and I did
run off to MIT and said not to MIT to
see is he was in I think he was at
Rockefeller that year and sat in some
place over coffee
and explain this connection
and it was a very very exciting time and
it was I think there were conversations
like that going on perhaps in lots of
coffee shops around about how physics
and the way it was evolving and the
geometric side of mathematics were
really becoming uh quite intertwined and
now they're
inextricably intertwined as far as I
could as far as I can see
so those were all those were all good
times but then as is said as he's been
giving my my talk uh
I did get frustrated I was stuck I was
really stuck in a problem I was trying
to prove a certain number was irrational
I guess you all know what an irrational
number is uh it might not seem so
important that a number be rational or
irrational but in this case uh it seemed
to have a lot of a lot of implications
and I was wholly incapable
of solving this problem and it's still
an open problem this whole area it's a
great set of problems about volumes and
whether
they're rational
in some sense so uh anyway I was I was
very frustrated
uh I had been I was on the wrong side of
of a divorce
I was on turned out on the right side of
my next marriage I did have a new
girlfriend who's standing sitting right
there my new girlfriend and
my South American Business at long last
started paying some dividends in fact
they started paying a lot of dividends
and I had some money and I invested that
money and found out that I wasn't bad at
it
and all of this
was made me think okay it's time for a
change and so in 1976 I was 38
I felt I'd been a mathematician all my
life but really sort of since I was 18 I
think I was so I I guess I spent 20
years
in that game and decided to to go into
business and never occurring that I
would apply mathematics to the business
Ivy did subsequently but I just felt you
know you read the newspapers you you you
think you'll do pretty well but and and
we did we did okay but after a little
bit I started collecting some data and I
figured
there's something to be modeled here
like we used to do in the old Ida days
so I brought in the best modeler in the
world uh Lenny a guy named Lenny
Baum from Ida and persuaded him to come
and we're going to make these models and
do great
and Lenny started making models and with
me and we were fooling around
but I kept trading and then Lenny seemed
to have got less and less interested in
models and more and more interested in
reading the news reel that in those days
it was just a role it would tick away
and you'd read the news and Lenny was
always reading the news instead of
thinking about models
and then he started having opinions on
what was going to go up and what was
going to go down this was all foreign
currencies bonds that kind of stuff
and I started listening to him and uh he
was right he was right
he was right enough times he said okay
the hell with the modeling let's just uh
let's just try to make some money and uh
we had a remarkable run in a two two
years since I said to Howard the model
and we multiplied our investors money by
12. now then that was even after that
phase that's a that sounds pretty good
right for uh it was we were incredibly
lucky see the last word up there is luck
Good Luck Good Luck Good Luck and we
certainly had good luck uh I've had a
lot of good luck
in my career so uh but in the back of my
mind was well okay London doesn't want
to build models but maybe we could build
some someone else could come in and
build models and another fellow Jim ax
who was quite a famous mathematician uh
left Stony Brook to come and and he did
build some models so
those next years was a combination of
fundamental trading I did venture
capital I invested in all kinds of
things but the models kept being built
and working better and better
and finally
at the end of about a 10-year run
it was clear to me that this
gut-wrenching business of fundamental I
mean
you know if you're doing fundamental
trading one morning you come in you feel
like a genius you know your positions
are all your way and you think God I'm
really smart and look at all the money I
made overnight then the next day you
come in and they've gone against you and
you feel like an idiot there was
we were pretty good at it but it just
didn't seem to be a way
to live your life you know uh so click
building models go with the model so
by 1988
I decided it's going to be a hundred
percent models and it and it has been
ever since in the business that we built
so some firms uh you know investing
firms say oh they have models and what
they typically mean is you know we have
a model and it advises the trader what
to do and if he likes the advice he'll
take it and if he doesn't like the
advice he won't take it well that's you
can't that's not science you can't
simulate how you would do how how was
how were you feeling when you got out of
bed uh you know 13 years ago when you're
looking at at historical simulations did
you like what the model said or didn't
you like what the model said that it's a
hard thing to back test so uh if you're
going to trade using models you're just
slavishly use the models you do whatever
the hell it says no matter how smart or
dumb you might think it is at that
moment and that uh turned out to be a
wonderful decision
so we built a business
a hundreds hundred percent based on
building computer models
uh
starting in those areas that that I I
mentioned currencies uh financial
instruments uh gradually uh moving to
stocks and finally to anything that
moved uh
well it had to be uh tradable how to be
liquid we were all was always liquid but
and you know bringing in data data in
those days we you know we sent gals down
to the New York Federal Reserve to copy
histories of interest rate numbers I
mean they didn't exist in the 70s you
couldn't go and buy data and it was
certainly not online deliveries of all
this stuff so to build the original
models we needed to collect a lot of
data by hand which we did and uh but
gradually
um you know we got smarter the models
got better we brought in more and more
people is said our we have the best math
and physics department in the world at
Renaissance I don't think that's quite
true uh on the other hand it ain't bad
uh we have a lot of smart uh Smart Guys
and uh and we certainly hired people who
were good at that kind of work
so we started this thing called The
Medallion Fund in 1988 in 1993 we closed
it
to any new investment by Outsiders just
employees could invest
by 2002 we started taking out the
outsiders all together buying them out
and by 2005 there weren't any left so
since then last five years this vaunted
Medallion fund has been owned a hundred
percent by by the employees
uh which today are about 300
300 employees
and well
so
people would always ask me well what's
the secret how come because we're not
the only
Quant firm in the world we're not the
only guys who have you know made models
I disparaged some who who model making
was sort of a part-time thing but there
were certainly other outfits but we seem
to have done better than than anybody we
had really established a remarkable
record so people always ask me well
what's the secret you know what are the
secrets not because I'm not going to
tell you the various
predictive
signals and so on and so forth
unless no I'm definitely not
we'll keep that that's even bigger
Secrets than that
their stuff down there at iea
it's these secrets are uh we try to
guard them but the real secret sauce
is that we start with great scientists
we start with
first class people who've done first
class work or we believe have reason to
believe we'll do first class work and
and because I was there at the beginning
and a few other people who had been
pretty good at math and science we had
we had good taste and that that's uh uh
stayed with the company
the second thing is we provide people
with a great infrastructure
and I've had people come to us from all
over when they come to work they said
they never saw it's more easy to get to
work here than anyplace else the data is
easily through we have someone in the we
have an alumnus here
that I saw earlier who could testify to
that I'm not going to ask him to do so
but he would so the infrastructure give
people a good infrastructure and I think
the most important thing that we do is
have an open atmosphere
so my belief is the best way to conduct
research on a broad scale is to make
sure as much as possible that everybody
knows what everybody else is doing at
least as quickly as possible sometimes
you got an idea you want to keep it to
yourself for a little while you don't
want to look like an idiot but the
sooner the better start talking to other
people about what you're doing because
that's what
what will will stimulate things the
fastest no compartmentization no we
don't have any little groups to say this
is our system and we developed it and
you you run it and we get paid based on
that and so on none of that everybody
meets once a week all the researchers
meet any new idea gets
uh brought up discussed vetted and
hopefully put into put into production
so it's an open atmosphere
and uh
and people get paid based on the overall
profits you don't get paid just on your
work you get paid based on the profits
of the firm so everyone has an interest
in really everyone else's success
okay so why don't we have enough
I don't want to dwell on this point but
why don't we have enough teachers of
math and science in the high schools who
know the subject and one answer is well
if they knew the subject well they'd
also know enough to work for Google or
Goldman Sachs or God knows where because
today the world is so much more
Quantified and the economy is so much
more based on quantitative methods than
it was 30 or 40 years ago so uh the
difference in the quality of the job the
pay and the respect is so great for
someone who's actually qualified to do a
good job of teaching High School
mathematics that they get pulled away
and uh don't often find themselves uh in
in the classroom anymore so you have to
make the job better that means pay these
folks more which we do in New York
through our program and a few other
cities and provide them more respect and
support which we do so uh you know if
you pay a guy 25 more and make them feel
or her
feel special
all of a sudden the career is a lot
better if you make the career better
people stay and will stay in their
career if it stays the way it is people
won't stay in the career and if we don't
do something
uh it isn't going to be a good situation
because one of as far as I can tell
and unlike most of the interviews with
you which I assume are largely about
your incredible success in in Quant and
as a Quant but
um is that one of your one of the
reasons you were so successful it seems
to me if I try and distill this is being
able to bring in really talented people
and let them run and with their talent
yes
and let them run uh
uh you have to have a good taste
in selecting people and uh but then you
don't sit on them you you you let them
do their thing and uh
that's uh
that's very satisfying and again when I
went into business
um
that was even more important yeah in a
certain sense and uh
I hired some terrific people there and
let them
as you say do your thing but do you
think your experiences chair helped
Prime you for that or not I mean the
sense of hiring faculty and saying okay
we think you're good now do good things
it's good
I mean I learned how to manage people
which is very difficult and something
you don't learn as an academic as a rule
right and uh so I left
Stony Brook I I think after eight years
and um and that's when I went into
business and uh
but I had learned to manage people
and uh
and I would I was
I was good at that I I uh well
recognizing talent and encouraging him
do the best thing is is great at
managing people if you can do if that's
what you can I mean sometimes
unfortunately there's the minutia of
other things that get in the way but
that's the heart of a good yeah that's
and and it's and it I it obviously
worked for you you and fortunately you
were you actually were able to build
look let me let me put this well let me
there's as far as I can tell again I've
tried to to think about your life having
been studying it lately
three factors probably are important but
one I I learned one was that you you you
had sold this company that had started
uh way back when in Colombia and so you
had a cushion you had a you weren't you
had a monetary cushion you weren't
quitting your job in some sense with
worrying about feeding my family I did
and in fact uh
it uh
that business was sold
and uh
for
quite a lot of money
and uh
my friends said from Columbia okay now
we have all this money uh we want you to
help invest it
I don't know anything about investing
but I said okay I'll do that
and I found a guy a mathematician who
had gone into the Commodities business
and uh I went and talked to him
to see what he was doing and
he seemed to really know what he was
doing so I said okay we're going to give
you X dollars
you can have 10 percent of the profits
and uh we want you to uh make some money
for us
if you lose too much you have to stop
and he said what's too much I said well
if you're down 30 percent you you have
to stop but as I was walking out the
door I said and if you make
a tremendous amount of money you have to
stop
how much is that I said if you multiply
our uh the fund uh by a factor of ten
after your fees then you have to stop
wow and well he couldn't argue with that
but the remarkable thing was that after
a few
steps that he that he took that didn't
work he get into something
and made a fortune in nine months nine
months later he had
multiplied our money by a fact of 10.
wow and uh
much of that was in a Bermuda trust that
had been set up
for me by uh
the father-in-law
of one of the two boys because he was
very appreciative that I'd gotten this
business going in the first place and he
owned he owned half the business and he
uh he took a hundred thousand dollars
and put it in a Bermuda Trust for my
family oh and so that hundred thousand
was invested with Charlie and that
became a million so now I'm
gone so uh uh so I don't know how we get
into that but uh no well the the fact
that um
um that that well yeah I we got into it
by saying I knew you'd you'd had a
little you'd had a cushion financially
which would which allowed which makes it
a little easier to switch to to quit
Academia I think obviously the but the
other thing was that you had
um so that was certainly a help there's
no doubt about it and and it might have
been a harder decision if you were if
you were going paycheck to paycheck
um but but but also you also had a
cushion of intellectual Excellence you
were able to build on the investment
you'd made in humanity as far as I can
see you brought in let's see someone you
knew a very important person from The
Institute of Defense analysis who'd been
had been involved in creating an
important very important algorithm which
led to speaker speech recognitions right
um Baum is his name or something or yeah
and then also acts your great hire from
from uh so you you were able to say oh
I've got these really good people I
already know they're really good and and
I can bring them in that must have been
important it wasn't it was important and
um
at a certain we were doing fundamental
trading
uh initially
and that worked out okay
wait a minute
I should go well I thought we had 10
minutes left uh 10 minutes or so is it
yeah 10 or 15 minutes yeah
yeah maybe maybe 15 minutes thank you
uh I don't know where I was oh yeah it
was fundamental trading but finally we
get into uh making models and uh
they worked better and uh it was ever
since it was it was model making
and uh
and your experience in algorithms well
obviously algorithms became very
important as did
um machine learning I mean which which
were you directly exposed to machine
learning or is that something that we're
brought in by your colleagues machine
learning didn't exist in those days as a
notion I think machine learning has only
been around for about 10 years or uh 15
years
um
no we didn't uh we didn't do machine
learning but the uh the idea of of in
some sense
in in some sense looking at having a
vast Storehouse of data
that you could analyze and look for
patterns yes uh what became a central
feature obviously of what of what that's
what we did we had
a tremendous amount of data historical
data tick data even the tech we had a
ton of that and the way it worked is as
a guy would think oh well maybe uh
this would be a predictive signal and
he'd hook up something and then we could
test it
back tested for the previous 10 years to
see this does this really work and and
uh
if it was a statistically significant it
would go into the uh it would go into
the business so uh
that's the way
that's the way it will work and it's
probably still works that way yeah it
still works that way it's called black
box right but but and I'm intrigued by
that because in some sense
I've I've done a lot of discussions with
people in the past and and written about
AI but
um the idea that that that basically
patterns can be discerned that you might
not discern yourself but by by looking
at data enough uh and that's how Tesla
can look and find you know in principle
hopefully that someone's not a
pedestrian but a but a stoplight
um is is you is it a black box can come
up as saying this is what you should do
but it never tells you why you should do
it absolutely and and and it's
frustrating for people and I understand
early on you it was a natural tendency
for you guys not to believe it to say
look we have an intuition why should we
trust this machine telling us to do X
when there's no rational reason that we
can think of doing it I didn't worry
about that I didn't if it if it worked
it worked and uh but we had very strong
uh uh
oh
conditions
there's requirements yeah that can the
uh
the uh
the signal versus the the the rest of
the noise I guess
you know predictive signals and they
have to have enough statistical
significance
um
to uh put them into the system and
they're tested all the time
sometimes a signal
disappears after a while so you take it
out of the system what's happened is
that as the markets have become uh
electronic and computers have been
applied to generating prices and
accepting trades and all the rest the
markets have grown tremendously more
liquid
spreads have come down the bid ask
spreads have come down
the fellows who used to be you know the
Specialists on the floor Specialists of
all they were supposed to be the market
makers you know whatever it was full of
baloney they would create very
widespreads and at the first sign of
trouble they would they would disappear
uh
uh with
the Electronic Training has come the
ability to trade fast and that has
brought spreads down and in his broad
Market impact down so there's two things
that happens when you
buy a stock one thing
you pay a little typically you will pay
a little bit above the mid price just as
if you sell it you'll sell it for a
little bit below the mid price but the
other thing that happens is
infinitesimally perhaps you move the
market
well if you buy a hundred shares you're
probably not going to move the market
whether you buy a hundred thousand
shares you probably are going to move in
the market well how much you're going to
move it well if you're the only buyer
out there you're going to move it a heck
of a lot but if there's a lot of buyers
and and if you're the only if you're on
these sellers but if there's a lot of
people active in that market a hundred
thousand shares might go very easily so
the more volume
the better and it's volume that's been
created by these high frequency Traders
so I think the the research shows that
the costs of training
spreads and Market impact of them down
come down a great deal and it's all due
to high frequency Traders so uh is it
socially useful well if you think liquid
you know highly liquid markets are
socially useful then and I think so will
there ever be glitches and that could be
there was uh there was a glitch
I think they called it the flash crash
of a few months ago and for eight
minutes or so the market some Market
took a dive and they came right back
I mean it came right back no but I mean
it's an important point in 1987 when the
stock market crashed it went down 25
percent in half a day and it didn't
recover for six months because there was
nobody there on the other side they were
wrong
this thing recovered this flash class
recovery because someone had made a
mistake I presume some kind of order
went in that was much too big uh there
was nervousness in the market it was
already down three percent and it took a
dive and everyone stood back and said oh
my God what's going on well but then the
algorithms kicked in and you know uh
all this training just came back and and
this thing disappeared in 10 minutes so
it it
was a little destabilizing but it was a
whole lot
different from the crash of 1987 so
that's a long answer to a short question
yes I think high-speed trading is
socially useful and I think that the
people who argue against it are
wrong
not only the United States but in the
world looks kind of unbalanced unsettled
those big debts being built up by by
countries and we we have obviously a
recession in the United States and we're
we're busy bailing out Banks and you
know where's it all going where's you
know where's it all going
to hell in a handbasket or what and what
should we be
what should we be looking at well I
think all the things you mentioned are
worth looking at the national debt
has a fraction of GNP was considerably
higher even
than it is today right after the second
World War uh and we never paid off that
debt what we did was grow the GDP so the
denominator got bigger and bigger and
after a while we were back in the box so
uh there's nothing better
under most circumstances in my opinion
and some good growth and I don't think
we're taking steps to the United States
to promote that good growth because I
think we should be maybe even printing
more money and building infrastructure
and doing some things that the country
has
is lagging in getting which would get
some more people back to work and would
put us in a better position to compete
even if we do have some inflation it's
not the worst thing in the world uh as
inflation
but uh
so I don't think there's any
you know what happened in this collapse
is
the United States got a lot poorer and
it got a lot poorer because the value of
everybody's house went down
and people's most of people's net net
worth was Associated to their home and
they had been borrowing against the
rising prices in their home you know uh
home equity loans that had fueled a lot
of growth
and that that came to a to an end so we
had two bad things happen people's
balance sheets were decimated
uh and uh they had a uh not only
couldn't they borrow anymore but they
had to be paying back paying back debt
and
a balance sheet disaster
is not something it's just it's going to
get fixed very fast we we're it's going
to take a number of years
I think to rebuild
um to rebuild from from this base
and is the government doing the right
thing or the wrong thing I mean I'm not
a I'm not a big fan of this government
I'm not a big fan of the
of a tax bill that just passed except
that
uh it was well I have a there's a
Clapper up there no I
there's one Clapper uh
I mean it does it it made obviously it
made no sense to continue the tax cut
for Rich guys like me that made no sense
whatsoever
uh and and uh and for some of you out
here probably it didn't make much sense
but if that was the price to pay as it
apparently was because we have a rather
timid uh president that was the price to
pay for extending the unemployment and
making some other you know and and
keeping the tax cuts for for Less
affluent people uh and one thing or
another it was it wasn't the worst thing
in the world so it looks like maybe
it'll it'll produce a little extra
growth but that's what we need we do
need growth and my own view is I'd
rather have it at the risk of inflation
than have no growth and and say we you
know we we've held the dog value of a
dollar who gives it who cares if
everyone's out of work you know you've
got twenty percent unemployment at a
wonderful dollar is not gonna he said
helpful okay
the natural meltdown was based on
mortgages being created that were no
damn good
and they were created because there was
a market for them
so these subprime mortgages you lend
money to people that you would never if
you were the lender you would never
dream of lending money under these
circumstances on the other hand if your
uncle said don't worry uh you lend it
and I'll buy the paper you might say
well okay Uncle if you say you you'll
buy the paper I'll lend the money you
lend the money buy the paper sell the
paper to the uncle
uh this paper got securitized and at the
end of the day
stamped AAA now who the hell did that
the rating agencies stamped this paper
AAA and they stamped the AAA
either because they were idiots which I
think is largely the case uh
but also because
they were
their fees were paid by the issuers of
this rotten paper who wouldn't have
issued it in the first place if they
didn't expect to get AAA and then this
whole chain this whole chain I mean you
know in the old days you would go to the
really old days you go to the bank you
want to buy a house the bank actually
was the one who lent you this money
the bank was going to hold the mortgage
the bank was going to service the
mortgage and the bank wanted you to pay
so the banks were you know but
now a bank loans you the money for a
micro second and they they sell it to
the next guy so if the
so it it had very little to do with
Quant models it's true that quants were
designing these uh these uh packages of
mortgages but the the underlying
statistics what's the probability
that this mortgage is going to get paid
what's the probability that a guy who's
had seven jobs in eight years in four
different cities
uh and who was simply stated that he
earns uh you know whatever what's the
probability that he's really gonna pay
off his mortgage
anyone with common sense he common sense
it up that would think it's pretty darn
close to zero but uh but that fact was
not taken into account in the underlying
statistics so that's enough that's a
long answer
I will do one more I think lucky me when
when creating models to trade the
markets would you recommend focusing on
creating models around fundamental
economic data or on price Behavior such
as the S P 500 or oil gold or
combination of both thank you
I mentioned Warren Ambrose in my
beginning of my talk this mathematician
who inspired me I'm actually going to
answer your question
and I went to him one day early in my
career and I said Professor Ambrose I
mean really early is it best to learn a
lot about one area of mathematics or
learn a little bit about a lot of areas
in mathematics and he looked at me and
he said one can make the cliche either
way and that was the end of a discussion
so
there isn't any right answer to the
question you asked all those things are
good it's good to use economic models
it's good to use uh you know uh price
price histories it's good to it's good
to use make models using all these
things and there isn't any there isn't
any right or wrong to that answer
so
I think I uh I'm imaginative
I think I have a lot of imagination
and uh
my share of good ideas
to
bad one sometimes of course
in fact when you're doing science uh
you'll probably have five bad ideas for
every good one but uh
my friend Lenny Baum said uh
he said bad ideas is good
hmm good ideas is better
no ideas is terrible
and uh when you're doing signs you have
a lot of bad ideas
but uh you know uh but you got some good
ones if you're a good scientist and now
those carried today
my idea of leadership of an organization
is to hire the very best people you
possibly can
and I have a good taste in people
and then let them carry the ball
and when I became chair of the Stony
Brook math department
I reached out for the best person I
could possibly find and he was your
father
and uh I knew if your dad would come on
board it would open up the floodgates
uh people saying oh well this department
can really go somewhere
so I spent a lot of time courting your
father
and uh
finally he said yes
and then I was able to quickly hire
three or four other outstanding people
and uh and we did that over the next
couple of years I uh I only really have
one hero
in my life and at Annex Abraham Lincoln
many people I admire and so on but as a
hero it's Abraham Lincoln and he had
the following qualities
uh he had very very good social skills
people like to be around and he told a
lot of jokes and so on
he was very smart
he was very smart and his uh middle
before he became president he decided to
study euclidean geometry and understand
that much mathematics just on his own
because he was just curious and he was a
very very smart guy
thank you
good social skills wonderful social
skills and
determination
we had determination
we
there were so many times during the
Civil War where he could have just said
to hell with it
just have two countries so many people
are being killed in this terrible War
but he had a vision
of America
and he stuck to that vision
and and uh
just wouldn't give up
and over time uh he was right
and that
that entry together
when the Civil War I say we won the
Civil War the north the North
and uh
and then
he gossed with great effort the
amendment passed which abolished slavery
in the United States yes and that was
very difficult to get past
but he knew he had a how to get it
passed before the war was over and there
were a lot of seven Southerners now back
in the Congress and it would it wouldn't
get passed
and he said to his his guys
he said
this is very important I want you to go
out and do everything you can twist
every arm
give people this or that if they if they
feel they need it uh
uh I'm the president of the United
States um he was with great power use
that power and get this uh Amendment
passed and it worked yeah so uh I think
it was
just just a great man in every respect
Euclid what he said was self-evident
were the axioms the parallelism Axiom uh
that was the toughest one two points
describe a unique line and uh
and the intersection uh principle so
those he said were self-evident but from
then on the theorems that developed from
these were not self-evident they were
all
some of them looked obvious but
nonetheless they were all proved using
these initial
quote unquote self-evident things
now my
discovery of Zeno's Paradox
um
when I was a little boy maybe three or
four
I was riding in the car with my father
and he he said he had a stop to get gas
I said why why do you do that he said I
don't want to run out of gas
because you know the car won't run
and I said well
why don't you just use half the amount
that's in the tank
and then use half of that and then use
half of that
Etc and you'll never run out
you'll never run out of gas
now it I didn't think it further through
and realized yes but you'll never get
anywhere
do you think of math as beautiful in the
sense that art is beautiful I mean we
often hear this debate you know is
mathematics discovered or invented I
don't think people would say uh
Michelangelo discovered you know the
David inside of a block of marble even
though he would say stuff like that but
he actually created it but mathematics
and what's chiseled into your wall in
the Simon Center
do you feel that that's you know
discovered or really is it invented by
the human mind and then the follow-up
question after you answer that will be
is it beautiful is it does it rank among
alongside great music great artwork and
if so why so first is mathematics
discovered or invented the way art or
the you know inventions are found yeah
that's a uh standard question yeah and
uh
it's
it's both hmm
every true theorem
is out there
the number of true theorems
is I believe infinite
and the number of definitions that one
can make is infinite
so all these things are out there
but
on the other hand
you don't
know this there's no book of all these
things because
it's an infinite number of possible
theorems and definitions the key is in
doing mathematics
to let's say find a good definition a
definition that will get you somewhere a
definition that will unify perhaps other
things and so on
so
that's a creative act so it's a creative
act to find something interesting in an
infinite field in an infinite collection
of
of things so it's out there
but
you have to find it
and have a good taste
uh in in finding something that will
really go somewhere so our segue between
geometry and finance will be none other
than Albert Einstein who once said that
compound interest is the most powerful
force in the universe compound interest
is the eighth wonder of the world he who
understands it earns it he who doesn't
pays it uh do you agree with that uh I
never heard that you never heard that
okay I'll send you I'll send you an
email with the quotient uh yeah so once
again compound interest is the eighth
wonder of the world he who understands
it earns it and he who doesn't pays it
what what is your notion of the what's
the most powerful force in The World
According to Jim Simons
well the most powerful force in the
world according to me is some physical
Force I don't know which one to pick but
uh
but uh this of course is finance finance
and not uh and not physics so uh
d
uh I've been pretty successful in
finance
uh you've had some success I would say
yeah I've had some success today
actually I I
lots of money no no not a huge thing but
I'm here for you Jim if you if you need
anything
wants to know uh the proprietary
algorithms of the of The Medallion no
he's uh he wants to know has it become
harder for you
um given the rise in quantitative hedge
funds Quant funds and the thousands of
phds trying to create new algorithms has
that made it harder to create Alpha so
um can you say what Alpha means in the
context of hedge funds uh for people
that aren't familiar and then answer
that particular question
well when you say Alpha first you have
to understand beta and beta is the uh
uh the stock market as a whole
um let's say the s p average
so you could just uh invest in that and
you would be a hundred percent beta all
your return would be would come from the
let's say the s p the standard and
Poor's average
Alpha is
a source of earnings that is orthogonal
to that hmm
it's orthogonal to that and uh so that's
Alpha
now some
our Medallion fund
is uh I think
90 alpha or 95 percent Alpha it really
doesn't matter where the stock market is
going for The Medallion fund we have
another Medallion fund is only open to
employees of the of the company of
Renaissance and me of course uh as a
founder and shareholder so
uh
and and we have some publicly available
funds which do have some beta they're
not a hundred percent helpful and but of
course they don't do as well
as medallion
but uh but they do uh quite well until
today it had a bad day
I'm sorry again I'm always here if you
need uh if you need a cup of sugar I'm
here
um so in that space the question is um
I've heard it described that these
supercomputers and computers in general
are of course increasing exponentially
example of power computing power over
time and cost is coming down and yet the
super computers themselves are suffering
from the fact that there's more
subscriptions there's more people that
want to use the computer now than in the
earlier days so it's sort of offsetting
the exponential gains and processing
power and I guess James altitude's
question here is has the just the net
quantity of hedge funds and Quant PhD
yes I understand that
yeah I didn't answer that question yeah
so
I think the question is do we have
competition and how much competition
has competition hurt us
because there are more and more
quantitative funds up to a point I think
most funds are not quantitative funds
but they're certainly an increasing
number of funds that are quantitative
and uh our secret is just to stay ahead
of everybody to hire the best possible
people and the research goes on all the
time all the time we're doing research
trying to find new predictive signals
new predictive signals uh for example
that's a big example so a signal is well
you know what a signal is it so it tells
you what's
a predictive signal was a signal that
tells you what's gonna what's gonna
happen there's some probability of right
what's up with a greater than
probability greater than a half
and the more of these signals that you
have
an independent and not correlated with
each other if they're highly correlated
it's really just one signal but
um
the more you have the better
and uh we have uh I won't even say the
number and I'm not sure what it is but
it's a very large number of predictive
and they keep uh being developed and
sometimes these signals lose their power
yes and uh you have to discard them
uh other people have caught on
whatever
in the earliest days of my
Trading
uh I traded Commodities
and commodities had a tendency to trend
a pretty strong tendency to Trend so
that was a good way to make money you
would just say well if it was up last
week it's likely to be up next week or
so on uh but people gradually caught on
to trending so after uh
several years or maybe
10 years after I started in the business
it the trending in Commodities had uh
completely disappeared the stocks never
trended particularly so there was no
real trending in charge but commodity
killed us and so so that's an example of
a signal
discovering new signals other people uh
might find some of those as well and
that might uh
the effect of that might be but the
signal kind of goes away because too
many people are using it but um
so we have awfully smart people and they
keep coming up with new signals so
that's and we've stayed
you know we've stayed with ahead yeah
so one thing I've always done is do
something new I love to do something new
and I don't like to run with the pack
uh for one thing I'm not such a fast
runner so uh you know if you're one of
end people all working in the same
problem in different places if well me I
know I would I'd be last I you know I'm
not going to win that race but if you
can think of a new problem or a new way
of doing something that other people
aren't all working on at the same time
maybe that'll give you a chance so
do something new
second
collaborate with the best people you
possibly can
when you see a person get to know a
person who seems like a like a great guy
or a great gal to work with in something
try to find a way to do it
because uh that that gives you some
reach and some scope and it's also fun
to work with terrific people
I wrote down here be guided by Beauty
I really mean that I think pretty much
everything I've done has had an
aesthetic component at least to me now
you might think well building a company
that's trading bonds what's so aesthetic
about that but it is what's ecstatic
about it is doing it right
doing it right getting the right kind of
people and approaching the problem and
doing it right
and if you feel that you're the first
one to do it right and I think we were
that's a terrific feeling and it's a
beautiful thing to do something right
it's also a beautiful thing to solve a
math problem or create some mathematics
that people hadn't thought of before so
be be guided by beauty is not such a bad
principle
and then I wrote down
don't give up
uh at least try not to give up
and
sometimes you can it's appropriate to be
at something to be trying to do
something for a hell of a long time
and finally
hope for some good luck
so that's it
okay