[Music]
in the course of my lifetime I developed
a conceptual
framework with the financial crisis it
does have a relevance to other people
for their understanding of this very
complicated
reality thank you very much the
formative experience of my life was the
German occupation of Hungary in
1944 I was not yet 14 years old at the
time coming from the first two lectures
kind of summarize the experience of of
of of my past the concept of reflexivity
provided me with a new way of looking at
financial markets a better way than the
prevailing
Theory the entire edifice of global
financial markets that has been erected
on the false premise that markets can be
left to the their own devices has to be
rebuilt from the ground up the next two
lectures are exploratory new ideas that
I am developing
now open Society can Prevail only when
people can speak truth to power it needs
the rule of law that guarantees freedom
of speech and press freedom of
Association and assembly and other
rights and freedoms
there is a deep seated conflict between
capitalism and open Society Market
values and social values in the end how
a democracy functions depends on the
people who live in
it the fifth lecture is of course the
conclusion that brings it together to
put it
bluntly the United States stands to lose
the most and China is boys to emerge as
the greatest winner there is a growing
belief that the Global Financial system
has once again escaped collapse and we
are slowly returning to business as
usual this in my opinion is a grave
misinterpretation of the current
situation Humpty Dumpty can't be put
together again thank
you it is a summing up of a life
philosophy but it's not a closed system
it's an open system that can develop a
lot more and I hope that other people
will be inspired uh by this approach and
and develop it further
[Music]