good afternoon and welcome to the fifth
and final session in our series of ceu
lectures I'm John shatak president and
director of central European University
we're starting just a little bit late so
we will go a little bit longer Beyond
3:00 I'm sure you'll all agree that this
has been an extraordinary
week and it's been my great privilege
over the course of the week to host
these pathbreaking lectures by George
Soros held here in Budapest at the
Hungarian Academy of Sciences under the
offices of central European University
today we have reached the grand finale
never one to shrink from controversy or
prediction today George Soros will bring
together the themes he has been
exploring throughout the week and turn
his attention to the future he will
outline key Global Trends and discuss
their economic and political
implications as he sees them for the
years ahead focusing in particular on
the increasingly important role that
China is likely to play on the world
stage as we've done throughout the week
we're expanding our audience today far
beyond Budapest and are including
students appropriately from China from
Hong Kong University this will complete
our unprecedented three continent five
University Global Outreach to students
who are participating in these lectures
through interactive video conferencing
in real time our moderator for this
lecture is Howard Davies director of one
of the world's great universities the
London School of economics and political
science whose students were part of our
Global audience on Monday we also have a
distinguished former International
leader here in the front row who will
offer a brief commentary from the floor
uh Christan boar a Brazilian Senator and
former candidate for president Mr Soros
will speak for approximately 50 minutes
following which Mr Davies will briefly
comment Mr Soros will then take
questions starting with three questions
from Hong Kong and then more questions
from the audience here in Budapest and
now to deliver his Fifth and final
lecture I'm delighted once again to
introduce George Soros who will take us
into the future with a grand summation
of his thinking about our
world thank you
in these lectures uh I've offered a
conceptual framework for a better
understanding of human
events these events are not determined
by timelessly valid scientific laws such
laws exist of course but they are not
sufficient to determine the course of
events the complexity of the situations
is one reason and the role of the
participants thinking is
another I have focused on the reflexive
two-way connection between the
participants thinking and reality and I
emphasized the causal role that
misunderstandings and misconceptions
play in shaping
reality but these influences have been
strangely ignored
they introduce an element of uncertainty
into the subject matter which except in
the simplest situations make it
impossible to predict the future one can
still sketch various plausible scenarios
and evaluate their likelihood one can
also prescribe desirable
outcomes I've done both many times
indeed I can claim to be a
specialized a specialist in it uh
focusing on predictions as an investor
and prescriptions as a
philanthropist I've been successful
enough in the former to be able to
afford the
letter I should like to devote today's
discussion to this dual
task we are at a moment in which the
range of uncertainties is unusually wide
we've just passed through the worst
financial crisis since World War I is
quantitatively much larger and
qualitatively different from other
financial
crisis the only relevant comparisons are
with the Japanese uh real estate bubble
which burst in
1991 and from which Japan has still not
recovered
and with the Great Depression of the
1930s what differentiates this crisis
from the Japanese experience is that the
letter was confined to a single country
while this crisis has involved the
entire
world what differentiates it from the
Great Depression is that this time the
financial system was not allowed to
collapse what but was put on artificial
life support
in fact the magnitude of the credit and
leverage problem uh we have today is
even greater than in the
1930s in
1929 total credit outstanding in the
United States was 160% of GDP and it
Rose to
250% by
1932 in 2008 we started
at
365. and this calculation doesn't take
into account the pervasive use of
derivatives which was absent in the
1930s and yet in spite of that the
artificial r support has been successful
barely a year after the bankruptcy of
Leman Brothers financial markets have
stabilized stock markets have rebounded
and the economy is showing signs of
recovery people want to return to
business as usual and think of the crash
of 2008 as a bad
dream I regret to tell you that the
recovery is liable to run out of steam
and may even be followed by a double dip
although I'm not sure whether it will be
in 2010 or
2011 My Views are far from unique but
they are at variance with the prevailing
mood the longer the turnaround lasts the
more people will come to believe in it
but in my judgment the prevailing mood
is far removed from reality this is
characteristic of far from equilibrium
situations when perceptions tend to lag
behind
reality to complicate matters the lag
Works in both directions most people
have not yet realized that this crisis
is different from previous ones that we
are at the end of an era others
including me failed to anticipate the
extent of the
rebound the confusion is not confined to
the financial sphere it extends to the
entire International Arena
after the collapse of the Soviet Empire
the United States emerged as the sole
superpower no other power or combination
of powers could challenge its
Supremacy but the unipolar world didn't
take root when President Bush sought to
assert americ Supremacy by invading Iraq
on false pretenses he achieved the exact
opposite of what he intended the United
States suffered a precipitous decline in
its power and
influence so the disarray in the
International Financial system is
matched by instability in international
relations the New Order that will
eventually emerge will not be dominated
by the United States to the same extent
as the old one
to understand what's happening we need a
this different conceptual framework from
the one to which we have become
accustomed the efficient market
hypothesis looks at financial markets in
isolation and totally disregards
politics but that gives a distorted
picture
as I have pointed out several times
behind the Invisible Hand of markets
there is the visible hand of politics
which establishes the rules and
conditions in which the market mechanism
operates my conceptual framework relates
to the political economy not the market
economy as an abstract construct that is
governed by timelessly valid laws I look
at financial markets as a branch of
History the International Financial
system as it was uh reconstructed after
the second world war didn't create a
Level Playing Field it was lopsided by
Design the international financial
institutions the international monetary
fund and the World Bank were organized
as shareholding companies in which the
rich countries held a disproportionate
share of the votes and also controll the
boards this put the countries at the
periphery at a disadvantage Visa those
at the
center ever since the system has been
dominated by the United
States at the Breton Woods conference
Lord KES proposed but it was the head of
the American delegation Harry white who
disposed since then we have gone from an
almost an almost completely regulated
system to an almost completely
deregulated one but the changes were led
by the United States and the system has
continued to be guided by what has
become known as the Washington
consensus although
the rules laid down by the Washington
consensus consensus are supposed to
apply to all countries equally the
United States as the issuer of the main
International currency is more equal
than the
others effectively the International
System has a two-tier structure
countries that can borrow that can
borrow in their own currency constitute
the center and those whose borrowings
are denominated in one of the hard
currencies constitute the
periphery if individual countries get
into
difficulties they receive assistance but
only on strict
conditions that holds true whether they
are from the center or from the
periphery but if the center itself
becomes endangered then preserving the
system takes precedence over all other
cons
considerations that happened for the
first time in the international banking
crisis of
1982 um if the D dat countries had been
allowed to default the banking system
would have collapsed therefore the
International Financial authorities
baned it together and introduced what I
called the the time the collective
system of
Landing the leaders the lenders were uh
induced to roll over their loans and the
D countries were lent enough additional
money to service their debts the net
effect was that data countries fell into
severe recession Latin America lost a
decade of growth but the banking system
was allowed to earn its way out of a
hole when the banks built up sufficient
reserves the the uh loans were
restructured into so-called Brady bonds
and the
banks uh wrote off their remaining
losses something similar happened again
in
1997 but by then the banks had learned
to securitize their loans so they
couldn't be forced into a collective
system of landing and most of the losses
had to be taken by the data countries
this set the pattern the data countries
were subjected to harsh Market
discipline but when the system was in
danger the nor normal rules were
suspended Banks whose Collective failure
would have endangered the system were
bailed
out the financial crisis of 2007 2008
was different because it originated at
the center and the periphery countries
were drawn into it only after the
bankruptcy of Leman Brothers the MF was
faced with a novel task to protect the
periphery from a storm that originated
at the
center it didn't have enough Capital but
member countries bend it together and
raised a trillion
dollars even so the IMF had some
difficulties in coping with the
situation because it was designed to
deal with problems in the public sector
and the shortage of credit uh was
impacting mainly the private sector but
on the whole the IMF adapted itself to
its novel task uh remarkably
well overall the International
Financial authorities have handled this
crisis the same way as previous ones
they bailed out the failing institutions
and appli Li monetary and fiscal
stimulus but this crisis was much bigger
and at first the same techniques didn't
work the rescue of Leman Brothers
failed that was a game changing
event financial markets actually ceased
to function and had to be put on
artificial life
support this meant that governments had
to effectively guarantee that no other
institution whose failure would endanger
the system would be allowed to
fail that's when the crisis spread to
the periphery because periphery
countries couldn't provide equally
credible
guarantees this time it was Eastern
Europe that was the worst hit the
countries at the center used the balance
sheets of their central banks to pump
money into the system and to guarantee
the liabilities of commercial Banks and
governments engaged in deficit financing
to stimulate the economy on an
unprecedented scale and these measures
have been successful and the global
economy appears to be
stabilizing there is a growing belief
that the Global Financial system has
once again escaped collapse and we are
slowly returning to business as
usual this in my opinion is a grave
misinterpretation of the current
situation Humpty Dumpty can't be put
together again let me explain why
the globalization of financial markets
that took place since the
1980s was a market fundamentalist
project spearheaded by the United States
and the United Kingdom allowing
Financial Capital to move around freely
in the world made it difficult to tax it
or to regulate it this put Financial
capital in a privileged position
governments had to pay more attention to
the requirements of international
Capital than to the aspirations of their
own people because Financial Capital
could move around more freely so as a
market fundamentalist project
globalization was highly successful
individual countries found it difficult
to resist it but the Global Financial
system that emerged was fundamentally
unstable because with it was built on
the false premise that financial markets
can be left safely left to their own
devices that is why it broke down and
that's why it can't be put together
again Global markets need Global
regulations but the regulations that are
currently in force are rooted in the
principle of national sovereignty
there are some International agreements
most notably the Basel Accords on
minimal Capital requirements and there's
also good cooperation among Market
Regulators but the source of the
authority is always the sovereign
state this means that it's not enough to
restart a mechanism that has stall we
need to create a regulatory mechanism
that has never existed
as things stand now the financial system
of each country is being sustained and
supported by its own government the
governments are primarily concerned with
their own economies this stands to give
rise to financial
protectionism which threatens to disrupt
and perhaps destroy the global financial
markets British Regulators will never
again rely on Icelandic authorities and
countries at the periphery will be
reluctant to be entirely dependent on
foreign owned
Banks the point I'm trying to make is uh
that Regulators must be in regulations
must be International in scope without
it financial markets can't remain Global
they would be destroyed by regulatory
Arbitrage businesses would move to the
countries where the regulatory climate
is the most benign and this would expose
other countries to risks they can't
afford to
run globalization was so successful
because it forced all countries to
remove regulations but the process
doesn't work in
Reverse it will be difficult to get
countries to agree un uniform
regulations different countries have
different interests which drive them
towards different
solutions this can be seen in Europe and
if European countries can't agree among
themselves how can the rest of the
world during the crisis Europe couldn't
couldn't reach a europe-wide agreement
on guaranteeing the financial system
each country had to guarantee its own as
things stand now the the um euro is an
incomplete currency it has a common
central bank but it doesn't have a
common Treasury and guaranteeing or
injecting Equity into Banks is a
treasury
function the crisis offered an opport
Unity to remedy this shortfall but
Germany stood in the
way Germany used to be the driving force
behind European integration but that was
at a time when Germany was willing to
pay practically any price for
reunification today Germany is very
different it's a it's at odds with the
rest of the world in fearing inflation
rather than recession and above all it
doesn't want to serve as the deep pocket
for the rest of Europe without a driving
force European integration has ground to
a
halt
fortunately Europe had the benefit of
the social safety
net it had held down European growth
rates in good times but it served its
purpose in the downturn and the
recession in euroland turned out to be
less severe than expected now that the
fears of an economic coll collapse have
subsided the European Union is showing
some signs of political
Revival for instance the European
Central Bank has effectively bailed out
the Irish banking system and Ireland has
resoundingly endorsed the L
treaty so perhaps I should not be so
pessimistic about
Europe the fact that the financial
crisis is having long-term different
long-term impacts on different countries
may turn out to be more of a problem in
the short term all countries were
negatively affected but in the long term
there will be winners and losers
although the range of uncertainties for
the actual course of events is very wide
shifts in relative positions can be
predicted with greater
certainty to put it
bluntly the United States stands to lose
the most and China is poised to emerge
as the greatest
winner the extent of the shift is
already exceeding most expectations
there will be significant changes in the
relative positions of other countries as
well but from a Global Perspective the
one between the United States and China
is the most
significant the United States has been
at the center of the International
Financial system ever since the second
world war the dollar has served as the
main International currency and the
United States has derived immense
benefits from that position but lately
it has abused its privilege starting in
the 19 1980s it has built up an ever
increasing current account
deficit this could have continued
indefinitely because the Asian tigers
first under the leadership of Japan and
now of China were willing to finance
that deficit by building up their dollar
Holdings but the excessive indebtness of
the United States households brought the
process to an end when the housing
bubble burst households found themselves
overextended the banking system has
suffered tremendous losses and has to
earn its way out of a whole in
commercial real estate and leverage
buyouts the blood leting is Yet to Come
the these factors will continue to weigh
on the American economy and the American
Consumer will no longer be able to serve
as the as the motor for the world
economy to some extent China may be able
to take its place China has been the
primary beneficiary of
globalization and it has been largely
insulated from the financial crisis for
the West ER in and the United States in
particular the crisis was an internally
generated event which led to the
collapse of the financial system for
China it was an external shock which has
hurt exports but left the financial
political and economic system
unscathed China has discovered a
remarkably efficient method of
unleashing the
creative acquisitive and entrepreneurial
energies of the people who are allowed
to pursue their
selfin while the state can cleam off a
significant portion of the Surplus value
of their labor by maintaining an
undervalued currency and accumulating a
a a trade
surplus so China is likely to emerge as
the big
winner now now China is not a
democracy and the rulers know that they
must a uh avoid social unrest if they
want to remain the rulers therefore
they'll do anything in their power to
maintain economic growth at 8% or more
and create new jobs for a growing work
Workforce and they have plenty of power
because of the trade surplus China can
stimulate its domestic economy through
infrastructure Investments and it can
foster its exports by investing in and
extending credit to their trading
partners after all that's what China was
doing when it was financing it exports
to America by buying US government bonds
now that the American consumers have to
cut back they can do the same with other
countries
so China will be a positive force in the
world economy while the United States
will be limping
along the Chinese economy is of course
much smaller than the United States with
a smaller motor the world economy is
like likely to move forward at a slower
Pace but Within These limits a tectonic
shift is taking place between between
the United States and China with third
parties reorienting themselves to the
source of positive
impulses the shift may not be permanent
or
irreversible just think of the rise and
fall of China Inc but at the present
moment it constitutes the most
predictable and significant Trend in the
global political
economy and China is pulling its trading
partners like Brazil and some African
and Asian countries along with it India
is also doing well based on domestic
growth the success of Chinese Economic
Policy can't be taken for
granted the infrastructure investment in
the Chinese Hinterland may or may not
generate self- sustaining economic
growth under the Chinese system the
return on new Investments is generally
very low because investment decisions
are dictated by political rather than
commercial
considerations on the previous two
occasions the relaxation of bank credit
has produced a Spate of bad loans
this time it may be different because
there has been a shift in power from the
regional to the central authorities and
the local officials of the banks are no
longer uh under the control of the local
provincial authorities but success can't
be taken for granted moreover China may
be dragged down by a global so slowdown
but if China flounders the global
economy loses its motor therefore the
relative success of China is more
assured than its absolute
success we are at a moment in history
which in some ways is comparable to the
end of the second world war then the
prevailing system had actually collapsed
and the new one had to be built from
scratch at Breton Woods the Victorious
Powers approved equal to the task
inspired mainly by Lord KES they built a
system that could accommodate the entire
world even if the United States was more
equal than others now now the prevailing
multilateral system call it
International capitalism didn't fully
collapse but it has been greatly
weakened its inherent flaws have been
revealed and is challenged by a viable
alternative the rise of China offers a
fundamentally different form of economic
organization than the current
International Financial system it may be
given the label of State capitalism as
distinct from the international
capitalism championed by the Washington
consensus we are at the end of an era
but we are not fully aware of
it the two forms of economic
organization State capitalism and
international capitalism are in
competition with each other neither of
them is
attractive the Washington consensus has
failed International capitalism in his
present form has proven itself
inherently unstable because it lacks
adequate regulation it's also highly
unjust because it favors the haves over
the Have
Nots at the same time an international
system based on state capitalism would
inevitably lead to conflicts between
states the first sign of conflict are
already beginning to surface because
ironically China is repeating the
mistakes of the colonial powers in
dealing with the countries that are rich
in natural resources just at a time when
the colonial Powers have learned from
their past mistakes and are trying to
rectify
them in order to gain access to Natural
Resources China is dealing with the
rulers and neglecting the people this
helps oppressive and corrupt regimes to
stay in power this is an undesirable
outcome but China is not the only one to
be blamed for it when a Chinese company
tried to buy Unocal the American Oil
Company it was rebuffed and more
recently riotinto reneged on a deal to
sell an interest to a Chinese company
this has pushed China into dealing with
those countries that the International
Financial in institutions have shunned
Burma Sudan Zimbabwe and the Congo and
Angola they stand out Guinea uh is the
latest
example uh where uh there's been a riot
with 150 people killed and China has
extended a loan of $7
billion this is becoming a source of
considerable friction which is not in
the best interest of China later on the
rest of the world but China considers
itself the grief party and Rel is
remains reluctant to join the extractive
Industries transparency initiative this
has become become the biggest obstacle
to the continued success of that
initiative while the prevailing
multilateral system will try to
reconstitute itself China will expand on
a bilateral basis China is of course
part of the multilateral system but it
doesn't occupy within that system a
position
that is Comm measur it with its current
and anticipated prospective strength
therefore it its participation in the
international financial institutions is
rather passive and its active expansion
is lying to go through bilateral
challenge for instance China will uh
complain about the role of the dollar
and will promote the role of speci
special drawing rights but it's unlikely
to allow the remin to become freely
convertible because that would destroy
the mechanism that has allowed the state
to harvest the fruits of cheap Chinese
labor through an undervalued
currency China will continue to maintain
Capital controls but will establish
bilateral clearing accounts denominated
in Remi with countries like Brazil
this will diminish the status of the
dollar as the international currency
without actually replacing
it to sum up the world is facing a
choice between two fundamentally
different forms of
organization we may label them
International capitalism and state
capitalism the former represented by the
United States has broken down and the
letter represented by China is in the
ascendant the path of least least
resistance leads to the gradual
disintegration of the International
Financial system as we know it yet a
system of bilateral relations is liable
to generate conflicts between
states a new multilateral system based
on and Sounder principles needs to be
invented that would serve the best
interests of both the United States and
China and of course the rest of the
world now while International
cooperation is almost impossible to
achieve on a peaceful basis it may be
attainable in a gr Grand bargain where
the entire Financial order is rearranged
the emergence of the G20 as the primary
Forum of international cooperation and
the peer review process adopted at the
Pittsburgh meeting are steps in the
right
direction but the G20 has to operate
within the confines of the Articles of
Association of the IMF as they are
currently because changing the articles
is a long drawn AR
process this is what a New Breton Woods
conference could accomplish in one f
swop it would reconstitute the IMF to
better reflect the prevailing packing
order among states and revise its
methods of
operation it would decide how to treat
financial institutions that are too big
to fail and it would consider new rules
to control capital mve movements because
the total freedom of financial Capital
to move around freely in the world has
proved to be a source of instability and
needs to be
corrected the use of the dollar as the
main International currency has produced
dangerous
imbalances the dollar is no longer no
longer enjoys the trust and confidence
it once did yet no other currency is in
a position to take its place there is a
general flight from currencies into gold
and other Commodities and tangible
assets that's harmful because it keeps
those assets out of productive use and
Stokes the fears of
inflation the United States ought not to
shy away from The Wider use of special
drawing rights
sdrs uh that should induce China to
abandon it back to the dollar and that
would be the best way to reduce
International
imbalances since sdrs are denominated in
several National currencies no single
currency would enjoy an unfair
Advantage the range of currencies
included in the sdrs would have to be be
widened and some of the newly added
currencies which would in include the
rembe may not be fully
convertible therefore the dollar could
still reestablish itself as the preser
as the preferred Reserve currency
provided is properly prudently
managed one of the great advantages of
sdrs is that they allow the
international creation of money that
would be particularly useful at times
like the
present the money could be directed to
where it is most needed that would be a
gr great improvement over what's
happening
currently a mechanism which would allow
rich countries that don't need
additional reserves to transfer their
allocations to those who need them is
readily available and has already been
used on a small
scale the
reorganization of the prevailing World
Order uh uh may have to extend uh behind
beyond the financial system if we are to
make progress in resolving issues like
global warming and nuclear proliferation
it may have to involve the United
Nations especially membership of the
security
Council this uh rather profound process
needs to be initiated by the United
States but China and other developing
countries ought to participate in it as
equals they are reluctant members of the
brettonwoods institutions which are
dominated by countries that are no
longer dominant the the rising Powers
need to be present at the creation of
the new order to ensure that there'll be
active supporters of
it now why should the United States
initiate changes in a system of which it
had been the main
beneficiary because the system can't
survive in its present form and the
United States has more to lose uh if it
is not in front Forefront of reforming
it America lost a lot of power and
influence during the bush presidency
without farsighted leadership the
relative position of the United States
is like likely to continue
eroding the United States is still in a
position to lead the world it can no
longer impose its will on others as the
Bush Administration sought to do but it
could lead a a Cooperative effort which
would involve not only the developed but
also the developing world this would
reestablish American leadership in an
acceptable
form now why should China submit to a
new multilateral system in view of the
fact that it is set to emerge as the
winner from the current turmoil the
answer is equally simple in order to
continue Rising it must make itself
acceptable to the rest of the world that
means that it must move towards a more
open Society uh um combining an
increased measure of individual Freedom
with the rule of
law given the current military power
relations China can continue Rising only
in a peaceful environment where the rest
of the world willing accept the rise of
China it's even more important for the
sake of a peaceful world that the United
States should find its proper place in a
new world world order a declining
superpower losing both political and
economic dominance but still preserving
military
Supremacy is a dangerous mix and as I've
tried to show democracy is in deep
trouble in America the financial crisis
has inflicted hardship on a population
that doesn't like har to face harsh
reality President Obama has deployed the
confidence multiplier and claims to have
contained the recession if there is a d
a double dip the population will become
susceptible to all kinds of
fear-mongering and populist
demagogy if President Obama fails the
next Administration will be sorely
tempted to create diversions from
troubles at home and that could be very
dangerous for the
world President Obama has the right
Vision but he needs to be more
farsighted he believes in international
cooperation rather than the bush Cheney
idea of Might is right but he is pre
preoccupied with many pressing problems
Reinventing the International Financial
system is not high on his agenda some of
his economic advisers still seem to
believe that the efficient market
hypothesis is valid except once in a 100
years the financial institutions that
have survived are are in a stronger
competitive position than ever before
and they will resist a systemic overhaul
that would curve their
powers what is lacking is a general
recognition that the system is broken
and needs to be reinvented that's why it
would be so important that the theory of
financial markets I've outlined in these
lectures should gain wider acceptance
the Chinese leadership would need to be
even more F farsighted than President
Obama they are in the driver's seat and
if they moved towards a more open
Society they would have to give give up
some of their
privileges right now the Chinese public
is willing to subordinate individual
freedom to political stability and
economic advancement but that may not
continue
indefinitely corruption is a big problem
and China needs the rule of law so that
citizens can criticize the government
and prevent it from abusing it Powers
its powers and China needs to become a
more open Society in order to be
acceptable to the rest of the world the
rest of the world will never subordinate
the freedom of the individual to the
prosperity of the the Chinese
State as China is becoming a world
leader it must learn to pay more
attention to the opinion of the rest of
the world but all this may be happening
too fast for the Chinese leadership to
adjust to it China is accustomed to
think to thinking of itself as a as the
victim of
imperialism so it doesn't realize that
is beginning to occupy an imperialistic
position that's why it has such
difficulties in De in dealing with
Africa and its own ethn ethnic
minorities hopefully the Chinese
leadership will rise to the occasion
it's no exaggeration to say that the
future of the world depends on it thank
you
[Applause]