I know that the principle of fallibility
and reflexivity is against making
predictions so I'll try to make a
prediction anyway and my prediction is
that everybody who is interested in the
thinking of George Soros should come
back to these lectures I do believe this
was uh one of the most intensive type of
rethinking your all Philosophy for the
last 20 years and nothing has done more
than on the concept of open Society I
have been rereading yesterday the book
opening the Soviet system that he been
basically wrote 20 years ago and then
the situation looks slightly more clear
you have the open Society by the way the
open society and this is very much
according to also poer was based on the
idea of a democracy inhabited by a
scientists critically thinking people in
a very critical mode which experimenting
with the idea and not being afraid of
failing
and of course this type of a
confrontation between open society and
close Society was a formative experience
for Our Generation I do believe we're
going to a much more difficult period in
which Carl poper Met car Ro and the
problem of a simple theonomy between
open society and closed Society is not
as useful as it was so as a result of it
I'm very grateful to George Soros for
making this uh type of talk and I just
want to make three points and ask two
questions the first point is very much
about this manipulative function poer
himself at the end of his life became
obsessed with
television all his latest interviews
have been attack on television but he
never went to attack his concept because
it is not about television this is about
liberal rationalism how rational it
could be it's very much the
enlightenment fallacy and he basically
decided to stay with it I do believe
that what uh uh Mr Soros has done today
first of all is much more intellectually
honest being between two fallaces the
enlightenment fallacy and the postmodern
fallacy this is the problem of a moral
and tragic choice where you stand nobody
can simply say one is fallacy and the
other is not a fallacy but you need a
kind of a religion of your own and this
tragic nature of modern liberalism in my
view is something to be stressed against
a very naive type of uh things which
basically believe that liberalism is
natural and self- obvious and nothing to
be done the second problem is all these
arguments which are coming with the
postmodern fallacy are not new ones if
you go back to history pl's criticism of
democracy is very much about the rule of
the sophists people who are not
interested in truth who simply try to
persuade the others and honestly
speaking it's much easier to talk truth
to power than to talk truth to the
voters and from this point of view
rethinking electoral democracy in terms
of open Society I see as the major
Challenge and from this point of view
this lecture is very different from many
that we have heard uh before but if this
is the case I have three questions the
first has a lot to do with the problem
of politics and I in government
comparing your lecture from yesterday
and your lecture today yesterday you put
much more trust in government in
regulating economy now when we know how
much the manipulative function have
taken precedence in politics how sure
you are that the government is going to
fulfill the function that you subscribe
to this when it comes to the economy and
second is when we know now that it's not
only the cognitive function but this is
also the manipulative function are you
in a mood to rethink the way you have
been supporting education or the way you
working with media in your foundations
because basically part of the supremacy
of the education was also part of the
Enlightenment view of the world it was
enough to educate the people to inform
them the informed citizen was the ideal
now the citizen can be informed but he
can be informed in a very manipulative
way so in a certain way I do believe
that you're coming to a radical moment
in which we so much used to take
democracy and open Society for granted
that it takes your talk to start asking
questions which ass so that we have
forgotten the answers thank you very
[Applause]
much I W comment we can open it up you
can open it yeah so but this was I do
believe also there are going to be much
more important questions that are going
to come from the audience like yesterday
we're going to give the Precedence to
New York and to the Colombia University
students who are there so they're going
to have the first three questions
please gas I'm the senior associate Dean
here at Columbia School of International
and public affairs and I'd like to thank
you first for including us in this telec
conference it's an honor for us to be
involved and thank you on behalf of Dean
John coatsworth we have a number of
students who have interesting questions
prepared for you I'd like to invite them
to come up to the podium and join me and
to introduce
themselves as they present their
questions the first student who I'd like
to ask to come to the podium is Miss
Joe please join me
here thank
you hi Mr sorus my name is San Jo I'm a
first year student at Columbia um
University School of International
public affairs I was born in Beijing and
uh um I read your theory about uh
reflexivity before I have a two quick
questions for you um first one is
um you mentioned the term the pursuit of
knowledge which I agree that it takes
willingness and um in my opinion
tremendous commitment but more
importantly I think it takes significant
resources too for example I need to pay
for Columbia to to listen to your
lecture today and um but for the
majority of the population people don't
have enough resources especially
economic
resources and to pursue the reality
that's that's why political machine has
room to man manipulate sorry so in your
opinion is there any solution to this
problem for example by devot by devoting
more resources perhaps more than
manipulative power spans to promote the
open Society
so there was a very interesting question
coming yeah so probably we should answer
question by question because she's yeah
she's very much interested when you
don't have an access to education and
cannot get knowledge how you can defend
yourself from the manipulative uh Power
of the governments and how you see the
solution of this yeah well o o
obviously
education is very education of the
electorate is very important in
developing an open society and and uh
access to education is an important
requirement uh and
basically uh many countries accept uh
most developed countries accept that
responsibility in in in recent years
there's been an increasing tendency to
charge fees this is in uh in in Europe
uh
and but only at the at the at the
University uh level and I think that
there ought to
be uh I mean you could argue that people
who get a university education get a leg
up in the world that it's proven that
their uh income afterwards is is uh
substantially higher than others so uh
uh maybe they ought to pay for that
privilege but maybe they ought to pay
for it later so uh so um in a way in
America uh you have universities that
give scholarships and and uh but collect
from alumni and I think that's a very
good system actually uh um so uh I'm I'm
all in favor of of of of uh making
education more widely widely available
uh but it may be appropriate for uh for
you know to have student loans available
that has been abused in
America uh so it is a it is a it is an
issue how can one provide the the the
best educational opportunities equality
of opportunity in education thank you
very much you have a second
question yes and um my second question
has something to do with China so when
it comes to China the culture of this
country emphasized Central Authority
since more than 2500 years
ago um and so far it seems to have
limited impact on its economic growth
and equality of foreign
policies so my question is in the long
run do you think the clash between
manipul manipulative power and public
awareness reality will influence
China and the structure of the world
it's it's a very good question about
China years ago it was going to be
question about Russia too and it was
about the political culture and to
certain extent where political culture
is going to stay in your definition of
the open Society because the question
here was where do you see the trend is
China is going to overcome this culture
of a centralized government and very
much much more obedient relations to
power yes no I mean you you you're
absolutely right that the history of of
China is an imperial history with the
ruler having a lot of power and and the
subjects uh being subjected
to various kinds
of rules uh some more harsh than others
uh and it is to be hoped that China will
develop into a more open society as it
as it gains a power and influence in in
the in the world uh because uh I think
that there is in China a great desire
and need for stability it's because of
the history of of China people are very
concerned about maintaining
stability um and that of course relies
on the state power so China today cannot
yet be considered an open
Society uh but as China becomes a a an
influential great power in the world and
it needs to be accepted by the rest of
the world and and the Chinese
leadership will have to pay more
attention to what the rest of the world
thinks about China because that is the
way for China to to rise and become more
influential thank you very much for your
questions probably two more questions
from Colombia from New
York uh good morning and uh good evening
for you uh thank you very much for your
lecture it was very interesting my name
is Alexander iluk and I'm a gradate
student of School of International
Affairs here at Colombia I'm from
Ukraine and I have a question uh how uh
do you see the way a society can evolve
into avoiding manipulative mode of
government and what is the role of int
intellectual Elites in that process how
do you see
this the question was what is the role
of the intellectual leads to prevent
this rise of manipulative governments
and this a question of somebody who
comes from Ukraine so he knows what he
speaks
about I I I think your question is very
very relevant because I I firmly believe
that an open Society does need an
intellectual Elite and that is not a
very
popular
um idea today uh because because
everything is tends towards
egalitarianism uh and I think that is
the that is actually uh uh dangerous uh
for an open Society because you have one
person one vote right but the
educational level the level of
understanding seriousness Etc of
different people is not not the same and
therefore there there needs to be
well-informed people people who are
concerned with with the with the with
the public interest who take more
interest Express their views and their
views gain some
respect
um in in in England uh basically
democracy developed uh under the careful
guide guidance and of the
aristocracy uh people who who held
themselves to pretty high
standards and and so on um and they had
also the Leisure to to be concerned with
public affairs um and um I think we need
more of that uh because these issues are
not that easy to understand and and um
if if U now with the various
uh methods of uh of uh well of of uh
reaching the broad public um the
intellectuals the elite is more
concerned manipulating reducing messages
to a level where it gets a lot of
traction so uh the elite has to have a a
a commitment to The Pursuit Of Truth and
then it has to have influence in the in
the general public I think that is those
are the conditions that you actually
need for a flourishing open Society
thank you very much and one more
question from New York after that we're
going to come to buest and probably
we'll go back to New York
later oh hi I'm I'm Matthew flag I'm a
second year PhD student in the economics
Department um Mr Soros you mentioned
that in order for an open Society to
function the the cognitive function of
our thinking must take precedence over
the manipulative
function but as we've discussed those
who espouse the manipulative function
seem dedicated to the end of suppressing
the objective reality u in your view uh
beyond the role of Education as we've
already discussed is it an achievable
goal go to have the majority of people
in a society dedicated to the pursuit of
Truth and uh if so uh how can we go
about achieving this goal in the face of
opposition to the truth from the
manipulators do you believe perhaps that
the media could could play a role in
this and how could they go about uh
doing
this media no uh Pato is going to be I
do believe uh happy to listen to this
question because the question was do you
expect that they are going to be the
majority of the TR seekers in society
and if they're not going to be such a
majority Beyond education where you're
going to see the solution what what
should be the role of the media and
basically what is the role of the media
well let me take a very
elitist point of view and I think that
even a very small percentage of the
population that that is uh genuinely
concerned with the public interest uh
can make a big difference uh because you
could see that the competition between
the various political views usually
bring you very very close to
50% uh it's interesting question why
that is but there is a convergence
around the 50/50 split and it's a very
very narrow so uh
uh difference that actually wins or
loses votes so if you just
have just a few percent that is
particularly
say is concerned with the pursuit of
Truth uh it could make a a tremendous
difference now the question of of of of
media is a very very troubling question
because media has two functions on the
one hand it's an
indispensable uh uh element in an open
Society it has an Institutional role U
on the other hand it's a
business and as a business it has to
cater to the
demand and if there is no demand for
serious information
uh but for
entertainment
then the media that is going to be
popular and read by a lot of people or
listened to by a lot of people is not
going to be concerned with serious
discussion of Affairs so in the end it
really does come down to the
electorate thank you very much we're
going to buest but is we heard there is
a good news for you you don't need a
majority of Truth stickers you should
have them only in The Swinging States
so so uh please let's go let's go with
the questions uh from
buest please M there is a question
here thank you I actually covered the
2004 election as a reporter so in a
sense I'm on both sides of this question
representative of the media and I hope
some kind of Truth seek
uh I'm afraid though that my verdict uh
at least from my experience covering
that election is going to be a bit
dismaying uh with with respect to what
you've told us here today I was struck
again and again when I interviewed
people uh at rallies particularly at
rallies for George W bush uh and I'm
talking about educated people uh people
who read the New York Times every day
and so on the number of times I would be
told for example that weapons of mass
destruction were were found in Iraq uh
and these again were not bited people
they read the Press uh they were
perfectly able to read in the press that
weapons were not found but I gradually
came to the view that our whole model of
how people understand politics very
often is wrong we tend to think of it as
a kind of inductive process by which
people gather facts and then make a
judgment about a political candidate or
a policy according to how it conforms to
the truth of those facts and in fact I
found again and again that people would
begin with a belief in this case a
belief in George W bush and his
leadership and then they would assemble
the facts to Accord with that original
belief and when they came to a conflict
that was particularly strong and the
fact that weapons of mass destruction
having served as the uh occasion or the
reason for the war were then not found
when they came to that kind of strong
conflict they simply rejected it out of
hand uh and I saw this and heard this so
much and from people who were again
educated had critical faculties of the
sort that you've just described uh had
been to the elite schools in the United
States that it struck me very strongly
that um much of the way we think about
how people make decisions about politics
May well be wrong I'm sorry that's a
long way to get to the point of if
indeed my conclusion or what I
discovered is true what are the
implications for your view of the open
society and what's necessary to it but
actually I would be interested in your
conclusions uh from your
uh experience but I I do think that at
around that time there was
really an a an increased uh disregard
for facts in the information that people
people were getting and there was a the
propaganda machine that was uh uh
parading as legitimate media uh you know
Fox
television uh their motto was uh uh what
was it
uh fair and balanced or fair and
balanced which was an Ian statement uh
um and it did actually mislead
people um because they were getting this
information as if it was information and
it was
deliberate uh misstatement of facts so
and you it you had it from politicians
like like vice president Cheney who had
absolutely no hesitation
uh saying things uh that were actually
untrue so uh um coming from
authoritative
sources it I think it did s the public
uh now you could say that the public is
responsible because they put up with it
uh and I think they are but I think that
this was a particularly dark period
in in in uh in American public discourse
I don't know whether you'd agree with
that but that's that certainly was was
my
impression thank you very
much
please thank you very much my question
is very simple do you believe that the
pursuit of Truth leads to an education
for truth and this leads for moral
values on
education not
necessarily not not not
necessarily
uh I
personally seem to have this
uh
particular Quest or or or or or U
emotional commitment but but I think
it's easy to
have different set of
values and and
um if you've been reasonably
successful
um living a myth uh that you have
created then there's nothing to stop you
from doing it so it's not that that's
exactly otherwise if if the truth
eventually uh uh uh had to convince you
then of course people would be convinced
that the problem wouldn't be there so
actually and
particularly since when it comes to
Natural phenomena we have
learned that uh you know Illusions don't
work as well as as uh as um a proper
understanding of the laws of nature you
know
starting with the
Alchemists you know who used incantation
to try to make uh uh gold out of Base
metals and you know they never
succeeded human Affairs are
different you can actually succeed
that's the whole point of what makes
what why reflexivity makes human
Affairs so very different
you know if the Alchemist if they had
been active in the financial markets uh
they would probably be
prospering uh because you can actually
change Reality by incantation so that's
how human Affairs are different from
natural Affairs and so you don't the
truth doesn't have the same convincing
power because it can itself be modified
it can be
manipulated and that's really why we
have this
problem thank you very much there was
two questions there
please I was actually very disturbed by
this uh this idea of manipulative
function I actually lived through both
2004 and 2008 elections in the US as a
foreigner and my what what Stroke Me In
Your in your speech in your lecture was
that you did not mention um the 2008
campaign and the Obama strategy which
was profoundly man manipulative by your
definition I mean it was obviously truth
but it was truth well told and I think
because of the wellt element it was so
persuasive that's why Obama beat Senator
Clinton in the primaries and then was so
strongly positioned in the general
election if if you agree that there was
an element of Charisma and manipulation
and selling the truth in in in his
campaign then there is a real dilemma
because obviously to change the society
away from
manipulative State we need to gain
political power but to do this we need
to join the game of manipul ating and
then it is a a a moral problem that I
would like to know how to explain to my
students here no I I I would have
to I I really have to differ from you
because yeah clearly uh Obama had
political advisors and they were telling
him what to say and what not to say and
and so on but there was a very different
attitude that
Obama expressed and he treated C the
electorate as intelligent people and
talk to them as intelligent people now
he wasn't widely heard but the the tone
and the intention and and the standards
that he applied were really to
me actually remarkably
uh um different from the other
side
uh the difference was in' 08 was was as
great as it was in ' 04 in in now I may
be biased so I in fact I am biased
nevertheless I believe this to be true
so however of
course you
you you can't avoid taking into account
uh the fact
that people's perceptions can be
manipulated and I think if you if you
disregard it you have no chance of
getting
elected thank you very much before going
there I remember politicians from the
Communist period on this talk on
manipulation who used to say we are
saying the truth only the truth but not
the whole truth so from this point of
there is a question there
[Music]
hello Alexander alunan U Moscow one of
Moscow universities and now seeu uh
visiting researcher um let me be in kind
of uh advocate for Dil uh for deil
uh founding fathers didn't promise
person of Truth they just promised
person of happiness and
Freedom isn't isn't it enough or was it
wrong I mean uh
is was they understandable I mean they
didn't they didn't say nothing about
person of Truth they said that um every
man every man could person the happiness
and every man is free
so maybe it's
enough or we should just should uh
person the
truth I had problem yeah the question
wasn't of course it's interesting one he
said when you have been referring to the
founding fathers the founding fathers
said nothing about the truth they were
about pursuing of happiness and freedom
do you need truth in order to be free
and happy this is the question in a way
I got it here
I definitely think so um because because
of this the um uh the importance of
understanding
reality uh in order
to uh uh be able to lead a successful
life you know uh um U make an impact on
reality the way
uh get the results that you want as
opposed to
unintended adverse consequences so to
eliminate to reduce the adverse
consequences you need to understand and
you need to understand that in the case
of human Affairs reality is not a a
passive Target that you shoot at it's a
moving Target yet and how people
perceive it and how people act changes
the reality that you have to deal with
so it's the reality in human Affairs is
much more difficult to understand but
nevertheless you need
to understand it in order to narrow the
Divergence between your intentions and
expectations on the one hand and the
outcome on the other
that's the same in both in dealing with
nature and with Humanity but but in case
of human Affairs is much more difficult
because it's a moving
Target because reality can in fact be
manipulated thank you very much
Professor
[Music]
gbor George I I loved your lecture I
would like to make a a few comments
disagreeing with you but I had to make a
comment about uh our last uh questioner
the expression happiness in the
Declaration of
Independence is much closer to the
French philicity and really meaning
Public Welfare to a very large extent so
this is not individual happiness it is
liberty and public welfare and of course
Public Welfare immediately gets us back
to the pursuit of Truth and I I have
really no question uh that the framers
uh the founding fathers were deeply
Enlightenment characters per uh
committed to The Pursuit Of
Truth so George I I have U uh uh a com I
have a couple of comments one is uh
about
elections well I think elections have
been chural democracy is the worst form
of government except for all others
elections have been incredibly
problematic for whenever we have had
genuine elections let us say for the
last 100 years and talk about the
manipulative function here in Hungary uh
we just had a rather extreme example
recently uh of that in an election
campaign never mind of course Hitler
Etc
so what the electorate does in response
to politicians who as you said want to
be reelected or want to get office and
who highly manipulative in many ways is
um never to be quite known but I'm my my
own experience over the last decades has
led me to believe if elections come out
the right way we are very lucky it is
then those few percent you just
mentioned but on the whole electors are
vastly
overtaxed in making complex decisions
about what the facts are or what the
policy policies should be Health policy
let us say or take any such thing so
that gets me to the other side of open
society and where I am in complete
agreement with you and uh which I think
has for me become vastly more important
in a way than elections I obviously
believe we have to have elections and
I'm all for them and I vote regularly uh
but the conditions freedom of speech
freedom of Association access to Media
all of those things that can help us in
the pursuit of Truth uh are for me have
become over the years much more
important uh uh really uh uh than uh uh
the electoral process as such which is
also so confined by artificial arrang
Arrangements about majorities and what
have you so it is really the Vigor of AI
Civil
Society not necessarily using the term
the way it is fashionable these days but
the Vigor of a civil society that is our
only hope and there I think as a matter
of fact the United States comes out very
well because we still have a society
where lots and lots of people dig for
the facts pursue the truth use the
Freedom of Information Act and so on and
uh
and show the bush lies for what they
were
so that's it it was a
common I agree with you entirely on the
importance of the
institutions and and uh and in fact
elections can often be a detriment to to
uh the development of those institutions
in some of the countries that I have
foundations uh uh take country like
Kazakhstan there is no way that the
ruling group is going to allow another
group to take possession of of of the
state when the there's so much oil there
and so much revenue and and so much is
at stake so so actually elections very
often just uh more or less push the
regime into repression uh when uh
without elections they might actually be
more relaxed I mean this is a rather
unorthodox view but uh I don't think
that elections do much good in those
countries so I entirely agree with you
and yet gradually you could
see a country like Kazakhstan exactly
because it does have uh uh natural
resources perhaps develop the
institutions that will eventually lead
to a democratic elections even uh so uh
but on the other point that you make uh
that uh really elections don't matter
that much I think there has been a a
change in America in the structure of of
uh the political parties
because with the two- party
system
uh
the Dynamics were always for both
parties to try to capture the middle in
order to gain a
majority and then
about roughly 25 years ago a little
longer than that 30 what years ago uh
the Republican party
was basically uh came under the
influence of uh people with the Fairly
extreme views who uh moved the country
further towards their views and did not
move towards a compromise position and
then the the Democrats tried to capture
the middle so they moved more and more
towards certain ideology I call it
Market fundamentalism and but that's
only part of it because of course in the
case of the Bush Administration it had
to do with military power and and Etc
and the the uh the uh uh unitary
presidency so the the Presidential Power
so at any rate instead of two parties
moving towards the middle you had one
party moving further and further to the
right whatever that may be uh and the
other party trying to capture it and the
whole political scene shifted very
radically
during our lifetime in in in America
thank you very much and therefore the
elections became more
important uh before you know so it was
one party or the other it didn't make
that much difference and they were
basically certain values as well as
institutions you mentioned the
importance of Institutions but I think
certain values of
uh you know public probity which may
have been hypocritical but nevertheless
they were the supposed values that were
guiding the people just you make a
commment probably elections could be a
fertile fallacy because if you see the
elections in places like Ukraine 2005
and others even elections that are
perceived as failing can mobilize public
energy so from this point of view I do
believe that elections really has a
problem of their own but unfortunately I
cannot see what is going to replace them
for the the moment so
please hello I'm Ellen Hume I'm an
anenberg fellow at ceu's Center on media
and communication studies you've taken
us on quite a journey with your lectures
so far and today in particular when you
were talking about the fate of our
political culture not just in America
but much more broadly it was a pretty
sad a pretty tragic picture of culture
today and what I'm trying to smoke out
is whether you're a pessimist or an
optimist and before you answer I want to
couch it in a little context I've just
returned from two African countries
where I've been trying to craft
arguments very similar to what your
wonderful foundations have done about
why governments should allow Free Press
and free speech and one of the arguments
actually I heard a little bit of in your
talk today and that was that governments
that live by Propaganda tend to start
believing their own propaganda and
therefore the objective reality comes
and gets them in the end so is there a
hope in your mind or maybe I am too
hopeful that our culture will shift yet
again to a more reality-based operation
since there is Ultimate failure like
death built into to the propaganda
machine no I'm very hopeful that it will
actually and I don't think that it's a
one way Street of decline you know and
and the past was not as glorious as I
may have implied in my speech I think
there were periods of of of uh uh when
things were working very well in certain
countries and then they
declined uh I I was I've been rather
shocked by the decline in
America um and that's that's genuinely I
I feel that and and it was a surprise to
me I think that the whole Bush
phenomenon was a shock to me because you
know I came
from
Hungary where America was looked up you
know with the there a certain idealistic
view of America as being the
of democracy and and and and so on so uh
it was it was and I think that there is
actually uh something that has gone
wrong and needs to be
corrected uh I think the the fact that
Obama was elected was a
tremendous change and yet I'm troubled
that the public opinion hasn't shifted
did as as much as the fact that a
totally different kind of president was
elected uh and the the political
discourse hasn't changed all that much
uh so there is I think
something uh
seriously wrong in America today but it
doesn't mean that the world is going to
H in a basket or that the past was
always wonderful thank you there is a
question there in Bulgaria we try to
believe that the pessimist is somebody
who believes that it cannot be worse but
The Optimist knows that it could
be okay I am from CU I am a doctor uh
student in law and I am also from
Kenya um my question relates to what um
you seem to be um concluding in terms of
uh uh back to the founding
fathers um why I I I am I'm a bit
troubled with that is because um much as
they were saying about self-evident
truths they belong to a particular class
uh their truths did not include the
Africans who are who they they still
enslaved their truth did not include for
for instance even women or there were it
was specific
truths um and yet that is where you kind
of fall back um and looking at American
society you would see you would say it's
an American society American society has
been kind of open but internally perhaps
when you look at its foreign policy
there is nothing open about it it is the
one that has been preaching in my
country for instance that uh Kenya about
U Market fundamentalism that you're
talking about that has caused a lot of
problems um here at see you I'm
grappling with the question of uh
enforcement of social economic rights so
my question to to you is um how open is
this concept to other realities that
perhaps um that there are so many people
who could be excluded from a
participation because of uh deprivations
and all that and yet Perhaps the main
talk I hear is about okay Free Press
free uh the civil and political rights
perhaps neglecting the I mean the the
social economic right and I understand
of course coming from the Communist
system communic realities it's perhaps
um I mean your realities also shape what
kind of uh Vision you would have so
that's the question how open is really
the open society that you think you you
you you you are thinking about yeah you
see uh I've been
stressing uh the
uh the difference between the our view
of the world and the way the world
actually is and certainly let's say uh
America had the
view of the world which believed in
equality uh human rights uh individual
freedom and so on and at the same time
you had
slavery at the time of the founding
fathers uh and when
you uh U talk about Market
fundamentalism I I think it is a a
totally false pretense you see this
invis the the uh the Invisible Hand of
the market that that provides
opportunity to all well behind the
Invisible Hand of the of the market
there is the visible hand of politics
and we sets the rules and and
uh while actually the International
System established uh uh at Breton Woods
uh and at the United Nations was on the
surface uh
uh a very uh rule of law kind of uh uh
um sort of equ equal treatment for for
each there's no question that the United
States which basically set the rules was
more equal than the
others and and it was not immediately
obvious but it's very definitely the
case
so I have a lot of sympathy with your
position
please uh Colin mcin uh George I find it
interesting and perhaps it's a little
ironic that you today have come around
to defending uh a conception of politics
rather like Plato I mean ironic because
of your being a follower of Poa who of
course was very against Plato the reason
I say this is that you you're
emphasizing today the point that propa
neglected and you earli neglected the
influence of propaganda and manipulation
in in politics and in democracies today
of course that problem was what Plato
saw all along was the problem of
democracy it was the problem of the
sophists as you pointed out manipulators
of opinion as a defense against that
problem Plato advocated an intellectual
Elite he'd be trained in certain ways
and would be committed to the truth he
called them the philosopher Kings of
course and they would be protection
against the sophists this has got as
anathema to POA and other liberal
Democrats because it seems to be give
more political power to this Elite than
to the run of the population so I wonder
whether you'd like to comment on whether
you think you've become unlike POA a
platonist about
politics basically the question was are
you not becoming much more on the Plato
side than on the poer side because it
was much more Plato who have been
pushing for the philosophers to run in
order basically to have an elite which
can counterbalance the manipulative
power of the sophists
yes I think uh um I mean it's well known
that Papa was a little too hard on on
lato to start with uh
um but I I'm
actually um had more trouble with
lewu than with Plato because you know
lewu was sort of a a a philosopher king
uh run running the country and running
it with a pretty harsh hand uh and and
suppressing uh
opposition uh and yet he guided
Singapore to very
successfully and I found that really
quite distressing in a
way that that he could be as successful
while
suppressing uh alternative views
um and I
mean even you look at China today it's
not an very far from an open
Society uh but there is a kind of a
social
contract uh
where people accept the
authority of of the rulers in order to
have stability and pro and and economic
progress and the rulers know that they
have to provide stability and economic
progress in order to be the
rulers and actually it is working very
well as a as
a machine that is moving China forward
whereas America which is a democracy and
you have freedom of of all kinds of
freedoms guaranteed
basically half the Congress is out to
trip up the other half and and U uh a
tremendous amount of is lost in the in
the adversarial uh fighting so uh I have
to observe these things they they kind
of don't fit into the conceptual
framework with which I'm I'm I'm still
operating I'm modifying the conceptual
framework uh but I have
to
recognize that democracy doesn't necess
is not necessarily a superior form of
social
organization it it requires something
more than democracy for that to be the
case and and I've identified the pursuit
of Truth as that something more that has
to be there but it really means a set of
values also where people are
sufficiently public-minded
um to to be concerned with the public
good I'll deal with that
issue in in the in next lecture actually
because I I think that's a very
important addition
requirement uh for an open Society to to
be
successful thank you very much there was
a question very early on and I feel
guilty it yeah and thank you um I would
like to join on the debate about the
manipulation and the politics and I
think the key word is conscious cons
Consciousness so um Idol voter in an
ideal country would U listen to every
political parties speak and um he he
would said that uh yeah yes he he wanted
to operate with my feelings he he he
just lied or or he just um he just he's
not the man of this country um so he he
would decide this and he he just
wouldn't vote on this party or on this
man and uh my family has Sweden friends
who said to me that it
is it is ex it is ex existing in Sweden
so if a party would say to the Sweden
people that we would low the taxes if
you would vote on us then they would
just laugh at them and they it couldn't
be a party and uh do you think that
Americans uh don't have this type of
Consciousness or is it lack of the
American
society the question if I'm going to
interpret it crudely is do you believe
that because the Americans are foring
the taxes they don't have a moral
feeling they don't have don't have a
moral feeling Moral Moral feeling or
moral sentiment yes I I think that there
is a very serious problem in America now
with values and I think uh the market
fundamentalism this uh belief that the
Pur suit of
self-interest somehow has a moral uh um
support in this Invisible Hand of the
market that ensures that people pursuing
self-interest uh get the reach the best
allocation of resources it's a it's a
it's a false uh interpretation of
markets of society and and it has become
extremely
uh
powerful because it happens to be very
suit greatly beneficial to the owners
and managers of capital it's it's a very
satisfactory uh set of beliefs for them
and therefore they actually were willing
to invest very serious amounts of money
and effort
to man ulate public opinion where it it
was it has been accepted as the truth
and and we just had the collapse of the
financial markets which ought to uh
bring about a serious questioning
whether
this set of uh this ideology
actually is well founded or not I am of
course very
much a Critic of it
uh I don't want to manipulate you and
I'm going to tell you the truth we have
three minutes and there's at least 78
questions being there so on this
truthful note I'll go to give uh uh Dean
Stone the possibility to ask a question
and I do believe that the other
questions after that uh probably we can
discuss outside of outside of the room
there thank you uh Diane Stone from the
Department of Public policy here at ceu
I've been struck this afternoon how much
the discussion about politics has been
very much focused on the nation state
talking about political parties
elections the American political
culture so my question would be to what
extent is the notion of open Society
linked to the nation state as a society
or the degree to which open Society can
be delin and and associated with the
ways in which society is forming in new
forms uh transnationally through the
internet and various other kinds of um
associations so Regional Association for
for example um and the extent to which
uh open Society could operate through
things like Twitter for
example uh and also is this a domain
where the threats and challenges to open
Society are perhaps greater than at the
national
level the very last sentence was to is
this is where the challenges uh to the
open no I think it's an excellent
question and and and and
clearly um the problems confronting
Humanity trans transcend National
borders and because of uh the uh
globalization of financial maret markets
Etc actually the the uh financial
markets have become Global the economy
of course has become Global but the the
uh political system remains founded on
the principle of sovereignty and that
has very
serious uh creates very serious problems
and unless we solve that problem
um
actually
the global markets will
disintegrate but more than that for
instance we are going to cook uh because
of global warming because we will not be
able to solve that problem it's not one
that can be solved on a national uh
basis so we we actually have to make
some very important steps forward in the
form of international
governance to catch up with the
globalization of of our
civilization thank you very much I want
to excuse myself for those who didn't
manage to take the flo they're going to
be two more lectures so you're going to
have your opportunity thank you very
much to our colleagues from New York
they had the first word they didn't get
the last one but I do believe they're
also going to get their chance
and director
well I want to thank our audiences here
in Budapest and in New York uh I think
through open discourse we have explored
the challenges uh and opportunities of
open Society tomorrow uh these ideas
will be explored even further when Mr
Soros looks at what he sees as a
conflict between open society and
economic fundamentalism so uh be
prepared to return and engage in further
stimulating uh conversation of the type
we've had here today for now let me
Express gratitude to our expert
moderator Ivan kashf and ask you once
again to join me in thanking our
extraordinary Lector George
[Music]
Soros very good question