good afternoon and welcome to the third
in our series of ceu lectures I'm John
shadik president and director of central
European University and it's my great
privilege throughout this week to host
five lectures by George Soros held here
in Budapest at the Hungarian Academy of
Sciences under the offices of central
European
University in today's lecture Mr Soros
will discuss the concept of open society
which guides his philanthropy and is
Central to his political and social
thinking over the past quarter Century
as we all know he has devoted
unprecedented philanthropic support to
the underpinnings of this concept around
the world from equal access to Justice
to freedom of
expression these lectures are being
video conferenced to universities on
several continents creating interactive
Global audiences of students in real
time today's lecture will include
students from Columbia University in New
York in addition to invited guests uh
and central European universities
students here in Budapest our moderator
today is Ivan KF an international
political commentator and Civil Society
leader from Bulgaria Mr Soros will speak
for approximately 50 minutes after which
Mr crosi will offer his own brief
commentary Mr Soros will then take
questions as he has in previous days
starting with three questions today from
our audience at Columbia University and
then from the audience
here in Budapest now to deliver his
third lecture I'm delighted once again
to introduce George Soros who once again
needs no
introduction thank you very much today I
shall introduce the third pillar of my
conceptual framework namely open
Society in the previous lectures I was
summarizing the conclusions of a
lifetime of study and
experimentation here I will be breaking
new ground because my views on open
Society have changed over time and they
they are still evolving as a result the
next two lectures will be much more uh
expl exploratory in
nature the connection between open
society and reflexivity is far from
obvious on a personal level they are
closely connected as as you recall I was
studying
economics uh in at LSC and at the same
time I was reading Carl Popper's open
society and its enemies and it was
Papa's insistence on our inherent
fallibility that led me to question
basic the basic assumptions of economic
theory and develop the concept of
reflexivity but on a conceptual level
the connection is only indirect
indirect it's is the first pillar the
fallibility that connects the other two
fallibility in this context means not
only that our view of the world is
always incomplete and distorted but also
that our in our effort to simplify an
extremely complex reality we often
misconstrue it and our misconceptions
play an important role in shaping the
course of
history if there is is anything really
original in my thinking is this emphasis
on
misconceptions it provides a strong AR
argument in favor of critical thinking
and open
Society POA didn't give an exact
definition of open Society because he
cons he considered exact definitions
incompatible with our imperfect
understanding he preferred to approach
things from the opposite direction by
first uh describing them and then giving
them a label uh the form of organization
he named open Society bore a close
resemblance to
democracy the net effect of his approach
was to justify democracy by an
epistemological
argument since perfect knowledge is
beyond the scope of the human intellect
a society characterized by the freedom
of speech and thought and free elections
is preferable to a society which imposes
its ideology by force having been
exposed to Nazi persecution and
communist oppression I found this
argument very
persuasive Papa's philosophy made me
more sensitive to the role of of
misconceptions in financial markets and
the concept of reflexivity allowed me to
develop my theory of bubbles this gave
me a leg up as a market
participant after a successful run as a
hedge fund manager I went through a kind
of midlife crisis I was approaching 50
my f hedge fund had grown to be 100 400
million of which 40 million belonged to
me personally I felt that I had made
more than enough money for myself and my
family and running a hedge fund was
extremely stressful and
depleting what would make it worthwhile
to
continue I thought long and hard and
finally I decided to set up a foundation
devoted to the promotion of open Society
I defined its Mission as opening up
close societies uh correcting the
deficiencies of open societies and
promoting a critical mode of
thinking as time went by uh I became
increasingly involved in philanthropy I
established a
foundation here in Hungary in
1984 when it was still under communist
rule
in China in 1986 in Poland the Soviet
Union in
1987 and as the Soviet Union and
Yugoslavia disintegrated I set up a
network of foundations that covered
almost the entire former communist World
in this way I acquired some practical
experience in building open
societies uh I learned a lot I
discovered things that I should have
known in the first place for instance
that the disintegration of a close
societies doesn't necessarily lead to
the birth of open societies it may just
it may result in just continuing
disintegration until a new regime
emerges that bears more resemblance to
the regime that had collapsed than to an
open Society
the event that forced me to thoroughly
reconsider the concept of open Society
was the reelection of President Bush in
the United States in
2004 here was the oldest and most
successful democracy in the world
violating the principles for which it
was supposed to stand by engaging in
human rights violations in the the name
of fighting uh uh the a war on terror
and invading Iraq on false
pretenses yet he was
reelected how was that possible I had to
ask myself what was wrong with
America I wrote a couple of books trying
to answer that question I blamed the
Bush
Administration for misleading the people
and
I blamed the people for allowing the
Bush Administration to mislead
them as I probed deeper I started to
question my own conceptual framework I
discovered the flaw in the concept of
open
Society in in in in so far as Papa was
mainly concerned with the problems of
understanding reality he put forward an
epistemological rather than a political
argument in favor of open Society he
argued that and I quote only democracy
provides an Institutional framework that
permits reform without violence and the
use of Reason in
politics but that's the end of the quote
but his approach was based on a hidden
assumption asson namely that the main
purpose of thinking is to gain a better
understanding of reality and that was
not necessarily the case the
manipulative function could take
precedence over the cognitive function
indeed in a democracy the primary
objective of politicians is to get
elected and stay in
power this rather obvious Insight raise
some additional questions about the
concept of open Society how how could
Papa take it for granted that free
political discourse is aimed at
understanding reality and more
intriguingly how could I who gave the
manipulative function pride of place in
the concept of reflexivity follow him so
blindly both questions led me to the
same conclusion our view of the world is
deeply rooted in an intellectual
tradition which either ignores the
manipulative function or treats it as
subservient to the cognitive
function it's easy to see why that this
uh this view of the world became so
ingrained the aim of the the cognitive
function is to produce knowledge
knowledge is expressed by statements
that correspond to the facts to
establish
correspondence statements and facts have
to be separate and
distinct hence the pursuit of knowledge
requires that thoughts should be
distinguished from their subject matter
this requirement LED philosophers whose
primary
preoccupation is with thinking to the
belief that reason and reality are
separate this dualism had its roots in
Greek philosophy and it came to dominate
our view of the world during the
Enlightenment the philosophers of the
Enlightenment put their faith in reason
reason was supposed to work like a
search light illumin ating a reality
that lay there passively awaiting
Discovery the active role that re reason
can play in shaping reality was largely
left out of account in other words the
enlightenment failed to recognize
reflexivity this resulted in a distorted
view of reality but one that was
appropriate to the age when it was
formulated at the time of the
Enlightenment humankind had as yet
relatively little knowledge or control
over the forces of nature and scientific
method held out infinite promise it was
appropriate to think of reality as
something out there waiting passively to
be discovered and reason as actively
engaged in exploring it after all at
that time not even the Earth had been
fully
explored Gathering facts and
establishing relationships among them
was richly
rewarding knowledge was being acquired
in so many different ways and from so
many different directions that the
possibilities seemed
unlimited reason was sweeping away
centuries of Trad additional
relationships and religious dogma and
generating a triumphant sense of
progress
the difficulties that reflexivity poses
to a proper understanding of human
Affairs went largely
unnoticed the leaders of the French
Revolution believed that reason could
help reconstruct Society from the ground
up but their faith in reason was
excessive Society failed to follow the
dictates of reason and the euphoria of
1789 uh
deteriorated into the terror of
1974 1994 1794 I'm
sorry the enlightenment misinterpreted
Reality by introducing a dichotomy
between thinking and reality which would
enable reason to attain perfect
knowledge the dichotomy was not in in
him ENT in the subject matter but
introduced by the philosophers of the
Enlightenment in their attempt to make
sense of
reality the mistake made by the
enlightenment has been given a name
postmodernists call it the enlightenment
fallacy I shall adopt that term but I
want to make it clear that I'm talking
about a fertile fallacy which contains v
a valuable kernel of
Truth let me explain more precisely what
I mean by a fertile fallacy we are
capable of acquiring knowledge but we
can never have enough knowledge to allow
us to base all our decisions on
knowledge it follows that if a piece of
knowledge has proved useful we are
liable to overe exploit it and extend it
to areas where it no longer applies so
that it becomes a fallacy that's what
happened to the enlightenment the
dichotomy between reason and reality
worked very well for the study of
natural phenomena but it was misleading
in the study of human
Affairs fertile fallacies are the
equivalent of bubbles in financial
markets the enlightenment fallacy
is deeply rooted in our view of the
world it led Carl poer to Proclaim that
the same standards and criteria applied
in both the natural and the social
sciences and it led economic theory to
model itself on Newtonian
physics neither Papa's elegant model of
scientific method no economic theory
recognized
reflexivity what worse even I who
discovered or invented reflexivity in
the financial markets failed to
recognize that Papa's concept of open
Society was based on the hidden
assumption that the cognitive function
takes precedence over the manipulative
function that we are pursuing the truth
and not simply trying to manipulate
people into believing what we want them
to believe
the enlightenment fallacy is also at the
root of the efficient market hypothesis
and its political derivative Market
fundamentalism the fallacy in these two
intellectual constructs was exposed in a
spectacular fashion by the collapse of
the financial system my discovery of a
flow in open Society was less
spectacular because the concept is
widely accepted but on a personal level
it was equally
earthshaking it forced me to rethink the
concept of open
Society I have not abandoned my belief
in the merits of open Society but I
realize that it needs stronger arguments
to butress it papa took it for granted
that in an open Society the cognitive
function takes precedence
I now believe that this has to be
introduced as an explicit requirement
for an open Society to flourish let me
explain how I reached that
conclusion in a
democracy political discourse is not
aimed at discovering reality that's the
cognitive function but getting El Ed and
staying in power that's the manipulative
function consequently free political
discourse doesn't necessarily produce
more farsighted policies than author and
that than an authorit authoritarian
regime that suppresses dissent to make
matters worse in the political battle to
manipulate reality a commitment to abide
by by by the truth has become a
handicap the Bush Administration had at
its disposal a powerful right-wing
propaganda machine working for it that
did not uh feel the need to respect the
facts this gave it a decided competitive
advantage over more old-fashioned
political practitioners who were still
under the influence of the Enlightenment
fallacy
and felt constrained by the
facts Frank Lun the one of the most
successful writing propagandists in the
United States openly admitted that he
used George Ells
1984 as his textbook in devising his
slogans as a believer in the open
Society I found this shocking how could
o valan news
be as successful in an open society as
in a totalitarian state with its
Ministry of Truth which could use
stalinist methods to keep people in
line this line of inquiry provided me
with a clue to the question what's wrong
with America people are not particularly
concerned with the pursuit of Truth they
have been conditioned by ever more
sophisticated techniques of manipulation
to the point where they don't mind being
deceived indeed they seem positively to
invite it people have
become used to receiving messages
prepackaged hence the influence of paid
political
advertising and they are more interested
in being entertained than informed hence
the influence of of populist
commentators like billowy or rash
limbo the techniques of
manipulation have developed gradually
over time they originated in the
commercial Arena towards the end of the
19th century when entrepreneurs
discovered that they could improve their
profit margins by differentiating their
products through brand Ing and
advertising this prompted Research into
the motivation of consumers the testing
of messages and the use of of uh focus
groups uh uh setting in motion a
reflexive process which changed the
behavior of the public it led to the
development of a consumer society and
spread from there to politics and
culture these Trends
undermined the hidden assumptions on
which economics and politics were based
economic theory has taken the conditions
of demand and suppliers given and showed
how free markets under the conditions of
perfect
competition lead to the optimum
allocation of resources but the shape of
the demand curve was not independently
given it was subject to manipulation by
advertising the theory of repr
representative democracy assumed that
candidates would present themselves and
their programs and the electorate would
choose the ones they preferred it didn't
anticipate that the candidates would
study public opinion and then tell the
electorate what he wanted to
hear both these theories failed to take
into account that reality can be
manipulated the manipulation of
reality also became a major theme in the
Arts it was literary criticism that
eventually led to the development of the
postmodern worldview which turned the
enight enement upside down it denied the
existence of an objective reality that
could be discovered by reason instead it
saw reality as a collection of often
contradictory
narratives I had dismissed the
postmodern worldview out of hand because
it was in conflict with my profound
respect for an objective reality I I
didn't realize the connection between
the postmodern world viw and the bush
administration's propaganda machine
until I read an article by Ron Sask kind
which opened my eyes he quoted one of
the operators of that machine uh
supposed to be Carl Rove uh as saying
that we don't study facts we create them
this forced me to change my mind I had
to take the postmodern position more
seriously and recognize it as a fertile
fallacy fully equal in its influence to
the Enlightenment and currently perhaps
even more
influential but I still regard the
postmodern fallacy as more of a fallacy
and less fertile than the enlightenment
fallacy by giving precedence to the
manipulative function it ignores the
hardcoree of objective reality that
cannot be
manipulated this is more of a defect in
my eyes than the enlightenment's neglect
of the manipulative function
according to the
enlightenment
uh uh reason and reality are separate
and independent of each other the only
way people can turn reality to their
advantage is by understanding the laws
that determine the course of events
under these conditions it could be taken
for granted that this discovering those
laws had to come
first this led to the development of
natural science which is the greatest
achievement of the human intellect it's
only in the human Affairs in human
Affairs that the fallacy crept in by
contrast the postmodern worldview is
Thoroughly misleading it has St spawned
an aoral pragmatic approach in politics
it can be summed up as follows now that
we have discovered that reality can be
manipulated why should the cognitive
function be given precedence why not
engage directly in manipulation why not
pursue power rather than
truth now there is an answer to that
point of view that I find
decisive while reality can be
manipulated the outcome is bound to
diverge from the manipulators
intentions the Divergence needs to be
kept to a minimum and that can be done
only through a better understanding of
reality is this line of argument that
led me to introduce the
commitment uh introduce a commitment to
The Pursuit Of Truth as an explicit
requirement for open
Society this abstract argument can be
reinforced by a concrete
example uh look at the bush bush
presidency it was remarkably successful
in manipulating Reality by declaring war
on terror it managed to line up the
nation behind the president and uh pav
the way to the invasion of Iraq the
invasion was meant to establish the
supremacy of the United States in the
world but it achieved the exact opposite
America lost power and influence
precipitously and George W bush is
widely considered the worst president of
the United the United States ever
had this example ought to be convincing
yet now that the concept of reflexivity
is gaining recognition the danger is
that it will be misinterpreted in favor
of the postmodern
fallacy uh reflexive reality is just too
difficult to understand and people are
easily misled by simple answers it takes
a lifetime to understand the argument
that a a valid prediction doesn't
necessarily prove that the theory on
which it was based is also true while a
paid political announcement takes only
seconds is tempting to adapt the
postmodern view of the world but it's
very dangerous to disregard the
existence of an objective
reality one way to bring home
OB objective reality is to draw
attention to to death as a fact of
life the Mind finds it difficult to
accept the idea of ceasing to exist and
all kinds of narratives and myths have
sprung up around the idea of life after
death I have been struck by an AE ritual
where teams compete in a ball game and
the winners are sacrificed to the gods
that's an extreme example of the power
of such myths yet the fact remains that
the winning team
died even
so I have to admit that the absence of
of of uh life after death can't be
proven to those who who believe in it my
insistence on the importance of the
objective aspect of reality is a matter
of personal belief indeed it has a
curious resemblance to a religious
belief the objective aspect of reality
as I have constructed it has many of the
attributes of God as conceived in
monotheistic
religions it's omnipresent and all
powerful yet yet the ways of its working
remain somewhat
mysterious now I hold the objective
aspect of reality in very high regard
and I used to think that that is the
norm I've come to realize that my
attitude is quite unusual and it has to
do with my personal
history the formative experience of my
life was the German occupation of
Hungary in 194 44 uh under the wise
guidance of my father we not only
survived but managed to help others in a
situation full of dangers this turned
1944 into a positive experience for me
and gave me an appetite for confronting
harsh
reality this attitude was reinforced by
my involvement in the financial markets
I was a risk taker and often pushed
matters to their limit
but avoided going over the brink I
learned to protect myself against
unpleasant Surprises by looking looking
out for all the things that could go
wrong I chose Investments where the risk
reward ratio remained uh attractive even
under the worst assumptions this made me
emphasize the Dark Side of every
situation then I became active with my
Foundation
uh here the fact that I could do
something positive to to alleviate
Injustice increased my willingness to
recognize and confront harsh realities a
negative assessment became an invitation
for positive
involvement my Foundation ended up
devoting much of its resources to
seemingly insoluble problems like drug
policy and seemingly hopeless cases like
Burma Haiti Liberia Sierra Leon or the
Congo needless to say fighting Lo losing
battles is not the preferred choice of
most
foundations my commitment to the
objective re aspect of reality plays the
same role in my thinking as religion
does in other people's in the absence of
perfect knowledge we need beliefs I
happen to believe in harsh reality while
other people believe in
God nevertheless I would argue that when
Society ignores the objective aspect of
reality it does so at its own
Peril if we try to avoid unpleasant
realities by deceiving ourselves or the
electorate reality will public will
punish us by failing to meet our
expectations yes reality can be
manipulated but the results of our
actions are governed not by our desires
but by an external reality whose
workings we cannot fully comprehend the
better we understand it the closer the
outcome will correspond to our
intentions understanding reality is the
cognitive function
that's why the cognitive function ought
to take precedence and guide the
manipulative function ignoring an
objective reality that can't be fully
understood leads to the postmodern uh
fallacy so in recent history mankind has
adopted two fallacies about the
relationship between thinking and
reality the enlightenment fallacy and
the post modern fallacy they are related
to each other the enlightenment fallacy
failed to recognize the uh prevalence of
manipulation in human in the human
sphere and the discovery of the
manipulative function led to the
postmodern fallacy each of them
recognizes one half of a complicated
relationship
my conceptual framework being based on
the twin principles of fallibility and
reflexivity combines the two halves both
fallacies have been
influential but the
framework I I've put forward has
received little acceptance and this goes
to show how easy it is to misinterpret
reality much easier than to gain a prop
proper
understanding the postmodern fallacy is
now in the
ascendant it guided the policies of the
Bush
Administration and I noted alarm that it
has surfaced in the Obama Administration
as well I referred to a recent book by
George kof and Robert Schiller animal
spirits that has been influential in
shaping the economic policies of the OB
Obama
administration that book extols the
merits of the confidence
multiplier that is to say the ills of
the economy can be can be cured by
talking up the financial markets now
that is half true the stock market
really has allowed Banks to raise
capital and strengthen the economy in
other ways as well but the confidence
multiplier disregards the other half of
the truth that if reality fails to
conform to expectations confidence can
turn into
disappointment boom can turn to
bust I'm deeply worried that by
deploying the confidence multiplier
president Obama has taken ownership of
the recession and if there is a relapse
or uh he will be blamed for
it this discussion should help to
clarify my theory of reflexivity by
putting it into context of two false
interpretations of reality
in particular a a a point that may not
have come through loud and clear needs
to be emphasized that there is a
hardcore of of of of objective reality
that can't be manipulated like the
inevitability of death is this
hardcore
if that is ignored by the postmodern
fallacy and embolden emboldened by my
recent successes I will go so far as to
claim that my conceptual framework
provides the correct interpretation of
reality that's a bold claim and at first
sight it seems to be self-contradictory
how can a correct interpretation of
reality be be reconciled with the
principle of inherently imperfect
understanding Easy by pointing out that
reflexivity introduces an element of
uncertainty both into the participants
thinking and into the course of events a
framework that claims that the future is
inherently uncertain can't be accused of
perfection yet it can provide important
insights into reality it can even
anticipate the future
within bounds although the bounds
themselves are uncertain and variable as
we have seen in the recent financial
crisis by recognizing uncertainty my
framework manages to be both
self-consistent and consistent with
reality yet since it's less than perfect
it holds itself open to
Improvement actually I see tremendous
scope for further development my
original framework formulated under the
influence of Carl poer dealt only with
the problems of understanding reality
but when I added the requirement that
the electorate should cherish
truthfulness and punish deception I
entered the realm of values in that
realm uncertainty is even more prevalent
than in the fear of cognition therefore
a lot more thinking needs to be
done as we have seen the truth is
difficult to establish and often hard to
Bear the line of least resistance leads
in the opposite direction to avoid
unpleasant realities and reward
deception as long as it remains
convincing these Tendencies need to be
resisted for an open Society to remain
open and to
flourish this prescription is
particularly relevant to the United
States at the present time because the
United States is facing a particularly
unpleasant set of realities in the
aftermath of the financial crisis the
country has been living beyond this
means for the last quarter of a century
and making ends meet by Bor growing
abroad now the housing bubble has burst
consumers are overextended and need to
rebuild their savings the banking system
has collapsed and needs to to earn its
way out of a
hole the Bush Administration had
deliberately misled the electorate when
it invaded Iraq on false pretenses the
Obama Administration can't be accused of
deliberate deception never nevertheless
it has accepted that the country is
unwilling to face harsh realities and
deployed the confidence
multiplier unfortunately the objective
reality is unlikely to fulfill the the
hopes raised by the confidence uh
multiplier at the same time the
political opposition is not constrained
by facts in attacking the president in
these circumstan es the requirement that
the electorate should be more committed
to the pursuit of truth will be
difficult to meet it provides a good
agenda for my Foundation but the current
state of Democracy in America does not
strengthen the case for open society as
a superior form of social
organization I need to find a stronger
argument a better case can be found
by reverting to the founding fathers who
formed their views long before the
concept of open open Society was
introduced the founding fathers buil
that case on the value of individual
Freedom the epistemological argument
they employed was flawed the Declaration
of Independence states that we hold
these truths to be
self-evident and there is nothing
self-evident about them but self-evident
or not the value of individual freedom
is enduring and having been exposed to
totalitarian regimes I'm passionately
devoted to it and I'm not
alone reverting to the founding fathers
has another great Advantage it allows a
discussion of power
relations the Constitution protected
against tyranny by a division of powers
the division of powers recognizes that
there are competing interests and
different interpretations of reality
within society which need to be
reconciled by a political process the
Constitutional checks and balances
preclude the formation of uh absolute
power that could claim to be in
possession of the ultimate truth the
Constitution establish a mechanism where
different branches of government
interact and control each other but that
is not sufficient open Society can
Prevail only when people can speak truth
to power it needs the rule of law that
guarantees freedom of speech and press
freedom of Association and assembly and
other rights and freedoms they imp EMP
power citizens to defend themselves
against the absolute power of the state
and to make use of the judicial branch
for such defense that's how the founding
fathers creating created an open
Society let me spell out my conclusion
more
clearly open Society is a desirable form
of social organization
both as a means to an end and as an end
in itself it establish it it enables a
society to understand the problems
confronting it and to deal with them
more successfully than other forms of
social
organizations provided it gives
precedence to the cognitive over the
manipul manipulative function and the
people are willing to confront harsh
realities in other words the
instrumental value of democracy is
conditional on the qualities of the
electorate and the current performance
of American democracy doesn't live up to
its P past achievements we can't rely on
the inherent superiority of the American
model and need to prove ourselves a new
but quite apart from its instrumental
value open Society also has an intrinsic
value namely the freedom of the
individual which implies whether open
Society flourishes or not for instance
it applied to the Soviet
Union of course the freedom of the
individual must be made compatible with
the public interest and the the freedom
of other
individuals moreover the intrinsic value
of individual Freedom falls short of
being of
self-evident for instance it's not
generally recognized in China where the
interests of the collective take
precedence over the interests of the
individual this was the clear message of
the opening ceremony of the Olympic
Games it showed that by doing exactly
what they are what they are told and
exactly at the right time a large
collection of individuals can produce a
superb
spectacle with the changing power
relations between the United Station and
China the value of individual freedom is
likely to in to assume increasing
importance in the immediate future and I
will address that subject in my last
lecture thank you
[Applause]