a few weeks ago mr. Soros asked me as a
preparation for this job I'm doing at
the moment
to research the intellectual antecedents
if any of the notion of reflectivity
which was thought about for so many
years and is explaining to you today so
I said okay I can do that so my first
recourse was to go to Wikipedia and
well-known resource and I typed in
self-fulfilling prophecy first and page
came up and I started to read it and the
first thing that's noted in the in that
entry was that the man called Robert K
Merton a sociologist invented the phrase
self-fulfilling prophecy which
apparently derives from the Thomas
theorem which states that quote if men
define situations as real they are real
in their consequences so a reading
through this entry first of all I came
across the quote from Robert Merton
himself and he was discussing the case
of a bank run caused by a crisis of
confidence in the solvency of the bank
so Merton concludes the example by
saying quote the parable tells us that
public definitions of a situation
prophecies or predictions become an
integral part of the situation and thus
affect subsequent developments this is
peculiar to human affairs it is not
found in the world of nature untouched
by human hands predictions of the return
of Halley's Comet not influence its
orbit but the rumored insolvency of
milling wheels Bank did affect the
actual outcome the prophecy of collapse
led to its own fulfillment
that's mertens explanation of his
concept of a self-fulfilling prophecy as
I read through very soon we have a quote
preceded by philosopher Karl Popper
called the self-fulfilling prophecy the
Oedipus effect
this is a quote from poppers
autobiography unending quest he says one
of the ideas I discussed in the poverty
of historicism was the influence of a
prediction upon the event predicted I
called this the heed abyss effect
because the Oracle play the most
important role in the sequence of events
which led to the fulfillment of its
prophecy for a time I thought that the
existence of the Oedipus effect
distinguished the social from the
natural sciences as to say the influence
of a prediction upon the event predicted
but in biology too he goes on even in
molecular biology expectations often
play a role in bringing about what has
been expected he doesn't actually
explain why he thinks that in molecular
biology and on the face of it it sounds
implausible in any case that's what he
says so having read Wikipedia then I had
a look at the poverty of historicism I
obtained the book and looked up the
Oedipus effect in the index so I'm going
to read you a few passages from the
crucial four or five pages so you will
have an idea pointers so as to lay mr.
cirrhosis idea of leisure activity out
in somebody else's words and then I'm
going to invite him to comment on how he
sees the notion which he has developed
in relation to these earlier ideas of
what sound to be similar ideas and I
must say I was quite struck by a Papa's
formulation of the idea so here's what
popper says in poverty of historicism
which I think came out sometime in the
1940s so quite a long time ago and
Robert Merton was writing around the
same time I so page 11
underneath under the heading
inexactitude of prediction the idea that
the prediction may have influence upon
the predicted event is a very old one he
posted in the legend killed his father
whom he had never seen before this was
the direct result of the prophecy which
had caused his father to abandon him
this is why I call I suggest the name
Oedipus effect the influence of the
prediction upon the predicted event or
more generally for the influence of an
item of information from the situation
to which the information refers whether
this influence
tends to bring about the predicted event
or whether it tends to prevent it he
calls it the intimus effect I think it
might be more aptly called the Macbeth
effect because of course as you remember
in that play the witch's prediction of
Macbeth's murder of the king is partly
at least what brings about the murder of
the king and many other things happening
in that story so we have a case of the
prediction influencing the course of
events so that's the first formulation a
little bit further at page 12 he says we
a fit is under the heading object
objectivity and valuation we are faced
with we are faced in the social sciences
with a full and complicated interaction
between observer and observed between
subject and object the awareness of the
existence of tendencies which might
produce a future event and furthermore
the awareness that the prediction might
itself and exert an influence on events
predicted it likely to have
repercussions on the content of the
prediction and the repercussions might
be of such a kind of gravely to impair
the objectivity of the predictions and
the weather results of research in the
social sciences a prediction is a social
happening which may interact with other
social happenings and among them with
the one which it predicts it may as we
have seen helped to precipitate this
event but it's easy to see that it may
also influence it it in other ways it
may in an extreme case even coarsely
happening it predicts the happening
might not have occurred at all if it had
not been predicted at the other extreme
the prediction of an impending event may
lead to its prevention so that by
deliberately or negligently abstaining
from predicting it the social scientist
it may be said could bring it about of
course it to happen there will clearly
be many intermediate cases between these
two extremes the action of predicting
something and that of abstaining from
prediction might both have all sorts of
consequences final brief quote the
interaction pronouncements and the sort
and social life almost invariably
creates situations which we have not
only to consider the truth of such
pronouncements but also their actual
influence
developments the social scientist may be
striving to find the truth but at the
same time he must always be exerting a
definite influence upon society the very
fact that his pronouncements do exert an
influence destroys their objectivity so
these ideas certainly sounds very much
in the same and same ballpark as we say
as mr. Soros his ideas so the first
thing I'll do before we turn to
questions from the audience is him
invite terms to saw us to to comment on
on this and how he sees the concept of
reflectivity that he's explained today
in relation to these earlier ideas again
first of all I think popper spoke mainly
reflexivity of social theories whereas I
emphasize the reflectivity of the
subject matter recognizers of course
also the reflectivity of social theories
but more important is that the
participants are engaged in reflexive
phenomena and of course sociology has
recognized
reflexivity as a social phenomenon and
Merton was definitely the path breaker
with the bandwagon effect and Andy and
self-fulfilling prophecies but economics
has gone out of its way to eliminate the
reflectivity from the subject matter and
we have paid a very heavy price account
you know amounting to trillions of
dollars for that little mistake so
that's I would say is the different the
other thing that I would point out that
this reflectivity as a phenomenon hasn't
been analyzed the way for instance
self-reference
with Bertrand Russell and Freya and so
on then I got onto reflectivity by
reading about self reference and
apparent paradox of the liar that's what
led beyond but then I discovered that it
is really a much more pervasive
phenomenon so I would say that's those
are the major differences and and you
know I I then broke down
reflexivity into the cognitive and
manipulative functions and argued that
the two functions interfere with each
other creating an element of uncertainty
which is a characteristic of human
affairs of course it's not the only one
and when it comes to uncertainty again
economic theory has gone overboard
trying to eliminate uncertainty but
there are of course very valuable
antecedents that I would quote
particularly night ninety and
uncertainty which is basically what I am
harping on also I mean one thing you
didn't mention there worth mentioning I
think is now the popper no Merton saw
the application of reflexivity to the
behavior of financial markets since you
were a participant in financial markets
you applied it to there to that area
where it of course applies particularly
was spectacularly well right now there
which enables you to to understand okay
only know the particular irony is that
Robert Merton son got a Nobel price for
devising formula which ignored reflexive
okay now my my job is to throw the the
floor open to our
ensign was supposed to take questions
first from the remote audience at the
London School of Economics first like
three questions from them before we move
to people here and let me say before
getting questions from the LSE that I
would implore questioners to first of
all identify themselves by name and
affiliation then to make their questions
concise and to speak as clearly as
possible cuz we're hearing them here and
to make their questions questions not
speeches so a question to mr. Soros
concisely stated and clearly articulated
would be greatly appreciated with that I
open the floor to the élysée now we wait
for moderator in London - can you hear
us yes hello George we very much enjoyed
your lecture and we have actually three
I hope for questions if we can fit it in
in ten minutes so I'm going to hand it
over to the first path we hello my name
is Zachary myself we leave
but a master student and international
political economy Jared Elysee I was
interested in how a third party could
become aware of a reflexive relationship
and how they could sort of interact in
order to gain from the information they
learn about the existence of that
relationship and an applied example of
that with our applied question would be
how would a government become aware of a
positive reflexive relationship and
intervene in financial markets in order
to dampen the boom-bust cycle that
results as a consequence of reflexivity
okay I have some fortunately difficulty
hearing it can't can Mary perhaps you
could just repeat the question because I
have difficulty hearing it I could hear
it yeah what could you repeat a mission
in a reflexive relationship and in
particular the role of a government
could the government identify a
reflexive participation a reflexive
relationship that in fact be reflexive
itself in order to dampen down boom-bust
cycles did you hear that Daniel can you
hear me only just nothing I'm making it
simpler and simpler he put it very well
how can a third party influence a
two-party reflexive relation
and how can a government intervene using
your theory to stop a boom-bust cycle
did you hear that how can government
agency industry well of course this
question leads up to tomorrow's lecture
that's exactly what I will discuss
tomorrow but let me just preface it
perhaps but by saying that regulators
and government and financial authorities
also are subject to the same limits of
phal ability as market participants so
you have a constant interplay between
regulators and market participants but
both sides operate with imperfect
understanding and that's what makes the
process is so interesting but I will
deal with that more tomorrow
fortunately we're not going to hear you
tomorrow but perhaps we can tell us when
you next come to Elysee I'm handing over
to the next question hi thank you for
sharing your insights today my name is
jawad katya and i am a part-time finance
student masters and a full-time
proprietary trader and my question to
you is you talked a little bit about how
your general theory relates to trend
following and charting in general and
how much you may have or may not have
used these sorts of strategies in their
own trading thank you well again
obviously being at the School of
Economics you are particularly
interested in financial markets and and
that's again ten following I could
answer in general terms that actually
trends tend to validate themselves - for
an extended period and therefore trend
following is very often a valid strategy
which contradicts let's say the the
prevailing paradigm of efficient market
and rational expectations however
reality
may not fulfill the expectations that
are involved in that trend and then you
you you reach a point where the trend is
reversed and you don't want to be a
trend follower at that time
third question hi I'm corner hi Johnny
and I'm an undergraduate student
studying social policy my question to
you is how do you feel about the fact
that Adam Smith is known to be the
father of economics for his theories on
the invisible hand when market
fundamentalism is an economic policy you
criticize the most thank you again I
didn't understand that passion I think
the question was how do you feel about
Adam Smith as the father of economics
and the inventor of the invisible hand
in light of your theory of reflexivity
well you know Adam Smith wrote two books
I haven't read either of them and I am a
critical of the invisible hand actually
it it markers actually perform a very
valuable function but they only are
designed to allow individuals to fulfill
their individual needs and there are
social issues like for instance a
regulation of markets that markets are
not designed to to solve or to deal with
so behind the invisible hand of the
market there is hidden the visible hand
of politics and that visible hand is
deliberately obscured by market
fundamentalists who extol the virtues of
the markets forgetting or of obfuscating
the fact
that behind the market mechanism there
are political decisions that are then
determining how markets function I will
again you are anticipating actually this
happens to be the fourth lecture where I
will talk about market values and and
social values and the conflict between
capitalism and open society but I'm
happy to anticipate that that subject
I'm surprised that nobody from the LSE
wants to ask a question of mr. Soros
about Papa's philosophy versus his
philosophy because after all this is
where Karl Popper was a professor but
there are no questions about the
philosophical content of what mr. Soros
said in relation to to Papa but maybe
later we can come back to LSE but I
think now I will throw the questions
open to the audience present before us
so anybody with hands up and then we
proceed yes and I think you need to get
a microphone from somebody unless I
don't know was be happy I would like to
know what's the effect the role of an
educator in society as in the perfect
CVT effect for one side a high educated
a society each person has a bigger
effect but another side and educated the
society is more rational and perhaps a
more rational society the reflexivity
effect is is more anyway what's the role
of education of a society to have a
bigger or smaller
detractor well Christopher market is is
from Brazil and he was Minister of
Education and he introduced he
introduced ball sized koala which is
actually a payment to poor families to
allow their children to attend school
and I think it was it's a wonderful
scheme and has made it big difference in
Brazil and it has been imitated in other
countries not notably Mexico and I'm
actually a great supporter of that
scheme we introduced a variant of it in
New York about which I am not so not so
entirely happy but I'm supporting it
also and obviously education is a most
important for for an open society and
the altogether I think that if people
citizens would understand the
limitations of our ability to deal with
social problems if they understood
refractivity actually we could deal with
our social problems better so most of my
philosophy has a kind of a negative
thing or to it namely imperfect
understanding and and
and fallibilities there's all sound very
bad but in effect if you if you
understand it and and if you are in a
better position to improve your policies
perfection it can be the bane of of
social reform in the French Revolution
people believing in reason engaged in
terror the various ideologies which
claim to be in possession of the
ultimate truth it could be only imposed
by force so I think if we understand our
limitations and you return it around and
and what is imperfect can be improved so
we are in a way fortunate at that with
our fail ability because that leaves
infinite scope for for improvement we
won't solve all our problems we leave
some for the next generations to come so
some education should teach uncertainty
of the dogma right and I've been arguing
also that we ought to pass from the age
of reason to the age of faith ability
that it's a less a an achievement of
reason to understand fail ability okay
who's next
yes gentlemen middle level
better wait for ya thank you hello I'm
Robert Oracle from Mexico
I studied MBA in the CEO Business School
my question is well it's been said that
the 20th century was the physics century
and what and well this century will be
the biology century will be the biology
biology and biology and there is a
hypothesis that telling us that all the
sciences will come closer together do
you think this threatened threatens your
your own hypothesis or your own proposal
that we should separate the social
sciences from the Natural Sciences well
I think this question is if you didn't
say much about biology did allude to it
at one point because you have the
separation between the social sciences
and the Natural Sciences is bringing up
the point that biology is becoming
central and so he was wondering where
the biology threatens the dichotomy that
you have because it seems to involve
Sasa studying the social insects for
example to write that kind of issue I
think that's what it was yeah no
actually one of the one of the questions
that I struggle with is how does
reflectivity relate to complexity
because that's it evolutionary Systems
Theory has great similarities with
reflectivity in the sense that it does
not have a determinate outcome and it
evolves and I think that the
the two are in a way quite close to each
other in the sense that systems
evolutionary Systems Theory network
theory has relevance to human society
which is also a kind of network so
that's a general rules about network
theory apply to actually to financial
markets to banks because banks were
networks
and you had contagion destroying the
financial system similar to to a viral
attack so let's say epidemiology has a
relevance and which we ignored and which
which people are now aware of and we are
now looking at the at at those issues so
there are things to be learnt from
biology and and and other networks
however I think reflexivity which has
which has to do with the specific
relationship between thinking and
reality that's a specifically human
characteristic there is it applies to
human societies it may apply to whales
because whales seem to be able to
communicate and there are some evidence
that actually pretty pretty elaborate
societies but so I'm not I don't want to
delimit it purely to human society but
even there we probably
more and more relevant the content of
our thinking is probably more relevant
to our problems that the thinking of
Wales is is to our problems so that's
why I think reflexivity throws light on
the human condition and that's how I see
the the to relate to each other and
presumably our primate ancestors will
have reflexive relations well they've
won one of the things another is about
to take over their place as the other if
I described if I described marriage as a
reflexive relationship then certainly
monkeys would qualify for okay thank you
very much my name is Fernando shmita and
ambassador of Chile I see a lot of South
American people here well my question is
very simple can you elaborate a little
bit more on reflexivity reflexivity and
emotions well certainly
first of all reason and emotion are in
act inescapably connected that's one of
the discoveries of brain science which
confirms humans contention so so this
concept of the disembodied intellect was
a I think is currently superseded but it
isn't purely emotion that kind of
interferes with reason they're on our
rational problems in reflexive
situations so for instance because of
this force
dichotomy between reason and emotion and
his concept of disembodied intellect and
rational behavior Alan Greenspan
described bubbles the specifically the
the IT of all the the technology bubble
as irrational exuberance his famous
words that he applied in 1996 well it
missed describes bubbles because if I as
a market participant see a bubble coming
I buy because that's the profitable
thing the rational thing to do and that
creates bubbles so you can't rely on
markets to prevent asset bubbles from
forming and therefore he was wrong to
describe it as irrational and in fact
you can't account on rational behavior
preventing bubbles so that's a problem
that needs to be solved and actually
requires the regulators to accept
responsibility for preventing asset
bubbles from growing too large so a
misinterpretation of what bubbles are or
how financial markets operate lead to
the wrong policies so emotions may be
involved in the Flexi situation but it's
not necessarily it's not emotion it's
not because it's fear and greed it's in
the nature as I will try to explain
tomorrow why and how it is in the nature
of financial markets that they are
bubble prone not equilibrium bound
okay who's next gentleman front row oh I
miss you student and a mistress today
what is the secret of your financial
success in reflect of your family story
thank you sorry
goodnight bit what is my to come up and
maybe can you say it again what is the
secret of your financial success in
reflect of your family story thank you
I would say that recognizing that I may
be wrong as simple as that
shall we move to the gentleman here yes
delighted to see you I speak into this
should we conclude that there are no
real lessons from history but only
subjective interpretations no I know I
don't know how you reach that conclusion
from what I said because it cannot be
tested about but about I was arguing
that the methods of natural science as
described so elegantly by offer to not
apply to the study of history it doesn't
mean that we cannot study history that
you cannot learn lessons that we can't
make reasonable contingent predictions
but not by this methods which produce
timelessly valid universally valid laws
history is one direction it's not
timeless it's time bound and when you
start with that then you need different
methods for studying historical
processes and I will argue in subsequent
lectures that economic theory as such
takes the wrong approach because it
looks for these universally valid laws
like if you have in physics whereas you
really need to study markets in the
financial markets and financial
processes in a context and you have to
recognize that conditions change and and
actually don't
repeat themselves maybe in the middle
there I need a good way for the mic my
name is catalina akash and i'm a
professor of philosophy here at the
Central European University my question
is related exactly to this last point
that you made as you emphasize that
poppers theory of falsification was an
explanation of how science can be both
empirical and rational because we have
the universal laws we create a test
situation and if there is a falsifying
instance we can give up the law and they
on the basis of what you said we cannot
apply the same apparatus in these social
sciences because we cannot aim to have
universal laws so I was wondering how do
you think we can hold up social sciences
to the requirements of being rational
and empirical you see I think that
social science can produce universally
valid laws but those laws don't
determine the course of events so for
instance I think I put forward the human
uncertainty principle as a universally
valid hypothesis and I believe it is
actually universally valid but by its
very nature it doesn't determine it
cannot determine how markets whether
that's if financial markets or or
or history is going to evolve in other
words human behavior is unpredictable
and that's the law yes yes yes but there
are actually some for instance
statistical generalizations I mean I I
will distinguish between near
equilibrium conditions and far from
equilibrium conditions and it is in the
nature near equilibrium conditions that
you can make statistical generalizations
and you can calculate risk on that basis
however in far from equilibrium
conditions that particular method is
going to and lend you in difficulties
because those things that apply in near
equilibrium don't apply and far from
equilibrium condition that's another
generalization here is the question from
this side even microphone over here yeah
no that's okay there's a yeah Julia sort
of our Economics Department see you
first question mr. surage is your
opinion or understanding of popper
changing as time goes by
are you more critical or more supportive
now as you were let's say in the 50s you
mentioned during your student years and
second question is that let me answer
that because I forget advocated by my
opinion of popper is evolving I have
become more critical of him as time went
on and of course he's not around to
defend himself which is but also
actually in preparing these lectures I
went a little too far in criticizing
popper and then I had to revise it
because because he actually for instance
and did recognize reflexivity
he only applied it to social sciences
but if pressed he would he would
certainly agree that it also applies
even with greater force to two
participants so but as you will hear in
subsequent lectures he took it for
granted that the purpose of thinking of
discourse is to get closer to the truth
and that's a false assumption it's a
it's what I call the Enlightenment
fallacy and and I of course he was a
critic of many of the excessive claims
for reason and nevertheless he and me
too fell into that trap and it has
forced me to modify my concept of open
society which I had adopted from him
these the second question oh we
understand that your critical position
towards the mainstream which basically
rules maybe from the from the late
seventies or this time period but the
question would be if it is relevant
which economic school you feel close to
because there is a you know a huge
number of schools not only what you call
you know know this this fundamental is
market fundamentalism you feel closer to
Schumpeter higher Keynes
night you mentioned thank you I was
definitely very much influenced by
Keynes and and I think that of course
he'd lived at a particular moment in
history where he had to deal with
incipient
with the problems of depression and
therefore he neglected the problems of
inflation but had he lived at a
different time I'm sure that he would
have been also his analysis would have
extended also to analysis of inflation
because of them because of that he
became discredited in the 70s when
inflation was the dominant problem of of
the time so I would say that I was I
would consider myself a follower of
games the same way as I'm a follower of
popper without necessarily agreeing with
everything they said that let me add to
what you were saying implies the first
question there
of course poppers name for reflectivity
the oedipus effect only tells you he
would have agreed that it can occur
between individuals because that was one
prediction about a particular man's
future action wasn't a social science
theory influencing rings so he obviously
would have agreed with the general
notion I think he was discussing he
doesn't he I think his if he was going
to give a name to I think he would have
called it interactivity not reflectivity
I think an element that you've
emphasized that he doesn't emphasize is
a positive feedback aspect he doesn't
ever make the point there that I make
the prediction of the event I change the
event that I predict and then that must
change the way I see the world he
doesn't see that with that circular
causation that you emphasize that's the
thing he doesn't he doesn't pick up I
think on that point
yeah who's like I can't see everybody so
clearly the su4 yes microphones coming
from
I'm Rahman Friedman professor of
economics at New York University
I have a couple of questions that limit
myself to two the first one is that I
think what gives reflects I just want to
comment on it you emphasize reflexivity
and there's a certain tension in your
writing and even in this speech about
the status of fallibility I wanted to
ask you where the fallibility in your
mind is necessary for objectivity to
have the force availability fallibility
being absolutely central and I wanted to
up Kent there's a the chairman's of the
spirit clearly indicated no speeches I
will give no speech I just want to
signal what I mean is that if there was
a mechanical connection between reality
and thinking and back to reality that's
reflexive that certainly would not be
something that would yield to the kind
of conclusions that you draw in the real
world context and that's where that
flexibility is actually quite different
from popper from from from from Merton
it's very different than a
self-fulfilling prophecy that has a
vague notion but that suggests such a
mechanical connection first I will want
to give a comment on the second question
that is directly in my mind related to
this which was us actually a phenomenal
question about educational reflexivity
by the gentleman from Brazil because
that question suggests one one wonders
whether it is complexity that underpins
reflexivity
my conjecture here I have some thoughts
on that is that it is exactly the way
Colleen just said that the very
this change and it's actually a non
routine change that is crucial for
reflexivity to have this force and you
can yes when you have education as Kane
said we can do more in understanding
things but at some point we're going to
reach the limit for it because there is
a question of non routine change that
will also that will always prevent a
complete understanding and therefore
reflectivities and is a is a property of
social systems to me and infallible 'ti
that are properties in principle these
are not properties that could be
eliminated with tank that can only be
eliminated if change in the world sees
which of course you have understood in
your understanding of the social systems
closed versus open
that's why reflexivity to me so that
this is basically a set of issues is
that flexibility really delay the
complexity rather than change and and
things that relate professor of course
tell ability is absolutely essential
it's a universal human condition and the
reflexivity
is a two-way connection between a biased
/ misconceptions and say the objective
reality and there are ways in which
misconceptions can actually change the
objective conditions
that's reflectivity but in order to have
life activity you must have the
misconceptions or the bias view to start
with otherwise you wouldn't have the
two-way connection so
it replaces this strange concoction of
perfect knowledge that is characteristic
of the prevailing dogma in in in
economics so that's in complexity yeah
Roman was asking about well you see this
is this is a issue that as I say I only
have a tentative answer at the moment
actually
reflexivity doesn't need to be complex
you see and therefore you can't say that
it's the same thing because actually
that flexibility can be something very
very simple like an enmity between
people where one person says to the
other you are my enemy and lo and behold
he is your enemy that's not that's not
complex I think what what other lives
reflexivity is awareness that i can be
aware of your attitudes towards me and
that can change myself but of course
when you're looking at the natural world
it's not aware of your your attitudes or
predictions about it Halley's Comet or
the motions of the planets so they can't
be influenced by our beliefs about them
but as humans we can be aware of other
people's beliefs about us as they
express them in statements and then that
can change us as a result of it
and it's so that I think is what new
facility comes from consciousness
awareness yes of others there's one
other point with regard to education you
see while education is a wonderful thing
it doesn't necessarily
give you very good results because
reality can be manipulated and and if
you are good at manipulating reality you
can get better results but how you
manipulate what your objectives are
depend on your values and values are
particularly how shall I say
questionable in others there is no one
set of values that you can say that's
good so so we have done a lot as a
foundation in the way of Education and
and sometimes we have educated very
clever manipulators of public opinion
who then used it to for very different
purposes for which I would have liked
them to use it I was a lady in the third
world a as a margaret de heinrich and
the one word that keeps popping up in my
mind from the very beginning of your
talk is instinct and professors what you
were talking about alluding to awareness
and of course that's the same thing and
you're someone mr. Soros has been
enormous ly successful and I imagine in
some part because of your natural
instinct and the question is if you're
sharing the concept of reflexivity with
so many people if they don't possess
that natural god-given gift of instinct
how can they truly take reflexivity
and use it to its full power I don't get
the question do well like I think the
question is you you have this conceptual
idea of reflexivity which you've applied
in your business life and could other
people have had the same success just by
taking over the idea or was it more to
do with
factors about you than just having that
theory I think that was the fourth
question well I mean we all we all have
the theory now we're not all
successfully yep
well look it's it's obviously it's not
sufficient really it's it's it's been
useful but it didn't determine the
outcome and but the fact is that at the
time when I first started using those
ideas they did give me a leg up in the
financial markets because people were
most other players in the market were
guided by other ideas
so however people did read my book so
I've lost that that that that edge that
I had yeah yeah it enables you to
predict bubbles movie it enables you to
predict bubbles more easily but you know
they're they're saying that economists
have predicted eight of the last three
recessions well I predicted eight of the
next three bubbles about Howard Robinson
in there in front he needs a microphone
I think any microphone nearby okay
this would be a philosophical question
I'm sure I was going to say I'm glasses
you're straight philosophical question
I'm afraid what do you think the
connection of your doctrine of
reflexivity is this old-fashioned
chestnut of free will does it follow
from what you said that there could not
be a deterministic account of human
behavior because in some sense or other
there are no definite facts about human
psychology or what people are going to
do these are not the kind of things that
we put into the natural laws and
therefore they determinism must be false
and got a libertarian free will must be
right or don't you want to go in and
down that road well we had a very
interesting discussion last night about
determinism and in free will and I would
take the position that that both are
half right and if you put them together
you actually get the reality to to think
of of free will as being absolutely free
is to me even more distorted than to
claim that human affairs are determined
by universally valid laws I mean there
are of course not not all of reality can
be manipulated there is you know there
are the laws of physics that that
prevail so you may be extremely good at
turning reality manipulating reality but
Indian reality has the last word and you
want to be dead now that's something for
instance you cannot manipulate a way
even though we have developed
all kinds of myths to deal with this
rather unpalatable prospect hmm well no
deterministic laws are psychology itself
well I mean I would say that that Freud
identified maybe certain people who are
a bear sick in the sense that they their
actions are determined by their in a fix
their their their preconceived ideas but
a well functioning human being has to be
influenced by his by reality yes and I
think your position is that the world is
half determined and the will is half
free hmm
the world is half determined and the
human will is half free okay she said it
was half to each of them was half true
who's next
something something more philosophical
would be welcome if there was something
yes go to the back iron you want to go
back one page okay he's got the
microphone of the Lancer right he's got
a microphone there hello thank you I am
Rodrigo from Mexico I am a student of
public policy at CU and first just to
say that I'm very grateful it's being a
very enriching experience being in in
this University in this environment and
I would like to ask you
Plato another philosopher had a negative
vision of time or an idea that time had
the generative effect over things of
reality on the other hand the paradigm
of modernity presents more of a faith in
progress conviction that the future will
be better than than the present
what do you think is this a Byzantine
discussion a pointless discussion or you
have understanding point what's the time
what's the effect of time over things
from your perspective thank you you know
I'm sorry about not fully understanding
the question should I repeat it very
briefly yeah I I mean my attitude to to
Plato has been greatly influenced by
Karl Popper although perhaps he has been
a little too harsh on tato
I think he's asking about progress
whether you believe in progress progress
I think so
what what do you think yes I certainly
have do believe in progress and
definitely think that that we can
improve our understanding and certainly
I would argue that let's say
understanding reflexivity makes dealing
with human problems political problems
much more difficult and some of our
preconceived ideas have to go out of the
window but it is progress because I
think we then understand the
difficulties involved in human affairs
and you usually misconceptions get
particularly wide and far-fetched when
you are confronted with insoluble
problems we don't like to tolerate
insoluble problems and therefore we tend
to design device force solutions again I
come back to the death which is an
insoluble problem in the
it's most likely to occur and we have
then developed all kinds of ways of and
myths to to do away with that prospect
and there are many other to grow from
the soup sublime to the ridiculous
the drop problem
it's an insoluble problem the drug
addiction is in the in is innate in in
in human nature some people get addicted
and it is a threat to society and
society then do usually did and the way
did we deals it it makes it a much worse
problem and then then then the drug
addiction itself and and the way for
instance American society has dealt it
with death has made dying much harder
and much more painful not to mention
more expensive then then then it need to
be and actually the two first projects
of my foundation in in in America one
was the project on death in America and
the other one was the drug policy
initiative and I arrived at it from this
rather abstract philosophical argument
about insoluble problems in Toledo da
ting remedies which make the problems
worse does that answer anywhere near
your question
enlighten me in other issues but yeah
basically I wanted to ask you what do
you think time the time time goes by
right and time has any kind of effect
over things over a political regime
Plato would say that time has a negative
effect and the effect of time over
things a turn turn it the generative as
opposed to that conception modernity
says that the effect of time over things
is positive and says the future will be
better now as against to the conception
of Plato do what do you think what's the
effect of that is if any at all or okay
it's maybe a bit like me I have to
interpret with which goes to wind up at
this point I'm told that it's the end of
the time and if you should do it
I know today's wonderful two hours has
only whetted your appetite for the
remainder of the week this has been an
extraordinary moment and I want to thank
our audiences here in Budapest at the
Hungarian Academy of Sciences and
Central European University and also in
London at the London School of Economics
but of course above all to thank George
Soros for sharing his thoughts his
experience his philosophy and launching
us on an extraordinary journey that will
all be going with him
and also to call him again so much for
thank you for all you've done to
facilitate today thank you very much