good afternoon
and welcome to the ceu lectures i'm john
shattuck president and director of
central european university
it's my great privilege to introduce
this special series of five lectures by
george soros held here in budapest
at the hungarian academy of sciences
under the auspices
of central european university in these
lectures
george soros will draw upon a lifetime
of practical
and philosophical reflection and share
his latest thinking on economics and
politics
today mr soros will present the
fundamentals of his
philosophical theory each lecture will
be video conferenced
to one of five universities on four
continents creating
an unprecedented interactive
international
audience of students in real time
today's lecture will include students
from the london school of economics
in addition to the invited guests and
central european university students who
are here
at the academy our moderator today
is the distinguished philosopher colin
mcginn renowned for his work in the
philosophy of mind
mr soros will lecture for approximately
50 minutes
and mr mcginn will offer a brief
response mr soros will then take
questions from the audience
starting with three questions from the
london school of economics and then
from our audience here in budapest
i'm now delighted to present george
soros
who truly needs no introduction
thank you very much and thank you for
all for
coming and both here and in london
in the course of of my life i've
developed a conceptual framework
which has helped me both in
make money making money as a hedge fund
manager
and in spending it as a policy oriented
philanthropist but the framework itself
is not about money it's about the
relationship between thinking
and reality a subject that is
extensively studied by philosophers
from early on
i started developing my philosophy as a
student
at the london school of economics in the
late 1950s
i took my final exams one year early
and i had a year to fill before i was
qualified to receive my degree
i could choose my own tutor and i chose
karl popper
who whose book the open society and its
enemies
had made a profound impression on me
in his books popper argued
that the empirical truth can't be known
with absolute certainty even
scientific laws can't be verified
beyond the shadow of a doubt they can
only be
falsified by testing one fair test
is enough to to falsify but no amount of
confirming instances
is sufficient to verify
scientific laws are hypothetical in
character
and their truth remains subject to
testing
ideologies which claim to be in
possession of the ultimate truth
are making a false claim therefore
they can be imposed on society only by
force
this applies to communism fascism and
national socialism alike
all these ideologies lead to repression
papa proposed a more attractive form of
social
organization a society an open society
in which people are free to hold diverse
divergent opinions and the rule of law
allows people with different views and
different interests
to live together in peace
having lived through both nazi and
communist occupation here in hungary
i found the idea of an open society
immensely
attractive while i was reading popper
i was also studying economic theory
and i was struck by the contradiction
between
papa's emphasis on imperfect
understanding
and the theory of perfect competition in
economics
which postulated perfect knowledge this
led me to start
questioning the assumptions of economic
theory
these were the two major
inspirations of my philosophy
it's also deeply rooted in my personal
history
the formative the formative experience
of my life
was the german occupation of hungary in
i was not yet 14 years old at the time
coming from a reasonably well to do
middle class background
suddenly confronted with the prospect of
being deported and killed
just because i was jewish fortunately
my father was well prepared for this far
from equilibrium experience
he had lived through the russian
revolution and that was diplomatic
experience of his life until then
he had been an ambitious young man when
the first world war broke out
he volunteered to serve in the
austro-hungarian army
he was captured by the russians and
taken as a prisoner of war
to siberia being ambitious he became
the editor of a newspaper produced by
the prisoners
it was hand written and displayed on a
plank
and it was called the plank this made
him
so popular that he was elected the
prisoner's
representative then some soldiers
escaped
from a neighboring camp and their
prisoners representative
was shot in retaliation my father
is instead of waiting
for the same thing to happen in his camp
organized a breakout
his plan was to build a raft
and sail down to the ocean
but his knowledge of geography was
somewhat deficient
he didn't realize that all the rivers
in siberia flow into the arctic
they drifted for several weeks before
their
they realized that they were heading for
the arctic
and it took them several more months to
make their
way back to civilization across the
tiger
in the meantime the russian revolution
broke out
and they became caught up in it
only after a variety of adventures
did my father manage to find his way
back to hungary had he remained in the
camp he would have
arrived home much sooner
my father came home a changed man
his experiences during the russian
revolution profoundly
profoundly affected him he lost his
ambition
and wanted nothing more from life than
to enjoy it
he imparted to his children values that
were very different from those
of the milieu in which we lived he had
no desire to amass wealth
or become socially prominent on the
contrary
he worked only as much as was necessary
to make ends meet i remember being sent
to his main client to borrow some money
before we went on a skiing holiday my
father was grouchy for
months afterwards because he had to work
to pay
it back although we were
reasonably prosperous we were not the
typical bourgeois family
and we were proud of being different
in 1944 when
the germans occupied hungary my father
immediately realized that these were not
normal times and the normal rules
didn't apply he arranged false
identities
for his family and the number number of
other people
those who could paid
others he held for free most of them
survived that was his finest hour
living with false identity turned out to
be an
exhilarating experience for me too
we were in mortal danger people
perished all around us but we managed
not only to survive
but to help other people we were on the
side of the angels
and we triumphed against overwhelming
odds
this made me feel very special
it was high adventure i had a reliable
guide
in my father and came through unscathed
what more could a 14 year old ask for
after the euphoric experience
of escaping the nazis life in hungary
started to lose its luster during the
soviet occupation
i was looking for new challenges and
with the help of my father
i found my way out of hungary when i was
i became a student in london in my
studies
my primary interest was to gain a better
understanding
of the strange world into which i had
been born
but i have to confess i i also harbored
some fantasies of become becoming an
important
philosopher i believed that i had gained
insights that set me apart from other
people
living in london was a bit was a big
letdown
i was without money alone and people
were not interested in what i had to say
but i didn't abandon my philosophical
ambitions
even when circumstances forced me to
make a living
in more mundane pursuits
after completing my studies i had a
number of false starts
finally i ended up as an arbitrage
trader
in new york but in my free time
i continued to work on my philosophy
that's how i came to write my first
major essay entitled the burden of
consciousness
it was an attempt to model a purpose
framework
of open and close societies it linked
organic society with a traditional mode
of thinking
close society with a dogmatic mode
and uh and open society with a critical
mode
what i could not properly resolve was
the nature of the relationship between
the mode of thinking
and the actual state of affairs that
problem
continued to preoccupy me and that's how
i came to develop the concept of
reflexivity
a concept i shall explore in greater
detail
a little later it so happened
that the concept of reflexivity provided
me
with a new way of looking at financial
markets
a better way than the prevailing theory
this gave me an edge first as a
securities analyst
and then as a hedge fund manager i felt
as if i were in possession of a major
discovery
that would enable me to fulfill my
fantasy
of becoming an important philosopher
at a certain moment when my business
career
ran into a roadblock i shifted gears
and devoted all my energies to
developing
my theory but i treasured my discovery
so much
that i couldn't part with it i felt
that the concept of reflexivity needed
to be
explored in great depth as i delved
deeper and deeper into the subject
i got lost in the intricacies of my own
constructions one morning
i couldn't understand what i had written
the night before
at that point i decided to abandon my
philosophical explorations
and to focus on making money
it was only many years later after a
successful run as a hedge fund manager
that returned to my philosophy
i published my first uh first
essay the the the alchemy of finance
in 1987. in that book
i tried to explain the philosophical
underpinnings of my approach
to financial markets the book attracted
a certain amount of attention it has
been read
by by most people in the hedge fund
industry
and it is thought in business schools
but the
philosophical arguments didn't make much
of an
impression they were largely dismissed
as the conceit of a man who has been
successful in business
and fancied himself as a philosopher
i myself came to doubt
whether i was in possession of a major
new insight
after all i was dealing with a subject
that has been explored by philosophers
since time immemorial what grounds did i
have for thinking
that i had made a new discovery
especially as nobody else seems to think
so
undoubtedly the conceptual framework
was useful to me personally but it
didn't seem to be
equally value considered equally
valuable by others
i had to accept that judgment i didn't
give up
my philosophical interests but i came to
regret them as
a personal predilection i continued to
be
guided by my conceptual framework both
in my business and in my philanthropic
activities which came to assume an
increasingly important role in my life
and each time i wrote a book i
faithfully recited
my arguments this helped me to develop
my conceptual framework but i can
consider
continued to consider myself a failed
philosopher once i even gave a lecture
with the with the title a failed
philosopher
tried twice again
all this has changed as a result
of the financial crisis of 2008.
my conceptual framework enabled me both
to anticipate the crisis
and to deal with it when it finally
struck
it has also enabled me to explain
and predict events better than most
others
this has changed my own
evaluation and that of many others
my philosophy is no longer a
personal matter it deserves to be taken
seriously
as a possible contribution to our
understanding of reality
and that is what has prompted me to give
this series of lectures
so here it goes
today i shall explain the concept
of ref of fallibility and reflexivity
in general terms tomorrow i shall apply
them
to the financial markets and after that
to politics that will also bring in
the concept of open society in the
fourth lecture
i shall explore the difference between
market values
and moral values and in the fifth i
shall give
some predictions and prescriptions
for the present moment in history
i can state the core idea
in two relatively simple propositions
one is that the situation
that has thinking participants the
participants view of the world
is always partial and distorted
that's the principle of fallibility the
other is
that these distorted views can
influence the situation to which
they relate because false views
lead to inappropriate actions
that's the principle of reflexivity
for instance treating drug addicts
as criminals creates criminal behavior
it misconstrues the problem and
interferes with the proper treatment of
addicts
as another example declaring
that government is bad tends to make for
bad government
both fallibility and reflexivity
are sheer common sense so when my
critics
say that i am merely stating the obvious
they are right up to a point
what makes my propositions interesting
is that their significance
significance has not been generally
appreciated
the concept of reflexivity in particular
has been studiously avoided and even
denied
by economic theory so my conceptual
framework deserves to be taken seriously
not because it constitutes a new
discovery
but because something as commonsensical
as reflexivity
has been so studiously ignored
recognizing reflexivity has been
sacrificed
to the vain pursuit of certainty in
human affairs
mostly most notably in economics
and yet uncertainty is the key feature
of human affairs economic theory
is built on the concept of equilibrium
and that concept is in direct
contradiction
with the concept of reflexivity as i
shall try to show
in the next lecture the two concepts
yield to two entirely different
interpretations
of financial markets
the concept of fallibility is far less
controversial
it's generally recognized that the
complexity of the world
in which we live exceeds our capacity to
comprehend it
i have no great new insights to offer
the main source of difficulty is that
participants are part
of the situation they have to deal with
confronted
by a reality of extreme complexity
we are obliged to resort to various
methods of simplification
generalizations dichotomies metaphors
decision rules moral precepts to mention
just a few
these mental constructs take on an
existence of their own
further complicated complicating the
situation
the structure of the brain is another
source of distortions
recent advances in brain science have
begun to provide
some insight into how the brain
functions
and they have substantiated hume's
contention that reason is the slave of
passion
the idea of a disembodied intellect or
reason
is a figment of our imagination
the being the brain is bombarded
by millions of sensory impulses
but consciousness can only process only
seven or eight subjects concurrently
the impulses need to be condensed
ordered
and interpreted under events time
pressure
and mistakes and distortions can't be
avoided
brain science adds many new details
to my original contention that our
understanding of the world in which we
live
is inherently imperfect
the concept of reflexivity needs
a little more explanation it applies
exclusively to situations that have
thinking participants
the participants thinking serves two
functions
one is to understand the world in which
we live
i call this the cognitive function
the other is to change the situation to
our advantage
i call this the part the manipulating
or participating function the two
functions
connect thinking and reality in opposite
directions in the cognitive function
reality is supposed to determine at the
participants views
the direction of causation is from the
world
to the mind by contrast in the
manipulative function
the direction of causation is from the
mind
to the world that is to say the
intentions of the participants have an
effect
on the world when both functions operate
at the same time
they can interfere with each other how
by depriving each function of the
independent variable
that would be needed to determine the
value of the dependent variable
because when the independent variable
of one function is the dependent
variable of the other
neither function has a genuinely
independent variable
this means that the cognitive function
can't produce enough knowledge to serve
as the basis
of the participants decisions similarly
the manipulative function can can have
an
effect on the outcome but can't
determine it
in other words the outcome is liable to
diverge
from the participants intentions
there is bound to be some slippage
between
intentions and actions and further
slippage
between actions and outcomes
as a result there is an element of
uncertainty
both in our understanding of reality
and in the actual course of in
events to
understand the uncertainties
associated with reflexivity we need to
probe a little
further if the cognitive function
operated in isolation without any
interference from the manipulative
function
it could produce knowledge knowledge is
represented by two statements a
statement is true
if it corresponds to the facts that's
what the correspondence theory of truth
tells us but if there is
interference from
the the manipulative function
the facts no longer serve as an
independent criterion by which the truth
of a statement can be judged
because the correspondence may have been
brought about
by the statement changing the facts
consider the statement it's raining
that statement is true or false
depending on whether it is in fact
raining
now consider the statement this is a
revolutionary moment
that statement is reflexive and this
truth value depends on the impact
it makes reflexive statements
have some affinity with the paradox of
the liar
which is a self-referential statement
but while self-reference has been
extensively analyzed
reflexivity has received much less
attention that's strange because
reflexivity has an impact on the real
world
while self-reference is purely a
linguistic
phenomenon in the real world
the participants thinking finds
expression
not only in statements but also in
various forms of
action and behavior that makes
reflexivity
a very broad phenomenon that typically
takes the form of feedback loops
the participants views influence the
course of events
and the course of events influences the
participants views
the influence is continuous and circular
that's what makes that's what turns it
into
a feedback loop
reflexive feedback loops have not been
rigorously analyzed and when i
originally encountered them
and tried to analyze them i ran into
various complications
the feedback loop is supposed to be
a two-way connection between the
participants views
and the actual course of events but what
about
a two-way connection between the
participants views
and what about the solitary individual
asking himself
who he is and what he stands for and
changing his behavior as a result of his
reflections
in trying to resolve these difficulties
i got so long lost among the categories
i created
that one morning i couldn't understand
what i had written the night before
that's when i gave up philosophy and
devoted my efforts
to making money
so to avoid that trap
let me propose the following the
terminology
let's distinguish between the objective
and subjective aspects of reality
thinking constitutes the subjective
aspect
events the objective in other words
the subjective aspect covers what takes
place
in the minds of the participants the
objective aspect
denotes what takes place in this in
external
reality there's only one external
reality
but many different subjective views
reflexivity
can then connect any two or more aspects
of reality setting up two-way
feedback loops exceptionally it may even
occur
within a single aspect of reality as in
the case of a solitary individual
reflecting on his own identity this may
be described
as self reflexivity
we may then distinguish between two
broad
categories reflexive relationships
which connect the subjective aspects and
reflexive events which involve the
objective aspect as well
marriage is a reflexive relationship
the crash of 2008
was a reflexive event when reality has
no subjective aspect
there can be no reflexivity
feedback pollutes can be either negative
or positive negative feedback
it brings the participants views and
the actual situation closer together
positive feedback drives them further
apart
in other words negative feedback
is self-correcting it can go on forever
if and if there are no significant
changes
in external reality it may eventually
lead
to an equilibrium where the participants
views
come to correspond to the actual state
of affairs
that is what's supposed to happen in
financial markets
so equilibrium which is the central case
in economics turns out to be
a limiting case
in my conceptual framework
by contrast a positive feedback process
is self-reinforcing it can't go on
forever
because eventually the participants
views
would become so far removed from
objective reality
that the participants would have to
recognize them
as unrealistic nor can the iterative
process
occur without any change in the actual
state of affairs
because it's in the nature of positive
feedback
that it reinforces whatever tendency
prevails
in the real world instead of equilibrium
we are faced with a dynamic
disequilibrium
or what may be described as far from
equilibrium
conditions usually
in far from equilibrium situations the
divergence
between perceptions and reality leads to
a climax
which sets emotion a positive feedback
process
in the opposite direction such
initially self-reinforcing but
eventually self-defeating
boom bust processes or bubbles
are characteristic of financial markets
but they can also be observed
in other spheres there i call them
fertile fallacies interpretations of
reality
that are distorted yet produce results
which reinforce the distortion
i realize that this is all very abstract
and difficult to follow it would be it
would make it much easier if i gave
some concrete examples but
you'll have to bear with me i want to
make a different point
and the fact that it's so difficult to
follow abstract arguments
helps me to make it in dealing with
subjects like
reality or thinking or the relationship
between thinking
and reality it's easy to get
confused and formulate problems
the wrong way so misinterpretations and
misconceptions
can play a very important role in your
role
in human affairs the recent financial
crisis can be attributed to a mistaken
interpretation
of how financial markets work i shall
discuss that
in the next lecture in the third
lecture i shall discuss two fertile
fallacies
the enlightenment fallacy and the
postmodern
fallacy these concrete examples will
demonstrate
how important misconceptions have been
in the course of history but for the
rest of this lecture i shall stay at the
lofty heights of abstraction
i contend that situations
that have thinking participants
have a different structure from
natural phenomena the different
difference lies
in the role of thinking in a natural
phenomena
thinking plays no causal role
and serves only a cognitive function
in human affairs thinking is
part of the subject matter and serves
both
a cognitive and a manipulative
function the two functions can
interfere with each other the
interference
doesn't occur all the time in everyday
activities like
driving a car or painting a house
the two functions actually complement
each other
but when it occurs it introduces an
element of uncertainty
which is absent from natural phenomena
the uncertainty manifests itself in both
functions
the participants act on the basis of
imperfect
understanding and the results of their
actions
will not correspond to their
expectations
i call that the human uncertainty
principle
and i consider it a key feature of human
affairs
by contrast in the case of natural
phenomena
events unfold irrespective of the views
held by the observers the outside
observer
is engaged only in the cognitive
function
and the phenomena provide a reliable
criterion
by which the truth of the observer's
theories can be judged
so the outside observer can obtain
knowledge
based on that knowledge nature can be
successfully manipulated
there is a natural separation between
the cognitive
and manipulative function and due to
that
separation both functions can serve
their purpose better
than in the human sphere
at this point i need to
emphasize that reflexivity
is not the only source of uncertainty
in human affairs yes reflexivity does
introduce an element of uncertainty
both into the participants views and the
actual course of events
but other factors may also have the same
effect
for instance the fact that participants
can't know what the other participants
know
is something quite different from
reflexivity
yet it's a source of uncertainty the
fact
that different participants have
different interests some of which may be
in conflict with each other
is another source of uncertainty
moreover
each individual participant may be
guided
by a multiplicity of values which may
not be self-consistent
as isaiah berlin has pointed out
the uncertainties created by these
factors are likely to be
even more extensive than those generated
by reflexivity i have lumped them all
together
and and when i speak of the human
uncertainty principle
which is an even broader concept than
reflexivity
the human uncertainty principle i'm
talking about
is much more specific and stringent
than the subjective skepticism
that pervades cartesian philosophy
it gives an uh an objective reason to
believe
that our perceptions and expectations
are or at least maybe wrong
although the primary impact
of human uncertainty falls under
participants
it has far-reaching implications for the
social sciences
i can explicate them best by
invoking karl power's theory of
scientific method
it's a beautifully simple and elegant
scheme
it consists of three elements and
three operations the three elements
are scientific laws and
the initial and final conditions to
which those
laws apply the three operations are
prediction explanation and testing
when the scientific laws are combined
with the initial conditions
they provide predictions when they are
combined
with the final conditions they provide
explanations
in this sense predictions and
are symmetrical and reversible
that leaves testing where predictions
derived from scientific laws
are compared with the actual results
according to popper scientific laws
are hypothetical in character they can't
be verified they can only be
falsified by testing the key
to the success of scientific method is
that it can test generalizations of
universal validity
with the help of singular observations
one failed test is sufficient sufficient
to falsify a theory
but no amount of confirming instances is
sufficient to verify
this is a brilliant solution to the
otherwise intractable problem
how can science be both empirical
and rational according to popper
it's empirical because we test our
theories
by observing whether the the predictions
we derive from them are true and it's
rational
because we use deductive logic
in doing so papa dispenses
with inductive logic and relies instead
on
testing generalizations that
can't be tested do not qualify
as scientific papers
emphasis on the central role of testing
plays a very important role in
scientific method and
establishes a strong case for
critical thinking but by asserting that
scientific laws are only provisionally
valid
and remain open to re-examination
thus the three salient features of
papa's
scheme are the symmetry
between prediction and explanation the
asymmetry between verification
and falsification and the central role
of testing testing allows science
to grow improve and innovate
proper scheme works well for the study
of natural phenomena but the human
uncertainty principle throws a monkey
range
into the supreme simplicity and elegance
of papa's scheme the symmetry mat
at the symmetry between predictions
and explanations is destroyed because
of the element of uncertainty in
predictions
and the central role of testing is
endangered
should the initial and final conditions
include or exclude the participants
thinking
the question is important because
testing
requires replicating those conditions
if the participants thinking is included
it's difficult to observe what the
initial and final conditions are
because the participants views can only
be inferred
from their statements or actions if it's
excluded
the initial and final conclusions don't
constitute singular observations because
the same objective conditions may be
associated
with very different views held by the
participants
in either case generalizations can't be
properly
tested these difficulties don't
preclude social scientists from
producing
worthwhile generalizations but they are
unlikely to meet
the requirements of proper scheme nor
can they match the predictive power of
the laws
of physics
scientific social scientists have
found this this conclusion hard to
accept
economists in particular suffer from
what sigmund freud
might call physics envy
and there have been many attempts to
eliminate
the difficulties connected with the
human uncertainty principle
by in inventing or postulating
some kind of fixed relationship
between the participants thinking and
the actual state of affairs
karl marx asserted that the ideological
superstructure
was determined by the material
conditions of production
and freud maintained that people's
behavior
was determined determined by drives
and complexes of which they were not
even aware
both claimed scientific status
for their theories although as popper
pointed out
they can't be falsified by testing
but by far the most impressive attempt
has been mounted by economic theory
it started out by assuming perfect
knowledge
and when that assumption turned out to
be unsustainable
it went through an increasing
contortions
to maintain the fiction of rational
behavior
economics ended up with the theory of
rational expectations which maintains
that there is a single optimum view of
the future
that which corresponds to it and
eventually
all the market participants will
converge around that view
this postulate is absurd but
it is needed in order to allow economic
theory
to model itself on newtonian physics
interestingly both karl popper and
friedrich hire
recognized in their famous exchange in
the pages of economica
that the social sciences can't produce
results compared comparable to physics
hayek invade against the mechanical
and uncritical application of the
quantitative methods of natural
science he called it scientism
and carl proper wrote about the poverty
of historicism
where he argued that history is not
determined
by universally valid scientific laws
nevertheless popper proclaimed
what he called the doctrine of the unity
of method
by which he meant that both natural and
social sciences should be judged
by the same criteria and hayek of course
became the apostle of the chicago school
of economics
where market fundamentalism was born
but as i see it the implication of the
human
uncertainty principle is that the
subject matter of the natural
and social sciences is fundamentally
different
therefore they need to develop different
methods and they have to be held
to different standards economic theory
should not be expected to produce
universally valid laws
that can be used reversally to explain
and predict historic
events i contend that the slavish
imitation of natural science
inevitably leads to the distortion
of human and social phenomena what is
attainable
in social science falls short of what is
in in in physics
i am somewhat troubled however
about drawing a sharp distinction
between
the naturals and social sciences
such dichotomies are usually not found
in reality
they are introduced by us in our efforts
to make some sense out of an otherwise
confusing reality
indeed while a sharp distinction
between physics and social sciences
seems justified there are other sciences
such as biology than the study of animal
societies
that occupy intermediate position
but i had to abandon my reservations
and recognize a dichotomy because
the social sciences encounter a
second difficulty from which the natural
sciences
are exempt and that is
that social theories are reflexive
heisenberg's discovery of the
uncertainty principle
didn't alter the behavior of of quantum
particles one iota
but social theories whether marxism
market fundamentalism or the theory of
reflexivity
can affect the subject matter to which
it refers
scientific method is supposed to be
devoted to the pursuit of truth
heisenberg's uncertainty principle does
not interfere
with that postulate but the reflexivity
of social theories does
why should social science science
confine itself
to passively studying social phenomena
when it can be used to actively change
the state of affairs as i
remarked in the alchemy of finance our
the the alchemy of finance the
alchemists
made a mistake in trying to change
the nature of base metals by incantation
instead they should have focused their
attention
on the financial markets where they
could have succeeded
how how could how could social science
be protected against this interference
i proposed a simple remedy recognize
a dichotomy between the natural and
social sciences
this will ensure that social theories
will be judged on their merits and not
by a false analogy
with natural science i propose this
as a convention for the protection of
scientific
method not as a demotion or
devaluation of social science the
convention
sets no limits on what social science
may be able to accomplish on the
contrary
by liberating social science for the
from the slavish
imitation of natural science and
protecting it from being judged
by the wrong standards it should open up
new vistas it's in this spirit that i
shall
put forward my interpretation of
financial
markets tomorrow i apologize
for dwelling so long in the rarified
realm of abstractions i promise to come
down to earth
in my next lecture tomorrow thank you
you