I hope we may be able to elaborate a
little bit more on this inet initiative
during the question and answer session
if any of you would like to uh ask some
questions about it uh but I wanted to
reflect in the uh seven or eight minutes
that I've been given on uh George's
broader ideas listening to George today
I was reminded of when we first met it
was in 1983 during the first of the
bubbles he mentioned the third world
debt crisis and was actually at the
annual meeting of the World Bank and IMF
I was then a young journalist working
for the financial times and I just ran
into him by accident we were talking
about what it was that the IMF was doing
wrong in Mexico and Brazil at that time
but for me his ideas were really a
revelation perhaps because I was so
young at the time uh and we became
friends and I followed the development
of georg's ideas closely enough to feel
that I really understood them so that
when he published what I still think was
his most important book The Alchemy of
Finance I felt like an initiate into a
secret religious sect uh not because I
worship George or indeed his ideas far
from it but because I was told at that
time by almost everybody I met the
Georgia's philosophy was totally
incomprehensible the reason people
bought that first book was because they
thought they would pick up some
investment tips yet I felt to me these
Concepts that he first described fully
in that book of and that he mentioned
today of reflexivity fallibility and
human uh uncertainty and particularly
the relationship between those three
concepts to me me those Concepts seemed
absolutely clear and
revelatory others as I said differed and
only bought the books for investment
tips but even though George was told
initially that his ideas were
incomprehensible he continued to explain
them with the combination of persistence
self-confidence and
self-criticism which has made him so
successful also as an investor and the
interesting thing now is that when he
talks about reflexivity as I think he
probably did most articulately in this
lecture now everybody in the markets
claims to understand reflexivity
perfectly in fact if they couldn't
understand it they would not be able to
uh continue in their jobs in the markets
uh and even in the policymaking world
among Central Bankers he mentioned mvin
King and finance ministers the idea that
the world goes through reflexive boombas
Cycles between finance and policy is now
pretty much accepted as the conventional
wisdom it's really only among academic
economists that this idea is not
recognized and perhaps although only
perhaps as George said uh the
development of inet will uh lead to um
its further uh it it its further
development but as reflexivity has now
become such Common Ground among
economists and policy makers all over
the world uh I want to put on uh if you
like my perverse my challenging hat and
actually disagree and challenge some of
the ideas that George put forward today
briefly uh the boomas sequences as
George said in his lecture can be
interrupted by government intervention
or other exogenous forces and the
question I want to raise is whether it's
possible that the world does in fact
tend into equilibrium despite what we've
just heard provided the periods are long
enough and not solely through the
operation of markets but through the
operation of markets interacting with
government if we take the role of
government into account is it possible
that the world does actually tend to
equilibrium orbe it going through fairly
large Cycles in a way this actually
relates to a theory that George first
discussed during that third world debt
crisis which he called the brink Theory
the idea that events push uh crisis to
the brink of complete chaos but not
quite over the brink and this is of
course a concept that's also uh been
developed in uh the mathematical theory
of complexity and Chaos where the world
is always or complex systems are always
said to be operating just on the edge of
chaos maybe the Super Bubble of finance
and regulation he uh he he's discussed
and indeed the even bigger Super Bubble
of Market fundamentalism and if you like
Keynesian Social Democratic politics is
not after all a bubble but in a sense a
process of evolution and maybe there is
an equilibrating mechanism are what
George called the brink Theory and what
might be called the mechanisms of polic
politics and democracy in other words
maybe there is an equilibrating
mechanism within politics which prevents
these boom bust Cycles in in Market
fundamentalism in economics going too
far George described how all bubbles are
created by a trend and a misconception
and it's absolutely clear that the
misconception not of just of the last
two or three years but really of the
last 20 years was as he said that
markets could totally replace politics
in ordering Human Society but maybe that
misconception is now going to be
corrected leading to the emergence if
you like of a new form of
capitalism and I think the key to this
new form of capitalism is it if it
emerges will in fact go back to
Georgia's three concepts of reflexivity
fallibility and human
uncertainty in my view we are perhaps
moving into a fourth phase of capitalism
if you like the first phase 19th century
capitalism was when politics and
economics were believed to be totally
distinct and both were believed to be
evolving in a generally constructive
Direction by the conventional wisdom or
were believed to be both doomed to
failure if you're a Marxist both
economics and politics would were
believed to be either constructive or
doomed to failure in the 1930s that
perception changed and from 1930s to the
70s we went through a phase when there
was a widespread belief that markets
were always prone to failure and social
injustice but governments were always
knowledgeable and just in other words
the market was always wrong the
government was always right in the 70s
there was another Revolution and from
1979 with the election of Margaret
Thatcher 1980 onwards we went through a
third stage in which the prevailing
belief if you like the prevailing
misconception was that markets were
always efficient and rational while
governments were always wrong now it
seems to me as a out of last year's
crisis we could be moving into a fourth
stage where it is recognized that both
markets and governments are fallible not
always fallible but frequently fallible
now the last point I'd like to make is a
more positive one which is that the
recognition of fallibility sounds
paralyzing but actually it can be
empowering fallibility and the
recognition the explicit recognition of
human uncertainty is George describes
creat space for change Innovation
creativity imagination and
Leadership and it forces
empiricism self-analysis and internal
self-correction and in my view nobody
has symbolized such creative con uh such
creative tension between fallibility and
confident self- knowledge both in his
business and his philosophical ideas as
George Soros thank you very
much if I may briefly uh respond before
with while people at the MIT prepar
their questions uh uh you may be right
and and certainly if we take that step
forward and recognize that both markets
and governments are failable liable to
make mistakes and therefore willing to
correct their mistakes uh we are more
likely uh to actually uh develop a
system uh which does not uh end in a
financial crisis however if we made that
assumption uh that we have reached such
a system should surely there are the
seeds of the next financial crisis so
you have to
assume that you will not be able to do
it in order to achieve it and as you as
you
know we've actually really
extended the uh the financial cycle by
several decades through
intervention uh and so to that extent
interventions were really very
successful uh how however then they made
the bubble when it's the Super Bubble um
that much greater uh and the and the the
the great crisis of 20 crash of 2008 was
preceded by the great
moderation when you know risk uh
assessments were at at a minimum so
that's the
contradiction and that's the the kind of
awareness of reality that we need in
order to uh maintain
balance I would agree with you that the
the system can only continue if there is
a systemic change not just a marginal
change if there is a systemic change and
not just in finance but in the whole
relationship of markets and government
that's right now whether that happens or
not as you say very much remains to be
seen the jury's out and in fact perhaps
the evidence is becoming less favorable
to that point of view but actually I
will will address exactly that question
in in my last lecture uh shall We Now go
to MIT uh where uh we'll take the first
uh set of questions and then we'll move
to the audience here in Budapest uh do
we have uh a question uh to start with
from MIT
yes we have three questions prepare good
afternoon Mr Soros Mr ketki and CU
participants first
question yes we can hear could you talk
a bit a bit more slowly because uh then
we'll we'll hear more
clearly very good can you hear
me can you hear
me okay I guess you can uh yes my name
is Mark I'm an alumnist of MIT
do we have we can't hear you have we
have we lost the sound we have lost the
sound for the moment pressure mic
again there we go yes um my name is Mark
lar I'm an alumnus of uh MIT and a
professor of management at suffk
University in Boston I'd like to thank
Mr Soros for a blast of fresh air and
unorthodox thinking uh I have a question
about the role of uh private incentives
and compensation incentives of top
managers as a possible um source of
distortion I'm wondering whether that's
a major or a minor factor in such crisis
and whether Mr s has some
recommendations about how to regulate
the uh compensation and incentives of
top
managers well I mentioned that
institutions uh that are too big to fail
have to submit
to government regulation of
salaries and there is at the moment some
serious um I would say
social injustice in the very large
bonuses that people in those
institutions earn
because the earnings currently are due
to a hidden subsidy that the banks are
receiving by keeping interest rates at
zero and allowing them to invest for
instance in government bonds 10year
bonds yielding 3 and a half% that's 3
and a half% free and clear hidden
subsidy this is the route that we have
chosen following the the Japanese
example uh to allow the banks to earn
their way out of a hole and I think for
the employees of the banks to then get
an extra bonus on that money actually is
socially
unacceptable another question from
MIT hello my name is am kalar I'm a
Sloan MBA student and I want to thank
you first for having this talk with us
um can you please share your views on
the comments made yesterday by Professor
rubini about the status of the US Dollar
carry trades and the consequences which
may arise when these positions will
unfold and do you think we're
experiencing a a new bubble evolving
thank
you uh I didn't actually read those
those comments so I don't know what you
are uh referring referring to but uh
certainly there are
currently uh
imbalances uh uh in uh the financial
system uh due to the uh quantitative
easing and the
availability of free financing so that
is actually for the moment uh to the
extent that the stimulus is applied in
the United States which uh really would
need to reduce its Uh current account uh
deficit uh the stimulus is applied in
the wrong place and is building up the
imbalances which were partially uh
responsible for the crisis in what sense
do you mean it's being applied in the
wrong place the stimulus well because to
to balance the world
economy the United States has been
consuming significantly more 6 and a
half% more at the end uh than it was
producing and that built up the the um
surpluses in the uh in the other
countries that uh uh and which were then
in invested in US government bonds and
that was uh sort of at the root root of
the great moderation that preceded the
storm that's what I mean MH so you're
saying the stimulus it would be better
if more stimulus were applied in other
countries in the in the exporting
countries and the in the Surplus
countries yes and then particularly in
the developing world and as you know I'm
advocating uh the re the use of the
special drawing rights uh for the
developing world but that would take us
too far here do we have another question
from
MIT hi my name is Fernando DTE and I am
a PhD candidate at MIT and my question
is in terms of predictability of returns
what are the different
implications between the efficient
markets hypothesis and
reflexivity the what in terms of the pr
predictability of the crisis and of the
cycle uh where were the where were the
specific different points between an
efficient market analysis and the
reflexivity analysis which in a sense
would allow you to see you know which
analysis was empirically better well you
know I'm not qualified to to criticize
the efficient market hypothesis and the
rational expectations Theory directly
because I'm not familiar with it the
fact that I
was uh able to make a living for last 50
years without being familiar with it is
a comment on the value of that uh of
those however um uh I I can tell you
that my uh interpretation of bubbles
expressly doeses not claim to be able to
tell whether a test will be successful
or not and from personal experience I
thought the Super Bubble was big enough
in
98 that it would lead to a collapse of
the financial system and I was wrong so
I do not claim to be able to predict uh
the future and I expressly claim the
opposite however I think that with that
theory it is possible to anticipate
events to uh create uh scenarios and
hypotheses that you can then test
against the actual course of events and
that is in fact what I have been doing
for the last uh 50 years as a market
participants a participant whenever I
could I formulated a hypothesis uh with
regard to a particular stock or the
market or an
industry um and then I tested it against
events and when events uh evolve
differently I reassessed it uh so I
think this and this is a very paparian
approach and that's why I'm a great
admirer of of Papa's uh uh theory of
scientific method uh even though he
doesn't apply the way he he he wants it
to uh to social phena uh because of this
Reliance on conjectures and
reputations uh and it it's been a very
very rewarding process as far as I'm
concerned well well let me press you a
little bit further on that uh to give a
specific example if we look at this
latest crisis and I think this was
really the question that was being asked
if we look at this latest crisis uh
could you describe for us at what point
you began to uh develop if you like
these hypoth a hypothesis suggesting to
you that we may be moving
into into a climax of a a major bubble
or perhaps even the Super Bubble and you
know what were some of the events that
led you either to confirm or uh draw
back from that
hypothesis that we may be that was clear
to me obviously for many years and and I
in in my my previous book in
2006 I spelled it out and I identified
actually uh the the subp and the housing
U Market as the locus from which the the
uh crisis would come so that was and I
was not the only one who who did that uh
so it was visible but when it would come
was could not be determined and frankly
I and many others who expected it to
happen expected it to happen at least a
year earlier uh then it really started
to hit uh in the early part of uh of uh
2007 and in August two and I I wrote
about it uh then and published it that
was the new paradigm uh which I wrote
actually at Christmas
2006 um um published in in in April um
and then in August I saw that this the
crisis has really
arrived and I came out of retirement and
took over the management of my fund uh
in order to uh protect my my um estate
um which I did in in August so from
August uh 2007 it was pretty clear to
you that this was going to be a major
the major uh financial crisis not just
another minor bubble of the kind that
we've seen over the last 20 years yes
but to for for the order of
uh being being truthful I did not
anticipate that Leeman brothers would be
allowed to fail I I saw the crisis as
being the turning point but I did not
anticipate that the authorities would
fail to rescue Leman brothers and I
think that was a gamechanging event do
you think I'm sorry to take the time of
of our friends at MIT but on on that
point of Leman Brothers do you think the
authorities had any real
alternative I I think they did although
they would say that they did not have
the powers uh of resolution to intervene
but in actual fact Whenever there is a
crisis and the authorities recognize it
that recognize it as such they took
measures or in historically which could
not be justified by the then prevailing
rules so they always uh used a large
degree of discretion and they could have
done it had
they been determined to do so another
question from
MIT this is Ricardo cavero head of the
economics Department of MIT good
afternoon Mr Soros um you mentioned the
the need to control credit uh in order
to regulate asset Bubbles and you
mentioned the example of China um but
the big difference between China and the
US is the type of financial markets they
have and we have in in China it's mostly
Bank Med credit most mostly Bank
mediated the same is true in Continental
Europe but in the US Banks play a very
small role so what do you do in a more
complex Financial market like the US in
order to control credit when asset
bubble is
developing I I I'm I'm sorry Professor
cabalero the the the sound transmission
was not very clear I think I understood
the question but uh come back if I've
misinterpreted uh I think the question
was that uh you mentioned that there's
going to be a need to control credit as
well as use monetary policy to regulate
Bubbles and you gave China as an example
of the successful control of credit uh I
think the question was that in China
it's possible to control credit because
they have uh a dominant banking system
and almost no credit markets and indeed
the the banking system is largely State
controlled if you if you have a system
like the US which is largely a credit
market securitized system is there any
feasible way of actually exercising
control over credit I think that was the
question yes I think there is and in
fact that control was being exercised as
I've mentioned in my lecture when I
started in business banking system was
extremely closely controlled and I I've
actually witnessed and participated in
the gradual decontrol
of the finance of the banking system in
1972 I wrote
a paper uh entitled the case for for
growth Banks because I said that an
industry that was totally dormant and
the people uh working in it were not
motivated by profit motive but were more
like more like government and employees
H there was a new group of banks
actually very much under the leadership
of Walter wristen of City Bank um and
they fanned out from City Bank and and
they actually wanted to do banking for
profit and uh and I said this could be
very rewarding uh for investment and in
fact it was uh and then in
73 it came the the oil crisis and the
large um surpluses that the oil
producing countries uh um uh received
which were then rechanneled through the
commercial Banks and that's when the
London Market the euro dollar market
suddenly came to life and gradually U
the very strict controls on on State
banking were were overcome by setting up
a London subsidiary that was exempt and
that then eventually led to the
financial crisis of 82 and so on so it
it is a historic process and I actually
have lived through the entire history
but is it possible now that the genie
has been let out of the bottle now that
you have a credit market system as
opposed to or a capital market system of
credit rather than a banking system of
credit in the US can you control credit
when it's supplied by the capital
markets well o o obviously you can't
control it as if if it were uh uh within
the banking system and actually what
happened was in
1982 as you recall because that's when
we first started discussing these issues
uh um the banks were forced by by the
central banks to renew roll over the
credits in order to prevent a collapse
and they didn't like it and that's
actually when they started securitizing
their loans uh so that they couldn't be
caught by the central banks in case of
need and then in
97 most of the Sovereign uh bonds had
been securitized and therefore actually
except in the case of Kore
South Korea uh the the banks could not
be uh forced to roll over the the loans
and that's why the brunt of the burden
was carried by the countries concerned
uh so uh it is more difficult if you
don't have it in the banking system but
I think that the measures that I
proposed and I think they need to be
further elaborated and and and refined
uh could actually
give you that kind of the control that
you that you need should we have one
more question from MIT and then we'll go
to the floor here and why don't we maybe
take take hang around unless there's
somebody dying at MIT we we'll have some
question I think there's someone about
to ask a question okay yeah last
question good afternoon Mr sorus I have
a question uh I'm a second year student
at MIT SLO and I want to carry on a
point about China
it's
on good afternoon Mr s I'm a second year
SL student to carry on with the point of
China it is able to control Capital
inflows due to its dominant economic
position in the
world how about a middle developing
country how does it do likewise one
example I think of is Malaysia which
closed up its its capital inflow borders
after 1998 crisis how does a developing
country like that
stand withstand International Capital
inflows uh I think the the question is
again uh apologies but it didn't come
through very clearly but uh I think the
question was about Capital controls and
the disruptive inflows and outflows of
capital uh China has Capital controls
even despite the fact that it's an
overwhelming now an overwhelmingly
powerful economy uh I think the question
was how how can other developing
countries other emerging economies uh
which are smaller and potentially more
vulnerable how should they cope with the
uh problem or the threat of disruptive
Capital flows yeah well it is much
easier to control Capital flows when
they are coming in than it is when
they're going out uh and you can see
that Brazil just imposed a
2% tax tax on all new Financial Capital
coming into Brazil in order to slow down
the inflow now that's a bit cruder than
the more sophisticated method that Chile
uh applies which uh apportions the the
uh the tax to the length of time that
the capital is is is committed uh uh but
and probably it will not slow it will
slow the inflow but probably will not uh
uh stop it uh but clearly there is a
greater role for Capital controls then
the Washington consensus recognized uh
prior uh to the the crisis now China has
actually
uh discovered a fabulous
machine uh for
mobilizing the creative and and
acquisitive uh energies of the people
and and yet uh uh creaming off a
significant portion of their
productivity for the benefit of the
state by tying the rembi to the dollar
and and effectively ensuring that the
Remi is
undervalued so that China has built up
the the amount of money that has been
creamed off without people feeling any
pain uh can be measured it's $2.3
trillion dollar and still
growing very good answer should we have
some questions here maybe we come back
to the yeah we we may come back uh if
there's time uh there's a question there
in the middle let's start with
that um hi yes um my name is Zan Gluk I
uh studied philosophy at Bard and now
I'm at the sociology Department here at
CU um I have two related questions I'll
try and make them brief um about the
nature of capitalism um one of them is
about economic theory and the other one
could I could say about uh Phil
philanthropy
practice um it seems that what you're
proposing here is a uh a theory of
crisis of sorts uh of financial capital
and I wanted to ask about um a broader
field of economic theory um crisis
Theory more generally and related to a
point brought up by Joseph stiglet in
his um lecture last week at CU um namely
that the postwar period we saw a 15
years of uh relative stability where
there were no um crises of capitalism
and that was a bit of an anomaly within
the history of capitalism I was
wondering how your uh Theory would apply
more broadly historically to say the
early capitalist crisis of the 19th
century
um and secondly just don't go second
because I missed the key key words so I
couldn't understand the question uh the
the the question is uh you have theory
of crisis of capitalism of financial
crisis uh can you relate it not just to
the crisis of the last 20 or 30 years uh
but going further back into into history
into the history of 19th century of
capitalism uh does your theory in some
sense still apply yeah yes the the big
difference that in the 19th century ever
since You' have had Financial PR uh uh
markets you have had financial crisis uh
in fact even when you only had two lip
markets you had financial crisis but but
each time there was a crisis there was
an attempt to understand what went wrong
and to uh bring some regulatory reform
and as I read the history of the 19th
century there were all kinds of
commissions in England examining after
each financial crisis what went wrong
and a step further was taken to build up
Central Banking and in the 20th century
uh after the after 19 29 uh you started
with the regulation of uh uh stock
markets uh so uh crisis were followed by
reforms whereas starting in 1980 because
of predominance of Market
fundamentalism uh crisis were followed
by
deregulation partly actually for very
practical reasons because in 19 after
1982 the banks also had to earn their
way out of the hole and it took them
about three to five years to do it
before eventually uh the uh Emerging
Market debt was reorganized into Brady
bonds uh so there was a practical reason
for doing it but there was also this
this um uh uh let's say ideological
reason and don't forget that glass
deagle was abolished only a few years
ago and and and uh short selling on the
stock exchange was the was abolished
only just in time uh for
bares yes there was a qu I think I had
the second question do you want to
briefly the second question very very
brief um uh it's it's related um and
perhaps could be related also to this
new economic Institute you're talking
about so about philanthropic
philanthropic practice um whether uh
philanthropy in your opinion um changes
the nature of capitalism um that is to
say um some critics have said that um
philanthropy sometimes acts as a
Band-Aid as what you've said is a
fundamentally broken system um and I was
wondering what you see the role of
philanthropy as whether or not it can
affect a deep structural change within
capitalism or whether you see it as some
type of a transition to uh a different
type of uh systemic solution to some of
the problems we've been
experiencing yes I I I do think and I
will deal with that issue uh uh
particularly in in the in the last
lecture uh where I deal with the
international aspects uh because uh
there U the system was supposed to to uh
to be uh a sort of a a Level Playing
Field but of but in fact the playing the
playing field was not level and and the
the center particularly the United
States was more equal than
others uh and and that brought about
certain imbalances which were very much
an element in the Super Bubble which I
didn't have time today to deal with but
I will uh deal with it in my fifth and
my last
lecture let question there and then one
there and then one no no no we'll have
this one and then you uh my name is
Peter Mi am from the economics
Department of the CU and in light of
your last words might be uh my question
is a little bit premature uh because you
uh promised what to speak uh later on uh
but I saw an interesting contrast
between your lecture and the the
subjects and the questions of the after
of the discussion after that people were
asking you about China in Malaysia and
other things so the international aspect
uh can we formulate the problem in uh in
in this language because what you
presented was basically a a uh a a
crisis uh
recurring according to the rules of the
international financial markets
according to the rule of the American
markets but maybe actually and in in the
last uh event it is certainly the case
that uh the the bubble was created by
real
differences on the globe uh the
difference where China is relative to
United States difference where India is
relative to United States so so it's not
uh a a rule problem it's it's a
complexity of the world it's
globalization where countries having
really different situations uh play the
game on the international context and
because of the uh communication these
things go very very fast uh don't you
think that uh these are probably as
important element of the story the real
differences and just uh a quick
reference to to the consequences I think
it was two days ago where uh Krugman in
the New York Times was talking about the
the Chinese currency problem very much
in the context as you do uh and then he
said China was stealing jobs from
elsewhere now this is real thing this is
not speculation and we cannot blame I
think from here or from anywhere else
that the Chinese government is pursuing
such a policy it's not speculation it's
not stupidity it's their interest
um yes there is obviously an
international aspect to it but let's
face it this particular crisis in 20072
2008 it originated at the center you see
and and therefore for this particular
phase of the crisis that issue is not
Central that's why I didn't deal with it
today I will deal with it uh fifth uh
lecture uh but if it is a very
definitely and I think that the
International System has to be rebuilt
uh I will I I don't want to go into my
fifth lecture now so bear with me until
then now there's a question over there
now there's a Forest of Hands going up
lots of people want to ask questions so
can we keep the questions question and I
would like to ask don't you think that
uh Regulators will be forced to ease
regulations at times of growth and this
is just a part of uh natural cycle that
regulations happen after such a crisis
and then as Market grow Regulators are
forced by politial political pressure to
ease uh Market regulations that
contribute later to the question is that
uh once the crisis subsides actually
Regulators will be forced to ease
regulation by political pressures uh so
even if there is a slight increase in
regulation in the immediate response to
the crisis
uh an easing in the long run is likely
well there already
is a desire to uh uh uh forget about
regulations because the the the the the
uh institutions that survived actually
their uh Market position has been
greatly strengthened and and therefore
they certainly tried to protect it with
all they have got and they've got plenty
so uh uh you will have a serious
issue uh and uh I just hope that we will
not forget uh about the reforms that are
needed uh because uh I I think that the
system has been very seriously weakened
and if you you put Humpty Dumpty
together again it will not
last uh question over there
and maybe another one after thank you
good afternoon Mr
shash writers Al also PhD candidate
myself actually can you slow down it's
hard to answer so THS and writers um and
PhD candidate bnab Edge my question
would relate mainly to the last question
of MIT emerging markets and Bubbles um
are you not concerned that actually a
new uh bubble is uh formulating in the
Emerging Markets let's say with the
words of yours um fed by the positive
feedbacks of the increasing commodity
prices um the belief that these
countries has a greater potential and
the carry trade operations yeah thank
you the question was about Emerging
Markets don't you think that a new
bubble is is is coming along in Emerging
Markets fueled by misconceptions like
commodity prices will go up forever
these these countries have far better
prospects you know the the rise of China
and so on I don't think that everything
is a bubble and I do think that that um
uh this financial crisis which
originated at the center has hurt the
center much more than the than the
periphery and and uh uh I I do expect
the Emerging Markets to do significantly
better uh than than uh than the United
States
economy there was a question
there good afternoon Peter
grumberg do you think there's scope for
applying some aspects of sharia law or
ethical banking uh particularly with uh
reference to provision of credit and
debt
Finance sh law Sharia
banking Islamic banking I I don't know
much about it I'm sorry or ethical
banking is is is there an ethical
Dimension to banking that that could be
somehow brought back would that be a way
of controlling the banks by telling them
to be more virtuous yeah no look I'm a
great promoter of ethical values but I
don't see the application in this in
this context and I I the impression that
I have but I really don't take this as a
Ser well considered opinion
that the Islamic banking kind of
reconciles the Islamic rules with
banking through subterfuge where using
some other techniques
to find a
compromise uh there's a couple questions
here in the middle and then one there
thank you
um I'm L leasi from City Bank and amcham
so I'm one of those hated
Bankers um I just wanted to ask how why
is it in your opinion uh Dr shes that so
little analysis is being done about the
culpability of
interventions like The Fanny May and
Freddy ma to enable some of these things
to to proceed this is probably the only
time when the people who didn't pay back
the money are the good guys and the ones
that didn't get it back are the bad guys
and uh I might be biased obviously in
that the question is and and the
gentleman works for City Bank so take
that into account uh the question is uh
why has so little analysis been done of
the culpability of government
intervention in in creating this crisis
and the main example being Fanny May and
Freddy Mack you know they were supported
by the government uh they encouraged
lending to subprime borrowers and so on
and this is the first crisis in which
the people who didn't pay back the debt
don't seem to um bear any moral
responsibility but actually I certainly
am un record uh uh blaming The
Regulators for failing to regulate I
mean that was perhaps the the major
failure that doesn't exempt the banks
but it certainly
uh uh uh Regulators were as much at
fault in in in in uh uh uh failing to
perform their duties as the banks were
in in exceeding their U mandate but if
if I could I I'd like to press you a bit
on this because actually the this is a
point of view that's presented a lot in
the Wall Street Journal by the
Republican Party in the US that actually
this whole crisis was caused by the fact
that markets were not free enough it was
the fact that governments intervened in
markets subsidized uh Home Loans to uh
you know poor households who wouldn't re
couldn't repay that actually caused the
crisis what's your reaction to that
argument it I think it's it's it's very
simple if you didn't have regulations
you Pro you wouldn't have sophisticated
financial markets because they would
have collapsed long ago I mean they
didn't collapse in '98
when there was plenty of reason for it
to to collapse because The Regulators
intervened successfully so uh to to to
argue that if you had no
regulations uh you would have no
crises I would say you also would have
no financial
markets okay
uh good afternoon Mr shos I'm Stuart
Durrant managing director of the ceu
business school and I'd like to pick up
on the issue which you raised of hidden
subsidies in Banks uh reported in the
times yesterday I think no surprise
there
um you make the point that the banks are
currently taking advantage of a window
of opportunity able to earn their way
out of a Hole by borrowing very cheaply
and investing in government bonds at 3
three and a half% or something what has
made is possible was to a large extent
the implementation of the quantitative
easing programs and at least the way it
was presented to me was that these
programs were introduced in order to
make government bonds less attractive to
Banks and to promote the spread of
credit into the economy is QE a failure
or do we need to try harder uh the
question is well in a nut show it's
whether quantitative easing is a failure
or is it responsible for this this this
hidden subsidy yeah no no but what the
question is the question was that the
the reason for this subsidy to Banks is
that there's been all this quantitative
easing keeping short rates at zero of
course that's given the subsidy to Banks
does that mean the quantitative easing
was actually a mistake no no I I think
that that uh it was absolutely necessary
uh to prevent a collapse uh so the
authorities did the right thing uh
with quantitative easing in my opinion
the mistake they made was not to
recapitalize banks on a compulsory basis
uh uh but to
inject uh these hidden subsidies to
allow them to earn their way out of the
hole the the injection should have been
at the level of the capital not at the
level of the balance sheet and uh the
700 billion uh of tarp uh money the
originally voted would have been in my
opinion enough to underwrite the
recapitalization of of of the banks uh
in other words uh the Scandinavian
approach would have been more effective
than the Japanese approach because we
basically gone the Japanese route and as
you know know after 18 years Japan is
still not out of the woods but even if
you did did recapitalize them if you
give the banks money at 0%
interest what is to stop them why
shouldn't they invest it in government
Bots at 3 and a half% and make these
large profits yeah aren't you inevitably
providing them with a subsidy well and
and and if the banks didn't uh invest at
3 and a half% interest rate would not be
3 and a half per but much higher so uh
that's a that's part of the mechanism of
quantitative easing basically uh the the
point is that if you recapitalize the
banks if you separated the old bank from
the new bank and injected Capital into a
new bank and allowed the old bank to run
off its portfolio there would have be
new Banks which are flush with deposits
and capital looking
for
suitable investment opportunity or
lending and therefore lending to the
private sector they would have been much
more ready to lend and to take risk okay
uh thank you uh Charles Kovac ex-banker
in any case uh while we're on the
subject of the interest rates uh I just
like to note that uh the 0% interest
rate was not necessarily charged by the
government for the money given to the
banks but that is the short-term
interest rate effectively paid to
Consumers uh in the United States and
that means that the demand dep deposits
of the banks have become very cheap this
goes a long way forward a lot more than
just the uh monies that the governments
have has in have invested um on the
other hand uh don't you think that the
lower interest rates which affect the
entire economy are also driven by the
general recession which seems to be
taking place in in the states it's not
necessarily just Bank driven yeah OB
obviously the fact that there is no
private demand keeps interest rates
lower than they would than it would
would be otherwise that's no question
could I ask you do you believe that that
the bond market is in potentially a
bubble you know you say we must look for
Bubble every but do you think that Bond
long-term Bond bonds at 3 and a half%
given what's happening with the fiscal
deficits all over the world that that
this is also a dangerously unsustainable
situ situation uh I think that that
right now you're still in a deflationary
environment although the economy is
recovering and and as soon as it starts
recovering uh um and you can you and the
if the
authorities don't manage it extremely
skillfully uh the financial markets are
going to get nervous about the prospect
of the
inflation and that would then push up
interest rates and choke off uh the
recovery and that in a way is
reminiscent of what happened in the'
70s uh where you had stop go uh and and
I think we we will be in a period of
prolonged uh stagflation if you like or
or or or uh or fears of stagflation yeah
uh but I think the the the the the
financial markets themselves will
prevent inflation from getting out of
hand there was a lady there at back
hello my name is Lila stria I'm a
registered auditor at business
adviser uh I my question is about a
book that was published uh in early 2009
by Harry
Dent uh this is a a an economist who was
successful in predicting uh the major
Bubbles and crisises that you were uh
talking about and in this book he says
that uh apart from quoting you that this
is the the end of an era
uh it describes quite a gloomy picture
uh of the next few years even decade um
he says that uh the Next Great
Depression will be from 2008 to Lasting
to
2023 with the worst part start uh
starting late 2009 making the Dow Jones
falling to 3,800 points which will not
recover until
2017 so would you like to reflect on
this thank thank you yes I I don't know
who it is I haven't heard the name but I
can disagree with it because on
principle because I don't think that the
future is predictable the way he's
predicting it I mean my whole theory is
that that uh uh financial markets evolve
in a historic process and history is
essentially unpredictable because it
will depend on decisions that have not
yet been taken so how can they be
predicted yes the lady over
there my name is Christina and I teach
Finance at CU Business School uh Mr shos
my question is you mentioned the
conglomerate mergers in the 1960s as a
contributor uh to the Bubba my question
is whether the recent mer the recent the
merger wave that started in the 1980s
with the Strategic mergers of large
companies has been
contributing uh to uh the financial
crisis on a longer term level by
creating large players in the market for
which lenders like to lend too thank you
the question was you you said that in
the 1960s the conglomerate Boom the merg
Mania created a bubble do you think a
similar a second round of merg mania
from the 1980s onward which created
bigger and bigger companies uh which
wanted to deal with bigger and bigger
lenders was also a a contributor to to
this latest
bubble a minor contributor I would I I
would say that it was not a central
element in in in in the Super Bubble
there was this uh and and obviously uh
the concentration of the financial
system is much more disturbing in that
respect than con the concentration in
the um uh the um uh normal
industry except I would say the media
but that's a different story because oh
tell us about the media no no it has to
do with the it has to do with democracy
uh we're we just we want to see if if
are there one or two more questions from
MIT okay I are there can we communicate
with
MIT tell them we will come back to them
uh we we'll come back uh We've we've got
about five minutes left so maybe there's
time for one or two questions from MIT
after we've had another question from
here yes sir in Middle there just a
moment the
microphone M wolitzky I'm not a
financial expert I'm just a doctor and a
taxpayer and my question is has anything
what we have heard today to do with a
taxpayer the bailout has definitely
something to do with a taxpayer and is
there a danger that at some point the
taxpayers don't want to support this
virtual system on top of them yes
obviously the tax players are an
important player players in this in this
and they are politically uh uh objecting
to the higher taxes uh that are implicit
in the runup of the of the U uh national
debt uh but you have to bear in mind
that there would be a an alternative
cost if you did not stimulate the
economy because and and you you really
have to look at the national debt a a as
as a percentage of the gross national
product so if the gross national product
Falls uh you can be in a debt
trap uh that would be much worse than
than than the stimulus so it's it's
something it's a question of the Lesser
evil that you have to consider right do
we have a question from
MIT no I I I I I think I think we we we
can't we can't get through to that uh
one more question then from the floor
here
Jay fogelman from The ceu Business
School faculty Mr Shor as to pursue an
earlier question uh you uh indicated yes
that the the uh Financial system and the
crisis that we're experiencing certainly
has an international Dimension uh that's
related to to globalization but I'm
wondering more specifically whether
changes in information technology and
Communications technology the internet
but much more than that
has erased Geographic and cultural
barriers and changed the speed of
communication and has provided a glut of
information much of it highly failable
has this changed the function of of
markets just in in quantitatively or is
it a difference in kind no it certainly
is also an element that has to be taken
into account it's not an essential
ingredient for say
explaining what is going on but it is a
contributing factor and uh and uh the
element of time is
extremely important particularly at
times of Crisis where you just simply
don't have the time
to gather all the information that would
be available if you had the time to
collect it and that applies to Market
participants and I can talk from
personal experience and and also of
course to the regulators and that is
responsible for the increased liquidity
preference that canes uh uh uh recognize
and is a contributing factor in the
severity or bringing on uh the crisis
and when you look at the incredible
increase in
volatility uh that had to do partly with
the increased speed of
communications uh but mainly with the
much increased range of of of
uncertainty that that uh pervaded uh the
market the fear of the
unknown this is going to be the last
question there's a gentleman there at
the end
good afternoon thank you very much for
coming my question would be don't you
think the biggest problem of this crisis
is is judging the the crisis so we talk
about regulation but the first step
would be judging and as um Mr said this
is international pretty much
International crisis so the whole
judging would be International who is
the one who's the one in charge and and
how what do you think about the first
step because you say it's a huge crisis
other people say it's not that
huge uh the question is and I think it's
a very good one to to round it off with
that uh the biggest problem of a crisis
like this is judging how serious it is
who should be in charge if it's an an
international crisis with International
Dimensions is there an authority there
who is in charge is there an authority
that is able to assess how serious it is
because some people say this is the
worst crisis in human history others say
well it's already over it what so how
can you be confident that there is a
regulator out there who can deal or a
set of regulators out there who can deal
with crisis actually you don't have a
regulator out there and that is the
challenge that confronts us because you
financial markets have been globalized
but globalization was based on a false
principle that markets don't need to be
regulated therefore globalization and
deregulation went together and you can
deregulate uh in a in a way that forces
the the
recit countries to join the
deregulation
because deregulation puts capital in a
position that it can move around freely
and it can escape Taxation and
Regulation and therefore it will go
where it is deregulated and since
capital is in indispensable for for the
economy countries had to compete in
deregulating but when it comes to
regulating it doesn't work the same way
because the regulation at which is in
existence is all based on the principle
of sovereignty
and different nations have different
interests
therefore they they will
regulate according to their their
interests and that actually puts into
place a very strong force for the
disintegration of global markets through
National
regulation and that and since a
multi lateral system is more efficient
than
a bilateral system uh of
regulations uh the challenge is how to
create something which currently doesn't
exist so it's not a question of
restarting the economy it's a question
of building a regulatory structure that
was not created when markets were
globalized
well this is an exciting and and could
go on much longer but I do want to thank
U our very Lively questioners and
audience at MIT and our equally Lively
audience and highly interactive audience
here at uh central European
University um we will continue this
journey
tomorrow when Mr Soros will outline his
concept of open society which is in many
ways the heart of what central European
University is all about I'm very
grateful to ANL kety for so expertly
guiding today's
discussion and of course and above all
to thank George Soros for continuing to
stimulate Us in this extraordinary
series of ceu lectures thank you