[Applause]
thank you very much and thank you for
coming and also I want to greet the
students at
MIT uh today I'll apply the concepts
introduced yes yesterday
fallibility reflexivity and the human
uncertainty principle
in into the financial markets please
brace yourselves because I'll pack a
lifetime of experience into this one
lecture the financial markets provide an
excellent laboratory for testing the
ideas that I put forward in an abstract
form yesterday the course of events is
easier to observe than in most other
places many of the facts take a
quantitative form and the data are well
recorded and well
preserved the opportunity for testing
occurs because my interpretation of
financial markets directly contradicts
the efficient market hypothesis which
has been the prevailing Theory uh about
financial
markets that theory claims that markets
tend towards equilibrium deviations
occur in a random fashion and can be
attributed to extraneous shocks if that
theory is valid mine is false and vice
versa let me State the two Cardinal
principles of my conceptual framework as
it applies to the financial markets
first market prices always distort the
underlying fundamental
the degree of distortions may vary from
the negligible to the significant this
is in direct contradiction to the
efficient market hypothesis which
maintains that market prices accurately
reflect all the available
information second instead of playing a
purely passive role in reflecting an
underlying reality financial markets
also have an active role
they can affect the so-called
fundamentals that they are supposed to
reflect there are various Pathways by
which the mispricing of financial assets
can occur the most widely traveled are
those which involve the use of Leverage
both debt and Equity
leveraging the various feedback loops
may give the impression that markets are
are often right but the mechanism at
work is very different from the one
proposed by the prevailing
Paradigm I claim that financial markets
have ways of altering the fundamentals
and that may bring about a closer
correspondence between market prices and
the underlying fundamentals contrast
that with the efficient market
hypothesis which claims that markets are
always accurately reflecting reality and
automatically tend towards
equilibrium my two propositions Focus
attention on the reflexive feedback
loops that characterize financial
markets there are two kinds of feedback
negative and positive negative feedback
is
self-correcting positive feedback is
self-reinforcing
thus negative feedback sets up a
tendency towards equilibrium while
positive feedback produces Dynamic
disequilibrium positive feedback loops
are more interesting because they they
can bring about big moves both in market
prices and in the underlying
fundamentals a positive feedback process
that runs its full course is initially
self-reinforcing but eventually it is
liable to reach a climax or reversal
point after which it becomes
self-reinforcing in the opposite
direction but positive feedback
processes don't necessarily run their
full course they may be aborted at any
time by negative
feedback I have developed a theory of
about boom bus processes or bubbles
along these
lines every bubble has two components an
underlying Trend that prevails in
reality and a misconception relating to
that Trend a boomas process is set in
motion when a trend and a misconception
positively reinforce each other the
process is liable to be tested by
negative feedback along on the way if
the trend is strong enough to survive
the test both the trend and the
misconception will be first further
reinforced eventually Market
expectations become so far removed from
reality that people are forced to
recognize that the misconception is
involved a Twilight period ensues during
which doubts grow and more people lose
Faith but the prevailing trend is
sustained by
inertia as Chuck Prince former head of
citybook group said we must continue
dancing until the Music
Stops eventually a point is reached when
the trend is reversed it then becomes
self-reinforcing in the opposite uh
Direction let me go back to the example
I used when I or originally proposed my
theory in
1987 the conglomerate boom of the late
1960s the underlying trend is
represented by earnings per share the
expectations relating to to that uh
Trend by stock
prices so here you have the the earnings
per share and the stock
prices conglomerates improved their
share their earnings per share by
acquiring other
companies inflated expectations allowed
them to improve their earnings
performance but
eventually
reality could not keep up with
expectations after a Twilight period the
price trend was reversed all the
problems that had been swept under the
carpet surfaced and earnings collapsed
as the president of one of the
conglomerates ogan corporation told me
at the time I have no audience to play
to this this is a model of um of uh the
conglomerate bubble the the the
charts of actual conglomerates like ogan
Corporation closely resemble uh this
chart bubbles uh uh that conform to this
pattern go through distinct
stages uh there is the
Inception then a period of
acceleration um reinforced by uh okay by
successful tests when the price de lines
but the it's still the trend reinforces
is strong enough to reinforce itself
then a Twilight period ensues uh um and
a reversal point or climax is reached
followed by an acceleration on the the
downside cating in a financial
crisis the length and strength strength
of each stage is unpredictable but there
is an internal logic in the sequence of
stages so the sequence is predictable
but even that can be terminated by
government intervention or some other
form of negative feedback in the case of
the conglomerate boom it was the defeat
of lisco in its attempt to acquire
manufacturers Handover trust that
constituted the climers climax or
reversal
Point
typically bubbles have an asymmetric
shape the Boom is long and and drawn out
slow to start it accelerates gradually
until it flattens out during the
Twilight period the bust is short and
steep because it's rainforce by the
forced liquidation of unsound
positions disillusionment turn turns
into Panic reaching its climax in a
financial
crisis the simplest case is a real
estate Boom the trend that precipitates
it is that credit becomes cheaper and
more easily available the misconception
is that the value of the collateral is
independent of the availability of
credit as a matter of fact the
relationship between the availability of
credit and the value of the collateral
is
reflexive when credit becomes cheaper
and more easily available activity picks
up and real estate values rise there are
fewer defaults credit performance
improves and lending standards are
relaxed so at the height of the Boom the
amount of credit involved is at its
maximum and a reversal precipitates
forcely liquidation depressing real
estate
prices yet this
misconception continues to ur in various
guises for instance the international
banking crisis of
1982 revolved around sovereign debt
where no collateral is involved the
credit worthiness of the S Sovereign
borrowers was measured by various debt
ratios like debt to GDP and that service
to exports these ratios were considered
objective criteria while in fact they
were
reflexive when the re recycling of Petr
dollars in the
1970s increased the flow of credit to
countries like Brazil their debt ratios
improved encouraging further inflows and
starting a
pple not all bubbles involve the
extension of credit some are based on
Equity
leveraging the best examples are the
conglomerate boom of the
1960s and the internet bubble of the
late
1990s When Alan Greenspan spoke about
irrational exuberance in
1996 it misrepresented bubbles when I
see a bubble for in are rushing to buy
adding fuel to the fire that's not
irrational and that's why we need
Regulators to counteract the market when
a bubble is threatening to grow too big
because we can't rely on Market
participants however well informed and
rational they
are bubbles are not the only form in
which reflectivity manifests itself the
they are only the most dramatic and the
most directly opposed to the efficient
market hypothesis therefore they deserve
special
attention but reflexivity can take many
other forms in currency markets for
instance the upside and downside are
symetrical so that there is no sign of
an asymmetry between boom and bust but
there is no sign of equilibrium either
freely floating exchange rates tend to
move in large multi-year
waves and the most important and most
interesting reflexive interaction takes
place between the financial authorities
and financial markets because markets
don't tend toward equilibrium they are
prone to produce periodic crisis
Financial crises lead to regulatory
reforms that's how Central Banking and
the regulation of financial markets have
evolved both the financial authorities
and Market participants act on the basis
of imperfect understanding and that
makes the interaction between them
reflexive and
unpredictable while bubbles only occur
intermittently
the interplay between authorities and
markets is an ongoing process
misunderstandings by either side usually
stay within reasonable bounds because
Market reactions provide useful feedback
for to the authorities allowing them to
correct their mistakes but occasionally
the mistakes prove to be self validating
send setting in motion we should or
virtuous circles such feedback loops
resemble bubbles in the sense that they
are initially self-reinforcing but
eventually uh self-defeating but
otherwise they take quite a different
shape it's important to realize that not
all price distortions are due to
reflexivity Market participants can't
possibly base their decisions on
knowledge they they have to anticipate
the future and the future is contingent
on the decisions that people have not
yet made what makes what those decisions
are going to be and what effect they
will have can't be accurately
anticipated nevertheless people are
forced to make decisions to guess
correctly people would have to know the
decisions of all of the other
participants and their consequence
quences but that's
impossible rational expectations Theory
sought to circumvent this
impossibility by postulating that there
is a single correct set of expectations
and people's views will converge around
it that postulate has no resemblance to
reality but it is the basis of financial
economics as it's currently taught at in
universities in practice participants
are obliged to make their decisions in
conditions of
uncertainty their decisions are bound to
be tentative and biased that's the
general generic cause of price
distortions occasionally the price
distortions set in motion a boomas
process more often they are corrected by
negative feedack back in these cases
Market fluctuations have a random
character I compare them to the waves
sloshing around in a swimming pool as
opposed to a tidal wave obviously the L
the latter are more significant but the
former are more
ubiquitous the two kinds of price
distortions intermingle so that in
reality boomas processes rarely follow
follow the exact course of my model
bubbles that follow the pattern I
described in my model occur only in
those rare occasions when they are so
powerful that they overshadow all the
other processes going on at the same
time it will be useful to distinguish
between near
equilibrium uh and far from equilibrium
conditions the near equilibrium
conditions are characterized by random
fluctuations and the far from
equilibrium situations
uh uh are those in which a bubble uh
predominates near equilibrium is
characterized by hrum everyday events
which are repetitive and lend themselves
to statistic
generalizations far from equilibrium
conditions give rise to Unique
historical events where outcomes are
generally uncertain but have the
capacity to disrupt the statistical
gener generalizations based on everyday
events the rules that can guide
decisions in near equilibrium conditions
don't apply in far from equ ium
situations the recent financial crisis
is a case in point all the risk
management tools and synthetic Financial
products that were based on the
assumption that price
deviations from a put putative
equilibrium occur in a random fashion
broke down and people who relied on
mathematical models which had served
them well in near equilibrium conditions
got badly
hurt I have gained some new insights
into far from equilibrium conditions
during the recent financial
crisis as a participant I had to act
under immense time pressure and I
couldn't gather all the information that
would have been
available and the same applied to the
regulatory authorities in charge that's
how far from equilibrium situations can
spin out of
control and this is not confined to
financial markets I experienced it for
instance during the collapse of the
Soviet Union the fact that the
participants thinking is time bound
instead of Timeless is left out of
account by rational expectations Theory
I was aware of the uncertainty
associated with reflexivity but even I
was taken in by I was taken by surprise
by the extent of the uncertainty in 2008
it cost me dearly I got the general
direction of the markets right but I
didn't allow for the
volatility as a consequence I took on
positions that were too big to withstand
the swings caused by volatility and
several times I was forced to reduce my
positions at the wrong time in order to
limit my risk I would have done much
better if I had taken smaller positions
and stuck with them I learned a hard way
that the range of uncertainty is also
uncertain and at times it can become
practically
infinite uncertainty
finds expression in
volatility increased volatility requires
a reduction in RIS risk exposure this
leads to what canes called increased
liquidity
preference this is an additional factor
in the forc liquidation of positions
that characterize financial
crisis when the crisis abates and the
rain of uncertainty is reduced it leads
to an almost automatic Rebound in the
stock market as the liquidity preference
stops rising and eventually
Falls that's another lesson uh that I
have learned
recently I also need to point out that
the distinction between near and
equilibrium and near and far from
equilibrium conditions uh uh that uh uh
that I've mentioned was introduced by me
while trying to make some sense out of a
confusing reality and it doesn't
accurately reflect reality reality is
always more complicated than the
dichotomies we introduce into it the
recent crisis is comparable to a 100e
storm we have had a number of Crisis
leading up to it these are comparable to
five or 10e storms Regulators who had
successfully dealt with the smaller sto
storms were less successful when they
applied the same methods to the 100-year
storms these General remarks prepare the
ground for a specific
hypothesis uh I put forward or have put
forward to explain the recent financial
crisis it's not derived from my theory
of bubbles by deductive logic
nevertheless the two of them stand or
fall together so here it
goes I contend that the puncturing of
the subprime bubble in 2007 set off the
explosion of a Super Bubble much as an
ordinary bomb sets off a nuclear
explosion the housing bubble in the
United States was the most common kind
it distinguished only by the widespread
use of collateralized debt obligations
and other synthetic instruments behind
this ordinary bubble there was a much
larger Super Bubble growing over a
longer period of time which was much
more
peculiar the prevailing Trend in this
Super Bubble was the ever increasing use
of credit and leverage the prevailing
misconception was the belief that
financial markets are
self-correcting and should be left to
their own devices President Reagan
called it the magic of the marketplace
and I call it Market fundament
mentalism it became the dominant Creed
in the
1980s when Ronald Reagan was President
of the United States and Margaret thater
was prime minister of the United
Kingdom what made the Super Bubble so
peculiar was the role that financial
crisis played in making it grow since
the belief that markets could be safe to
left to their own devices was false the
Super Bubble gave rise to a series of
financial
crisis the first and most serious was
the international banking crisis of
1982 this was followed by many other
crises the most notable being the
portfolio Insurance debacle in October
1987 the Savings and Loan crisis that
unfolded in various episodes
between 1989 and
1994 the Emerging Market crisis of 1997
98 and the bursting of the internet
bubble in
2000 each time a financial crisis
occurred the author the authorities
intervened merged away or otherwise took
care of the Fall failing financial
institutions and applied mon and fiscal
stimulus to protect the
economy these measures reinforced the
prevailing trend of ever increasing
credit and leverage but as long as they
worked they also reinforced the
prevailing misconception that markets
can be safely left to their own
devices that was a
misconception because it was the
intervention of the authorities that
saved the system nevertheless these
crisis served as successful tests of a
false belief and as such they inflated
the Super Bubble even
further eventually the credit expansion
became
unsustainable and the Super Bubble
exploded the collapse of the subprime
mortgage market led to the collapse of
one market after another in quick
succession
because they were all
interconnected the firewalls having been
removed by
deregulation that's what distinguished
this financial crisis from all those
that preceded it those were successful
tests that reinforced the process the
subam crises of 2007 constituted the
Turning
Point the collapse then reached this
climax with the bank csy of Leman
Brothers which precipitated the large
scale intervention of the financial
authorities it's characteristic of my
boom buas model that it can't predict in
advance whether a test will be
successful or not this holds for
ordinary Bubbles as well as the Super
Bubble I personally thought that the
Emerging Market crisis of 1996 7 98
would constitute the turning point for
the Super Bubble but I was wrong the
authorities managed to save the system
and the Super Bubble continued
growing that made the bust that
eventually came in 2008 all the more
devastating after the bankruptcy of lean
Brothers on September 15
2008 the the financial markets had to be
put on artificial life support this was
a shock not only for the financial
sector but also for the real economy
international trade was particularly
badly hit but the artificial life
support worked and financial markets
stabilized the economy gradually revived
a year later the whole episode feels
like a bad dream
and people would like to forget it there
is a widespread desire to treat the
crisis as just another crisis and return
to business as usual but reality is
unlikely to oblige the system is
actually broken and needs to be
fixed my analysis offers some worthwhile
Clues to the kind of regulatory reform
that's
needed first and foremost since markets
are Bubble prone the financial
authorities have to accept
responsibility for preventing bubbles
from growing too big Alan Greenspan and
others have expressly refused to accept
that
responsibility if markets can't
recognize bubbles Greenspan asserted
neither can and
regulators and he was right nevertheless
the financial authorities have to accept
the assignment knowing full well that
they will not be able to meet it without
making
mistakes they will however have the
benefit of receiving feedback from the
markets which will tell them whether
they have done too much or too little
they can then correct their
mistakes second
in order to control asset bubbles it's
not enough to control the money supply
you must also control the availability
of credit this can be done by using only
monetary tools you must also use credit
controls the best known tools are margin
requirements and minimum Capital
requirements currently they are fixed
irrespective of the market mood because
markets are not supposed to have moods
yet they do and the financial
authorities need to vary margin and
minimum Capital requirements in order to
control asset
bubbles Regulators may also have to
invent new tools or revive ones that
have fallen into disuse for instance in
my early days in finance many years ago
central banks used to instruct
commercial Banks to limit their lending
to a particular sector of the economy
such as real estate or Consumer loans
because they felt that the sector was
overheating Market
fundamentalists consider that crash
interference with the market mechanism
but they are wrong now central banks
used to do it we had no financial crisis
to speak of the Chinese authorities do
it today and they have much better
control over the banking system than we
do the deposits that commercial banks
have to maintain at the Central Bank
were increased 17 times in China during
the boom and when the authorities revers
course the banks obeyed them with
electricity
or consider the internet boom Alan
Greenspan recognized it quite early when
he spoke about irrational exuberance in
1996 but apart from his famous speech he
did nothing to avert it he felt that
reducing the money supply would have
been too blunt an instrument to use and
he was right but he could have asked the
SEC to put a freeze on new share issues
because the internet boom was fueled by
Equity leveraging he didn't because that
would have violated his Market
fundamentalist
principles
third since markets are potentially
unstable there are systemic risks in
addition to the risks affecting
individual Market
participants participants May ignore
these systemic risks in the belief that
they can always dispose of their
positions to someone else but Regulators
can't ignore them because if too many
participants are on the same side the
positions can't be liquidated without
creating a
discontinuity or a collap or a a
collapse um they have to monitor the
positions of the particip partipants in
order to detect potential
imbalances that means that the positions
of all major Mar participants including
hedge funds uh and Sovereign wealth
funds need to be
monitored uh certain derivatives like
credit default swaps and knockout
options are particularly prone to create
hidden
imbalances therefore they must be
regulated and if appropriate restrict Ed
or
forbidden the issuing of synthetic
Securities needs to be subject to
regulatory approval just as ordinary
Securities
are
fourth we must recognize that financial
markets evolve in a on directional
nonreversible
manner the financial authorities in
carrying out their duty of preventing
the system from collapsing have extended
an implicit guarantee to all
institutions that are too big to fail
now they can't withdraw that guarantee
as long as there are institutions that
are too big to fail therefore they must
impose
regulations that will ensure that the
guarantee will not be
invoked too big to fail Banks must use
less leverage and accept various
restrictions on how they invest the
depositor's money deposits should not be
used to finance proprietary
trading but Regulators have to go even
further they must regulate the
compensation packages of proprietary
traders to ensure that risks and rewards
are properly aligned this may push
proprietary Traders out of banks into
hedge funds
where they properly
belong just as oil tankers are
compartmentalized in order to keep them
stable there ought to be firewalls
between different markets it's probably
impractical to uh separate Investment
Banking from Commercial Banking as the
glass SLE Act of 1933 did but there have
to be internal compartments keeping
proprietary trade in various markets
separate from each others each other in
order to prevent
contagion some banks that have come to
occupy Quine monopolistic positions may
have to be broken up finally the Basel
Accords made a mistake when they gave
Securities held by Banks substantially
lower risk ratings than regular loans
they ignored the systemic risks attached
to concentrated positions in
Securities this was an important factor
aggravating the crisis it has to be
corrected by raising the risk ratings of
Securities held by Banks and that will
probably discourage the securitization
of of
loans all these measures will reduce the
profitability and average of
banks this raises an interesting
question as to
timing this is not the right time to
enact permanent reforms the financial
system and the economy are very far from
equilibrium and they can't be brought
back to near equilibrium conditions by a
straightforward corrective move just as
when a car is kidding you must first
turn the wheel in the direction of the
skid before you uh correct the car what
makes what needs to be done in the short
term was exactly the opposite of what is
needed in the long term first the credit
that evaporated had to be replaced by
using the only source of credit that
remained credible namely the state and
that meant increasing the national debt
and extending the monetary base as the
economy stabilizes you must then shrink
the monetary base as fast as credit
revises otherwise
deflation will will be replaced by the
Spectre of inflation we are still in the
first phase of this delicate
maneuver the banks are in the process of
ear earning their way out of a hole to
reduce their profitability now would be
directly
counterproductive regulat reform has to
await the second phase when the money
supply needs to be brought under control
and it needs to be carefully faced in so
as not to disrupt the recovery but we
can't afford to forget about
it uh you you have seen that my
interpretation of financial markets uh
call it the theory of reflexivity is
very different from the efficient market
hypothesis strictly speaking neither
theory is falsifiable by Poppa's
standards I predicted the bursting of
the Super Bubble in
1998 I was wrong then so am I right now
and some proponents of the efficient
market hypothesis are still defending it
in the face of all the evidence still
there is a widespread feeling that we
need a new paradigm and I contend that
my theory provides a better explanation
than the available
Alternatives behavioral economics which
is gaining increased recognition deals
with only one half of
reflexivity the misinterpretations of
reality but doesn't study the pathways
by which mispricing can change uh the
fundamentals I realize that my theory of
financial markets is still very
rudimentary and needs a lot more
development the the pathways by which uh
the the U Mis mispricing can affect the
fundamentals uh need a lot more study
obviously I can't do it on my own so I
may have been premature in putting
forward my theory as the new paradigm
but the efficient market hypothesis has
certainly proved
inadequate that has been the entire
edifice of global financial markets that
has been erected on the false premise
that markets can be left to their own
devices
has to be rebuilt from the ground
up and that concludes my today's lecture
but I would like to also want to use
this occasion to make an
announcement I have decided to sponsor
an Institute for New Economic thinking
IET for short it will be a major
institution fostering research workshops
and curricula that will develop an
alternative to the prevailing Paradigm I
have committed $50 million over 10 years
and I hope other others will
join I also hope that reflexivity will
one of will be one of the concepts that
will be explored but clearly it should
not be the only one I recognize the
potential conflict between being a
protagonist and a financial sponsor at
the same time to protect against it I
want to erect a Chinese wall between me
and The Institute to this end I will
extend my financial support through the
central European University and I will
not personally participate in inet the
jury will be expressly instructed to
encourage other Alternatives behind
besides the theory of ref
flexibity the plan is to launch inet at
a workshop on the lessons of the
financial crisis at Kings College
Cambridge on April 10th and 11th and I
hope that the new economic thinking will
find a home here at the
ceu thank you very much