there is a deep-seated
conflict between capitalism and the open
Society I want to start with that rather
striking quotation from George soros's
extremely rich and provocative talk to
let those words reverberate once again
through the
hall uh in their Clarity but also in
their radicalism we're standing here in
budapes almost precisely 20 years after
the fall of the Berlin
Wall uh and I remember vividly that time
20 years ago when the talk in the United
States was not only about the
inevitability of capitalism and
democracy because those two go obviously
hand inand but the Assumption and the
argument uh that the combination of
those two systems if you will political
and economic constituted the end of
History to use the title of the famous
essay by Francis fukiyama fukiyama was
arguing uh uh borrowing ideas from Kev
and Hegel uh that the fall of the wall
beckoned a new age in which capitalism
and democracy working hand in hand would
essentially take over the world well we
know that history didn't end uh we know
about the Balkans Rwanda the Gulf War
the Iraq wall War the there's been a
great deal of history since then but it
is striking uh to find in this place uh
uh expressed by a key figure in World
capitalism and World Finance the notion
that democracy and the open Society are
as they exist today and compatible I
want to uh seize on my rights as
moderator and reconceive this question a
little bit as a reporter as well in
terms of power power versus the open
Society I was reminded thinking as
George spoke uh of a time in 1987 when I
was covering the Haitian election which
was supposed to bring the transition of
democracy to Haiti after a long
dictatorship and turned out to be a
bloody disaster in which the people with
power confronted the challenge of all of
these people standing there ready to
vote by sending gunmen uh to murder them
murdering a couple of hundred of them as
it turned out I remember thinking at the
time that our vision of democracy is at
its heart a kind of beautiful myth it
proposes that on one sacred day everyone
in the society the powerless and the
powerful the poor and the wealthy stand
together with exactly the same amount of
power they have the power of one one
vote but of course that day does not
change power relations within a society
in Haiti the powerful pay gunmen
wielding ues and machetes to go and kill
voters in the United States the powerful
pay lobbyists to Lobby Congress pay
admen to make
advertisements uh pay political
candidates uh to run their campaigns um
trying to press down power in one place
is like pressing down on water in a lake
it rises somewhere else it seems to me
then that the heart of this problem has
to do with our conception of the open
Society particularly as George has set
it out to you today and in the previous
lectures and I want to press him a
little bit on this issue because the
open Society we're talking about which
he said is supposed to or exists to
promote the public good in fact was not
set up that way uh the framers the
famous framers of the Constitution put
together a system whose major function
was to divide government Power Balance
it one part against the other and to try
to clear a private space in which
government power could not dominate a
good example is the famous First
Amendment we've heard today about
brainwashing about the manipulation of
the public the use of the press to do
that we all know how this has happened
and is happening in the United States
the fact is though when we look at the
famous First Amendment what do we find
we find no right to truth we find uh no
right to Enlightenment uh we find no
right to know although we hear that
phrase used often the full text of the
First Amendment as regards freedom of of
the press reads as follows Congress
shall make no law abridging the freedom
of the press that is it is a limitation
on government Vis A the press it says
nothing about private forces uh and
indeed the Press is a collection of
private institutions moneymaking
institutions that can indeed be
manipulated it also says nothing about
restraining private power from
influencing politics through elections
so I would say today and I'd like to ask
George about this
isn't our problem really doesn't our
problem really have to do with
renovating our open society as it exists
uh in ways that will conceive of it less
as a neutral arbitrator and more of an
active power trying to assure what
George called the common good now this
may sound like a radical proposal in
fact we've had a hundred years of
fighting over precisely this issue
within the United States uh one example
boring as it is is campaign Finance
reform George said it's very and TR
rightly said it's extremely expensive to
get elected elected officials uh feel
that they uh owe falty to those who paid
for their uh campaigns this is obviously
true but in fact there's nothing
inherently expensive about getting
elected 70% of the cost of running for
office is buying television time the
Airways belong to the public the
government could has absolutely the
right to require although it can't limit
according to the Supreme Court it can't
limit what private agents give to
candidates it can require the airwaves
the broadcast and cable networks to give
space for free to candidates that is
something absolutely conceivable
absolutely doable it can also when it
comes when we talk about the Press can
not only ensure uh public access to the
airwaves public broadcasting and so on
it can require a certain degree of TR
truthtellah and I say this not as an
active proposal but as a matter of
History uh Franklin Roosevelt of course
in his regulation of broadcasting back
in the 30s then radio but it was
inherited by the television industry uh
imposed a fairness Doctrine um uh which
essentially said both sides at least uh
need to be heard he also imposed a
public interest requirement each year
the television networks had to uh make a
case to the licensing board that they
had served the public interest um this
was usually taken to mean that the uh
news divisions of broadcast networks
would be protected from the profit
motive which is to say they were lost
leaders uh they spent a great deal of
money they did it the networks thought
well we have to do this to serve the
public interest now this was a real
thing that actually expired in real time
uh this expired under the Reagan
administ Administration um so these
things uh could very easily be put back
into effect uh there are a lot of other
obvious proposals we could make in which
the open society would become an
affirmative supporter uh of the common
good and a counterveiling
force uh to Market power um let me say
my time is short just make a couple of
uh a couple of brief um other points um
well let me make a final point which is
this uh George has suggested uh that
people need to divide their private
interests uh from their political
interests um He suggests he offers
himself as an example and it's a very
Vivid one um I would suggest though that
the proposal that we produce many many
George soros's and have a kind of Truth
telling Squad is going to be a very
difficult thing to do because he's an
unusual a very unusual person
uh I also think uh that trying to
establish a group of of of Truth tellers
uh compared yesterday to a a platonic
idea that is we're talking about
Guardians of the public good who would
be trained um uh to observe to critique
and to lead the Public Public will not
in the end be a practical idea I think
the AL the what and I will be interested
to hear his views of this what needs to
be done as a program of reformation
of the original conception of an open
Society uh and many of these proposals
are absolutely conceivable absolutely
doable President Obama has talked about
for example bringing back the fairness
Doctrine there's a great deal of
opposition to it and one should observe
that the very forces that you've
detailed so well uh and so richly in
your talk militate against the very
reforms that I am suggesting I
understand that nonetheless uh I am
optimistic about it and I would ask you
whether we shouldn't really be looking
for systemic reform uh more than uh
private reform thank
you I think we should go to um to ask
them to comment and we can go after I
will indeed okay uh George suggests that
we we ask uh the students and faculty at
Fudan University in Shanghai uh to begin
with their comments and so I say hello
to our friends in Shanghai and welcome
them uh invite them to ask the first
question okay hello from F University
Shanghai uh thanks a lot for this uh
fancinating uh lecture and I'm the local
uh facilitator and we already have three
questions two from faculty members and
one from student now now I am handing it
over to the first participant
oh okay yeah hello judge I'm wishing
leave from school of Economics I me to
you this uh
uh okay uh just one one questions uh one
question in the conclusion you said I
believe that if more people separated
their rule as political participants
from their rule of Market the
partipate the American democracy will
function better I I I I agree with your
your standpoint but uh I just wonder one
question that's uh if I'm not
misunderstand what you you
say if uh uh without the the re
representative democracy or in James be
J in the the constitu Democracy the
separation of two rules you proposed
could be implmented or not that's you
know just L that two rules is closely
linked together that's all the questions
of Chinese Society faced today that's my
question thank
you I I
believe he asked you got the question
about the separation of two worlds yes
it's a very interesting question you
might restate it for the audience uh uh
I for once I understood it very
well that I suggest separating the two
roles how how could that how should that
apply in
China uh where you don't have a
representative uh democracy and I think
it's a very very interesting question
and it's much more difficult I think to
apply it in in China because China is a
very efficient
system of decision making but it is
characterized by a much greater
political influence over uh economic
decisions that effectively investment
decisions are mainly Guided by uh
political considerations rather than by
the profit motive um and
uh it it is in many ways efficient but
the the problem then of uh of
using uh personally or making decisions
for personal interest rather than the
public interest is is very great the
Temptation and and of course uh
corruption is the the the big uh uh
factor in in China that limits uh the
success of the Chinese uh uh uh model uh
and and uh
uh it's it's really the the main the
main problem uh and I think that that
actually moving towards a more open
Society more open Society uh and giving
the people uh more uh uh uh rights to
stand up and to to uh Express their
views uh and establishing proper
channels establishing the rule of law
rather than the rule of
men uh is the direction in which China
needs to go in order to to actually to
improve the efficiency of investment
because it's remarkable how low the rate
of return on investment in China is it's
actually quite amazing given China's
success uh uh but then more than 50% of
the G&amp;P actually goes into investment
but the rate of return on that
investment is very
low given uh if you conceive of private
interests uh having a determining effect
on public policy as corruption uh if we
Define it that way uh is China more
corrupt in the United
States
uh I would say that corruption is
endemic in in the system in in in in in
in the United States uh it's really
mainly in the
political uh
Arena that the the uh uh lobbying and
and and uh uh special interests
uh uh influencing the regulations that
are enacted that's where mainly the
Distortion comes into play whereas in
China it pervades the economic system
itself uh why don't we go to our second
question from Fudan
University Mr solos now we have the
second question hello this is up a
student student from un fan University
my question would be um agencies and
representatives somehow are made up and
most of the times of Elites and at the
same time your suggesting SE the
separation of the roles of the so
participants in the politics and
participants in the market was somehow
sent a negative message to those
Elites and which somehow indicated by
the history that we're going to see more
catastrophic effects as predicted Maybe
we would see more financial meltdowns in
the future so my question would be how
effect do you think your suggestion the
separation of roles would play in the
future thank you could you just repeat
the question I I think it's a question
about whether the separation of public
and private roles that you suggested
would play a distinctly negative role on
the elites and would have uh a negative
effect on their functioning as economic
agents that's how the he formed uh he
formed the question if you if you
separate it it will have a NE negative
effect on on Elites and playing their
role as economic uh agents of the
private
sector um I I I don't understand the
question
uh it doesn't make sense to me it could
be reconceived as do do the elites need
Market
fundamentalism uh and their influence on
the public sector uh to function
profitably they must they must be
motivated by self-interest in in order
to be making the rules I I don't see
that I think that that in a certainly in
a well functioning uh democracy that
that has not been the case well let me
put it in a different form if if what
your vision that you set out was inacted
would we be would we have as one final
result a more equal distribution of
wealth
um well I think that depends on on
the basically on the will of the the
electorate uh um well you mentioned the
estate tax which uh was abolished even
though it was absolutely contrary to the
interest of 99% of the population the
implication being If people really
understood what it involved embol it
would you are right actually
given the the influence of Market
fundamentalism uh the success of Market
fundamentalism uh In America which has
really kind of uh uh um skewed uh public
opinion uh against the their own
interest uh as the I quoted the state
that text is a a very good example uh
certainly if you eliminated that and it
then I think the public interest would
be better served and presumably it would
lead to
a a u a more equal distribution of
wealth but but I don't want to prejudge
it because let's say I happen to be in
that camp politically that that would
favor a more equal uh uh a distribution
but I don't want to impose my judgment
and claim it that that's how open
Society has to be I think it that is
really up to the people in the in in in
the Democracy concerned to make that
decision I I would press you just a
little on that before going back to
Fudan because isn't that a bit of an
imposed neutrality I mean really what
you're saying is that the public
interest should be more equitably
represented uh the broader public
interest and I would I think that would
suggest uh that the great concentrations
of wealth we've seen in recent years
would to some extent be reversed no
well look again the the the
evidence points points are that that the
the the uh differences in income have
tremendously increased in the last 25
years when Market fundamentalism has
become the dominant
greed uh and in fact the average has not
benefited it it's it's really the top
that uh one or 2% of the population that
gathered all the extra revenues that
came from benefit so that's and
therefore if you reversed it presumably
it would go the other way but I still
don't think I just don't want to I agree
with that argument but I don't want to
to pose that as sort of the the the open
Society because I would be prejudging it
which is not appropriate we'll go back
now to Fang University in Shanghai third
question okay thank you very much and
the third question from myself uh my
name is p associate professor in sko
management fan University I think the
title of the lecture is ISM versus open
society and one of the central me
messages con conveyed from this lecture
seems that the rise of Market
fundamentalism is a major threat to open
Society so my question is what's the
relationship between capitalism and
Market fundamentalism and putting
another way uh under what conditions
under what circumstances the roid will
uh Mark fundamentalism will develop and
even flourish in a capitalist Society
thank you could you repeat that well I
thought he was getting and I may have
misunderstood uh to the fact that
capitalism doesn't necessarily need
democracy as a partner um that is what I
understood the beginning of the question
meant uh that in fact and he is coming
of course from Shanghai uh one of the
most powerful cities in a country that
is both vividly capitalist and NE
non-democratic
uh but I afraid I didn't understand the
very last line of the question maybe
maybe you could repeat it I simply
didn't understand what you said the last
line just the last line Market Market
fundamentalism may not uh develop quite
fastly in uh capitalist Society because
uh uh Market fundamentalism is not equal
to capitalism so uh but you in the
lecture you say that in in in in the
United States Market fundamentalism even
flourish over the last several decades
uh in such a particular capitalist
Society so my question is under what
conditions or under what circumstances
Market fundament mentalism will develop
a flourish in a capitalist Society after
under under what situations does Market
fundamentalism flourish in capitalist
societies relationship between
capitalism and Market fundamentalism how
are they
different look thank you yeah thank you
very much for the
question it's a very good question uh I
don't think that market
fundamentalism has served capitalism or
or even the the people who espouse that
philosophy or ideology uh very well
because as as I tried to argue in my
previous uh uh uh lectures it is it has
been responsible for the Super Bubble
which burst with with with tremendous
damage to the American uh
economy uh and um I think that for
instance right now after the bursting of
the bubble when the um Financial system
is being allowed to earn its way out of
a hole to re re rebuild its capital
through hidden
subsidies um uh by keeping making U uh
uh um Capital available financing
available from the central bank as zero
cost when you can then invest Banks can
invest it with no risk whatsoever into
government bonds earning 3 and a half%
and not actually requiring uh uh uh any
uh uh uh Capital reserves to do that so
they are being
effectively given over a a hidden
subsidy and at the same time the banks
are now uh paying very large Bon bonuses
to their uh uh employees who are
supposed to be generating those earnings
by taking risks successfully in know
words making the right decisions here
they they are just benefiting from a
hidden subsidy and I think it's a big
mistake for them actually to use that
money in that way because it generates
public resentment so I think it's a very
uh shortsighted view uh on the part of
of of uh the mar Market
fundamentalists to persist in in in in
the putting their their uh private
interests ahead of the public interest
I'd like to to thank our uh participants
at Fudan University back later maybe we
will come back at the end we'll throw uh
the questions now uh open to the floor
and as we um reach one I'm going to ask
you one quick question to bridge bridge
this which is the policy that you just
identified that the Obama regime has or
the ex Administration excuse me has
pursued um uh was it the result of too
much private interest on public policy
did they make this decision as a result
of the influence of capital or uh did
they simply not know how to uh uh take
the other course that you described well
I think there two elements uh uh one
that that um uh they basically judged it
was a it was a conscious political
decision because there was this
alternative you for Simplicity sake you
may call it the the the Scandinavian
solution and the Japanese solution
because the Scandinavians
effectively uh uh nationalized their
Banks
temporarily and they they they got out
of a crisis pretty fast and of course
denationalize the banks whereas the
Japanese uh supported their banking
system through hidden subsidies and
basically the Obama
Administration uh decided to go the
Japanese uh route and that was partly I
think a conscious decision uh to that
politically it would be unacceptable
that in fact this anti-government
uh uh sentiment in and tradition in
America is too strong for them to go
against it um and secondly I think it in
a way the the there was a certain
sequence uh the crisis hit the previous
administration took this road uh um of
indir sub CES and they
didn't they weren't prepared with the
alternative so uh uh continuity dragged
them in so partly it was deliberate and
partly it was just the the shortness of
time or time pressure that led to that
and partly out of not wanting to oppose
the ideological beliefs of the American
and of course Obama wanted to be the
Great uniter and did not want to have
sort of
U impose a start off by being too
critical of what went be before and I
think that was a mistake because you
have had 25 years of
accumulated uh uh excess that came home
to roost uh but by claiming to arrest
the decline he has actually now taking
possession and there is an aru an
argument for doing the most the heaviest
lifting politically at the beginning
when you have the greatest political
Capital right um uh
questions um sir over there wait for the
microphone please and tell us your name
my name is George copit and I'm a
chairman of the fiscal Council in the
Republic of Hungary and I also lecture
at your University Central European
University in Budapest first of all I
would like to start by thanking George
choros for an extremely stimulating and
thought-provoking uh uh
presentation and I and then thereafter I
would like to just uh take a little bit
of an issue with your observation of the
US uh agency problem through the last 50
years or the last 100 years there was a
an observer of the US Senate in the
early I don't remember who it was manen
or who it was who uh observed that the
price of a senator in the US was about
$1,000 of course it was much more
today's prices than than what it is
today right but anyway uh there was
certainly a lot of agency problem uh in
the early part and in the course of the
I don't think that it's we are any uh
less moral uh or less corrupt Society
today as at the beginning of the century
but we could go on with that in any case
a you refer to the fact that you need
checks and balances in fact a lot of
institutional uh framework made up of a
lot of uh Watchdogs to watch over the
honesty of government and certainly in
the US there has been a lot of
Institutions created since that time in
the course of even the last 50 years but
going further back back the Federal
Trade Commission Securities and Exchange
Commission uh
1975 the Congressional budget office and
then of course even before the general
Accounting Office which then became the
general accountability office all of
this to serve precisely the purpose that
you have described in fact we in Hungary
and myself I'm heading a very new
institution which is more or less
patterned after the Congressional budget
office to keep the government honest in
fiscal policy but my question really is
looking forward a little bit and drawing
from already some of your remarks today
and elsewhere in media what sort of
Institutions do you think would really
uh serve the US and of course we could
extend that onto Europe what sort of
Institutions would really serve uh this
extremely useful purpose of watching
over the financial system if you could
it's it's what institutions what sort of
Institutions would serve the purpose of
watching over the financial institutions
look I I think that America actually has
all the institutions that it needs it
really has a wonderful Constitution that
in spite of a few uh maybe things where
it's maybe out of date uh uh like the
first amendment stands in the way of uh
uh of uh uh controlling uh uh spending
on elections and things like that uh
which the founding fathers didn't
anticipate couldn't anticipate 200 years
uh in advance so there are a few things
like that but on the whole the
institutions are really there uh it's
really the
values that I think have gotten skewed
and and distorted through this the the
Triumph of Market
fundamentalism and the and I've pointed
out the contradictions the the internal
contradictions in in those values so I
hold values responsible not institutions
I think we've got the institutions we
did in contrast let's say to countries
in Eastern Europe which are relatively
Young and the institutions are not
strong enough questions yes
sir there's the microphone
after I'm Fred branman I'm I'm a writer
I used to work with Excuse me with folks
Like Larry Summers and Paul Krugman and
so forth and concluded then and and have
seen nothing to uh change it sense that
that and I'm curious what you think of
this that we've ventured a phase of late
late capitalism High debts uncompetitive
industry uh major financial institutions
which no longer serve the the public
interest which make our previous
economic theories that worked in the
past irrelevant today fundamentally and
that America cannot grow uh as it's
grown in the past and that therefore um
we really have no choice but but to
start thinking about accepting that fact
accepting that the real model for
America the future has to be a European
style welfare state if it can't grow as
it has in the past and if it's not going
to fall apart into war in camps uh that
we need to start promoting values of at
least voluntary Simplicity if not um
just accepting that we're all going to
have to live more simply uh we are going
to have to have a major redistribution
of wealth and fundamentally change the
very image of where we're heading rather
than as I think we are now doing hoping
to recover the past
uh one last comment on that is I think
when you really look at the level of
debt that we've taken out and the fact
that we simply can't repay it under any
conceivable scenario for the next 10 or
20 years without a very robust set of
industries that are bringing New Wealth
into America which we can't see and we
think of what must be done to solve
global warming uh and to deal with an
aging uh Baby Boom generation that's
going to eat up an increasing uh uh
amount of or need an increasing amount
of entitlement
I wonder what you think of this notion
that we really have to stop Clos with
the past except we're in a late
capitalist phase and start thinking of
totally new solutions to which the old
Solutions are relevant thank I I think
we get the idea are we in a late
capitalist phase that can only be
confronted with a European welfare style
system and a major redistribution of
wealth no look that's your view uh uh
but it's not it's not necessarily
the the the view in
America uh and uh to to to say
that I mean you're right in the sense
that that the
European welfare state has actually uh
weathered this storm uh uh very well
compared to the United States uh and
while people particularly in America uh
used to be very critical of the welfare
state and the relatively low rate of of
of growth me as measured in in
GNP uh
[Music]
um
effectively uh there has been a payoff
because the automatic stabilizers have
actually really done done that job job
uh and hopefully this will influence
American opinion uh looking forward but
I as I say I think you are sort of uh
seeking to impose your views on America
and I don't don't think that's a
practical proposition uh next question
is in the second row here can you bring
the microphone
please and then and then back there
thank you
Mr Shores in the framework of an open
Society how do we analyze Mr Obama's
health program
proposition uh how would you analyze
President Obama's health proposition
particularly with uh respect to the
prosperity and problems in the in the
economy well I I'm I've been very I've
been quite distressed uh by by the
debate uh because the the
unfortunately the health system proposed
by
Obama uh really is not designed uh uh to
provide Health it's designed to pay for
procedures and it encourages then
procedures not preservation or uh
promotion of Health uh so it's
fundamentally flawed and I have no doubt
that what you need is is a National
Health Service a single provider because
only a single provider can uh be
concerned about prevention as distinct
from treating uh uh uh disease uh but
that is a non-starter as I said in my
lecture this is absolutely National
Health
socialism is is is has been uh
outlawed in in America uh I think I find
that rather distressing may I ask a
followup here why if indeed everyone is
insured and if it's in the interest of
health insurance companies since they
can't reject people when they're sick to
have them healthier because they will
then spend less money curing them why
canot the system Obama is uh now
champing also
Value Health because because the the
people can move from one to provider to
another so you don't have the if you
have one
provider then the
provider is concerned about having fewer
procedures uh
um in if you have many providers you
don't have the same situation so I I
think quite a apart from the fact also
that having the the U uh insurance
companies uh uh compete with each other
the only way they can improve their
profits is actually by denying uh
benefits so you've got the wrong
incentives built into the system okay
back
there my name is ulia V and I'm a
journalist a Hungarian journalist and if
you don't mind uh I stay a little bit in
this country uh even if we have 20 years
of so-called democracy and capitalism we
are beginners and therefore my question
might be naive but uh do you think there
is
anybody uh maybe you are the only one I
think who could
convince uh people who are playing role
in the market not to in be influenced by
politics or or people who are playing a
role in politics not to try to influence
the market I agree with Mr Danner that
George churos should be multiplied but
until he's not uh I doubt that there are
uh too many people who can be convinced
about uh the so-called open Society uh
this phenomenon we are waiting for so
much thank you how do you convince
people uh given that there aren't you
can't multiply George Soros how do you
convince people to separate their
private interests and their public
interest well by giving a lecture like
this is everybody in the room
convinced is is that the answer Moral
Moral suasion that is what
else I mean hope hopefully arguments can
still convince people
we we hope that is the case uh let's see
uh gentleman in the front here there was
people there yes and we'll go we'll go
over to the side
next Howard Robinson central European
University and it's really a followup on
the last question you emphasized as it
were the division within individuals but
a certain kind of platonism and
oldfashioned tourism also had that a
division between certain classes of
person so in Disraeli Cil for example
you have a civilized commercial Society
because the aristocracy the church and
the monarchy don't have Direct
commercial values in England this was
passed on through the public schools to
the middle class and the professions and
with keynesianism to the state sector is
there any way of restoring not merely
hoping people will be schizophrenically
honest but having whole sectors of
society who don't from moment to moment
make all their decisions on Commercial
basis Mrs Thatcher destroyed that in
Britain how can we restore
that how can can we restore uh parts of
society like the church the aristocracy
that have built built into their
Traditions a societal responsibility
divorced from pursuit of gain and
pursuit of wealth yeah I mean I don't
believe that you can you know uh uh this
uh trap of uh of idealizing the past uh
I try to resist it I can't totally
resist it uh because I see a deterior
ation in our values uh but I think we
need
to re reconstitute it in in some new
form and not hug back to to to the past
it was
actually I think the case of British
democracy the
um the aristocracy played a very
positive uh role but that was that
particular
historic situation so I think we need to
create a new one and I think it's not
impossible on this side yes right
there Ellen Hume from ceu I wanted to go
back to the question that we got from
China which I don't think was fully
recognized which is why is Market
fundamentalism so powerful in the states
how did it become the the the current
philosophy that so strong wrong and
could there be circumstances that it
might happen for example in China as
well how do we look for the Hallmarks
that create this Market fundamentalism
that you find so negative no look I I
tried to explain in my lecture
that the main I think the main power of
maret fundamentalism has been the very
well finan financed propaganda
uh uh and in fact uh there's been U some
studies that showed how seven
foundations played a very big role in
spreading the market values to areas
where they don't belong as for instance
uh law and economics and uh there a
there a typical example that was
basically
introduced uh uh by Financial uh
support for that approach uh so I I
think that's that is in my opinion why
it has been so successful and I think
that this moment when it has so
conspicuously uh done so much damage uh
because of its
instability uh um is the moment to bring
home that it has in fact failed and we
have to abandon it I I think it is worth
pointing out that this was in a sense a
premeditated decision brought about by
the Powell memo and certain other things
by think tanks to spread this um one
should also mention I think the the high
inflation and terrible economic
situation at the end of The Carter
Administration which Le led the ground
for the acceptance of this sort of uh
radical view of of capitalism yeah well
the the inflation of the S of the 70s
has had uh the effect of discrediting
Keynesian
economics and allowing the monetarist
and and and efficient market hypothesis
Etc to come to the
four yes uh on yes
sir then we'll go to the I'm G Kasper
the trustee
uh uh George I would like to comment on
your last point and really disagree with
you to a very large extent yes there
were those foundations Olan and so on uh
that gave money to
universities but I think that is
actually a very misleading understanding
of what really happened and uh Robert
skidelsky in a new book that he just
published weeks ago uh is taking a
difference intake he is saying it's
really the power of ideas and lots of
the ideas we now associate with The
Chicago School were very powerful many
of the participants remained ordinary
relatively poor in Gentile poverty to be
sure but relatively poor academics that
was never the issue but these ideas seem
to have a tremendous attraction because
they seem to work for a whole variety of
problems including the Assumption of uh
uh the rational consumer and so on now I
happen to agree with most of your
criticisms but I think the notion uh
that it is was a kind of conspiracy on
the part of belthy Foundations misleads
us completely yesterday there was
reference to the platonic uh uh Elites
and where you not going back to it well
the Dismal news is there are Elites
there are platonic Elites and it could
be the Chicago School of economics and
so we could indeed go in totally
undesirable directions and we should uh
for stall that and since I do have the
not the if not the podium the microphone
I would like to go back uh to the
earlier question about
institutions I really do I do believe
what you are doing this lecture uh
preaching as it were is very important
and needs to be done but in the end it
is only the quality of our institutions
and the engagement in these institutions
the journalists who are permanently uh
drumming and saying hey you're not doing
it right you are keeping information
from us and so on and so on that will
get us improvements I I I think hoping
for the day when the ordinary citizen
will
overcome uh self-interest and will act
only in the public interest assuming we
can Define it the public interest big
you are yourself are very reluctant
actually in many areas to Define what
the public interest is only then uh I
would put my trust in those Solutions
rather than in uh a big moral
reformation and that you know that
includes Hungary too I I will seize the
chance to self-interestedly put forward
the critiques because they follow
directly from what you said that I uh
put forward in my uh my remarks which is
are there not institutions that could be
encouraged aggressively uh to be
renovated in effect because many of them
already exist uh that can at least help
the moral suasion you're talking about
I'm talking about the fairness Doctrine
uh electoral reform uh limitation on
campaign spending public spending on
campaigns a lot of the problems you
pointed to do have uh conceivable
Solutions Beyond persuasion in the moral
realm undoubtedly there there are there
are reforms
certainly a campaign Finance reform is
very much needed but the the fact is
that you know every reform uh has some
flaw in it and I was a supporter of
campaign Finance
reform
um particular aspects of it and so on
but I also gave a grant to um the New
York
University Rance Center and I
said I would want you to study the
flaws the potential flaws in the reform
proposals that part of the grant was
actually never used in
was they didn't actually do a very good
job in I mean we have to recognize that
all our arrangements are flawed and this
is the Human Condition and of course you
are you're right that that Chicago
school had a
tremendous uh
intellectual power and and
influence
um but you see the a a school of thought
which basically said that government is
bad actually leads to bad government so
there is this
reflexive connection as well in other
words there are booms and busts
in in in in intellectual in intellectual
development so canes for instance had a
tremendous
Boom the
keynesians were did not have actually
the the subtlety of Mind of
canes uh just as Mark
didn't quite have you know Marxist
intelligence either who could could so
so uh kism got a little bit
overdone and and uh and basically KES
proposed his theory at a time of
depression when when the lack of demand
was the problem and therefore his
prescription uh uh involved public
expanding uh and he did not uh
propose uh anything much in the way of
arresting inflation had he lived in the
70s I confident he would have recognize
the problem of inflation it was inherent
in his general theory that that
equilibrium will not give you the
optimum that there are less than Optimum
uh uh Arrangements that can Prevail he
called them equilibria and of course
today even today we talk about multiple
equilibria which to my my mind means
that sometimes you're in disequilibrium
I call it
disequilibrium uh so I think he would
have dealt with with with with with
inflation but because he didn't
monetarism uh came back into Vogue
Milton Friedman uh was tremendous ly
influential uh and and actually that was
a Revival of the monetarist theory that
prevailed in the
1920s which then led to the great crash
was discredited by it so there has been
a little bit of a repetition in history
well and just the way the late 70s
discredited to some extent canes right
right thank you very much my name is
Cecilia bujer and I'm the Swedish
Ambassador here in
Hungary I think that my country is
possibly a good example of uh where you
have parted the uh Market sphere and the
political sphere as you call it uh and I
would personally argue that that's one
of the reasons why we have been
relatively prosperous over long period
of
time however we see almost the opposite
Trend in Sweden from your suggestion and
that is that we are having more Market
influence in the political square and uh
in some parts more uh political
influence in the market
sphere so my question to you would be
how do you Ensure uh an efficient use of
resources in the political sphere if you
don't have Market principles or Market
ideas uh guiding uh the use of public
funds and the other side is how do you
make sure that the market side or the
capitalistic side is taking
responsibility for public common uh
interests and goods if you do not have
political influence in this SAR and I'm
thinking about the environment and the
climate of course a very big question
thank you Ambassador um I'm reminded we
have four minutes left so if you can
begin to answer
that please don't misunder understand me
in being in any way opposed to markets I
think markets are really a wonderful
instrument for for allowing adjustments
allowing feedback in particular uh uh
very important that is neglected uh
uh
so actually I argued in my lecture for
the great for the minimum intervention
from government in in form of Regulation
and intervention in the economy one
should give whatever the markets can do
should be allowed to do it because they
they do it much much better than than
governments can then you you would do
less than than the swedes do presuma uh
well I don't want to go into the Swedish
situation because I don't know it well
enough but uh but um
uh it's
very markets have a role
but they they there are there's also a
need for political decisions and markets
are not designed to to make those social
choices it's markets are for exchange
among Market participants and there are
social needs and public goods and so on
which need to be provided by a political
process and generally as I argued in my
lecture uh um uh markets are actually
more efficient than the political
process therefore we should leave it to
them what they can do but to to claim
that they can do everything just because
they are more efficient is an
exaggeration that has cost us very deep
very dearly does anyone have a one-
sentence question we have uh we have two
minutes left I need your commitment to
one sentence yes sir you get the prize
Julius haran Central
University can you comment on the
relationship of Market fundamentalism
and the fall of communism because that
the relationship between Market
fundamentalism and the fall of Communism
one one well uh you know uh um the fall
of fall of disintegration of the Soviet
Empire was could be interpreted either
as the Triumph of capitalism or the
Triumph of open society and there were
these two approaches and
actually I I took it to be the victory
of open Society over close Society
others like VAV klous saw it as the
victory of capitalism
over uh of course I would argue my case
[Laughter]
[Applause]
[Music]
this is certainly the most Global
audience that we have had in the four
lectures to date and I want to
particularly thank our participants from
Fudan
University uh it's also been I think in
many ways our most
thought-provoking and debate provoking
lecture by our distinguished lecturer
and we are extremely grateful for that
tomorrow in his final lecture uh Mr stos
will bring together all the themes that
he has been exploring with us this week
and he will show the way forward from
our current enormous set of dilemas
crises and problems in many dimensions
so this will be an extraordinary moment
for us when we return to this Hall
tomorrow um I'm very grateful to our
moderator Mark Danner and once again I
invite you to join me in thanking George
Soros for inspiring and provoking us
with his thought and his thoughtfulness
[Applause]